{
  "topics": [
    {
      "topicName": "Mughal Empire",
      "subtopics": [
        {
          "subtopicName": "Akbar",
          "description": [
            "Akbar was the third Mughal emperor who reigned from 1556 to 1605.",
            "He expanded the empire and promoted religious tolerance.",
            "Akbar's policies and conquests helped to expand the Mughal Empire significantly.",
            "With wisdom and justice, he guided his reign, His legacy a testament to his might and his brain.",
            "A visionary ruler, Akbar's name will stand, A beacon of tolerance throughout the land."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "When did Akbar become the Mughal emperor?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1526", "1605", "1627"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "Akbar became emperor in 1556 after the death of his father, Humayun."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who is the father of Akbar?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Babur", "Sher Shah", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Humayun",
                  "explanation": "Humayun was Akbar's father and the second Mughal Emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When was the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1526", "1605", "1627"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "The Second Battle of Panipat occurred in 1556, marking Akbar's rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was defeated in the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": ["Hemu", "Babur", "Sher Shah", "Maharana Pratap"],
                  "answer": "Hemu",
                  "explanation": "Hemu was defeated by Akbar's forces in the Second Battle of Panipat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who abolished the religious tax Jaziya?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Aurangzeb", "Babur", "Humayun"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar abolished the religious tax Jaziya in 1564 as part of his policy of religious tolerance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When did Akbar capture Gujarat?",
                  "options": ["1572", "1556", "1605", "1526"],
                  "answer": "1572",
                  "explanation": "Akbar captured Gujarat in 1572 during his expansionist policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who built the city of Fatehpur Sikri?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Humayun", "Shah Jahan"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar commissioned the construction of Fatehpur Sikri, which served as the Mughal capital for a time."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the early name of Fatehpur Sikri?",
                  "options": [
                    "City of Sikri",
                    "City of Victory",
                    "City of Peace",
                    "City of Gold"
                  ],
                  "answer": "City of Sikri",
                  "explanation": "The early name of Fatehpur Sikri was City of Sikri before it was renamed to City of Victory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who built the Buland Darwaza?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Shah Jahan", "Babur", "Humayun"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "The Buland Darwaza, or 'Gate of Magnificence,' was built by Akbar to commemorate his victory over Gujarat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where is Ibadatkhana situated?",
                  "options": ["Fatehpur Sikri", "Agra Fort", "Delhi", "Lahore"],
                  "answer": "Fatehpur Sikri",
                  "explanation": "The Ibadatkhana, a prayer house and discussion hall, is located in Fatehpur Sikri, constructed by Akbar."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the first Englishman to reach India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ralph Fitch",
                    "William Hawkins",
                    "James Lancaster",
                    "Edward Terry"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ralph Fitch",
                  "explanation": "Ralph Fitch was the first Englishman to reach India during Akbar's reign and is considered a pioneer among English travelers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the name of the religion founded by Akbar?",
                  "options": ["Din-i-Ilahi", "Sikhism", "Hinduism", "Islam"],
                  "answer": "Din-i-Ilahi",
                  "explanation": "Din-i-Ilahi, or Divine Faith, was a syncretic religion founded by Akbar that sought to blend elements of various religions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the name of the calendar started by Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ilahi Calendar",
                    "Gregorian Calendar",
                    "Hijri Calendar",
                    "Bengali Calendar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ilahi Calendar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar introduced the Ilahi Calendar as part of his efforts to reform administrative practices."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which battle did Akbar defeat Maharana Pratap of Mewar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Haldighati",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Plassey",
                    "Battle of Talikota"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Haldighati",
                  "explanation": "Akbar defeated Maharana Pratap in the Battle of Haldighati in 1576."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where is the Haldighati mountain pass situated?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aravalli Hills, Rajasthan",
                    "Western Ghats, Maharashtra",
                    "Himalayas, Uttarakhand",
                    "Nilgiris, Tamil Nadu"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aravalli Hills, Rajasthan",
                  "explanation": "Haldighati is a mountain pass located in the Aravalli Hills in Rajasthan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the Mughal Emperor when the English East India Company was founded on December 31, 1600?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar was the Mughal Emperor when the English East India Company was founded in 1600."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where is the tomb of Akbar situated?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sikandra, near Agra",
                    "Delhi",
                    "Lahore",
                    "Jaipur"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sikandra, near Agra",
                  "explanation": "The tomb of Akbar is located in Sikandra, near Agra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the name of Akbar's military system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mansabdari system",
                    "Jagirdari system",
                    "Zamindari system",
                    "Iqta system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mansabdari system",
                  "explanation": "The Mansabdari system was a military and administrative system introduced by Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's revenue minister?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Todarmal",
                    "Birbal",
                    "Tansen",
                    "Abdul Rahim"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Raja Todarmal",
                  "explanation": "Raja Todarmal was Akbar's revenue minister and played a crucial role in reforming the revenue system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal Emperor built Agra Fort?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar is credited with the construction of the Agra Fort, which served as a major Mughal stronghold."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "‘Akbarnama’ and ‘Ain-i-Akbari’ are written by _____ ?",
                  "options": [
                    "Akbar",
                    "Ziauddin Barani",
                    "Abul Fazal",
                    "Abdul Qadir Badayuni"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abul Fazal",
                  "explanation": "'Akbarnama' and 'Ain-i-Akbari' are famous works written by Abul Fazal, who was Akbar's court historian."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Military Commanders during the Rule of Akbar were known as ______ ?",
                  "options": ["Kotwal", "Faujdars", "Bakhshi", "Sadr"],
                  "answer": "Faujdars",
                  "explanation": "Military commanders during Akbar's reign were called Faujdars, responsible for maintaining law and order."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following initiated 'Din-i-Ilahi'?",
                  "options": ["Jahangir", "Babur", "Akbar", "Humayun"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Din-i-Ilahi was a syncretic religion propounded by Akbar in 1582, combining elements of various faiths."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Name the author of the book 'Ain-i-Akbari'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abul Fazl",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Abdul Rahim Khan-I-Khana",
                    "Todar Mal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abul Fazl",
                  "explanation": "Abul Fazl, one of Akbar's Navratnas, wrote the 'Ain-i-Akbari,' which is a detailed document of Akbar's administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which language was the 'Ain-i-Akbari' originally written?",
                  "options": ["Persian", "Sanskrit", "Urdu", "Arabic"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "The 'Ain-i-Akbari' was originally written in Persian by Abul Fazl, the official historian of Emperor Akbar's court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor built the Agra fort?",
                  "options": ["Jahangir", "Shahjahan", "Akbar", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "The Agra Fort was built by Akbar in 1565, serving as the main residence of the Mughal emperors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Akbar commissioned ____ to chronicle the story of his father Humayun in ‘Humayun-nama’?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jagat Gosain Begum",
                    "Mariam-uz-Zamani",
                    "Jodha Begum",
                    "Gulbadan Begum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gulbadan Begum",
                  "explanation": "Gulbadan Begum, Humayun's half-sister, wrote 'Humayun-nama' on Akbar's request, chronicling his father's life."
                },
                {
                  "question": "_________ died in 1605, nearly 50 years after his ascension to the throne. He was buried outside of Agra at Sikandra.",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Aurangzeb", "Shah Jahan", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar died in 1605 and was buried at Sikandra near Agra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which emperor’s army did Maharana Pratap fight in the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahmud Shah",
                    "Humayun",
                    "Ibrahim Lodi",
                    "Akbar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Maharana Pratap fought against the Mughal army led by Akbar in the Battle of Haldighati in 1576."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The terms 'Jat and Sawar' are related to which of the following administrative systems?",
                  "options": [
                    "Zamindari System",
                    "Iqtadari System",
                    "Mansabdari System",
                    "Jotedari System"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mansabdari System",
                  "explanation": "'Jat' and 'Sawar' were ranks in the Mansabdari system, determining the number of soldiers a Mansabdar could command."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's father?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Babur", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Humayun",
                  "explanation": "Akbar's father was Humayun, the second Mughal emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor preceded Akbar?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Humayun", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Humayun",
                  "explanation": "Humayun was the emperor before Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When did Akbar ascend to the throne?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1560", "1575", "1590"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "Akbar ascended to the throne in 1556."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Akbar's original name?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abu'l-Fath Jalal-ud-din",
                    "Abu'l-Fath Muhammad",
                    "Jalal-ud-din Muhammad",
                    "Shah Alam"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jalal-ud-din Muhammad",
                  "explanation": "Akbar's original name was Jalal-ud-din Muhammad Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Akbar's religious policy known as?",
                  "options": [
                    "Din-i Ilahi",
                    "Sharia Law",
                    "Hindu-Muslim Unity",
                    "Akbari Policy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Din-i Ilahi",
                  "explanation": "Akbar's religious policy was known as Din-i Ilahi, which aimed to integrate elements from different religions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religion did Akbar originally follow?",
                  "options": [
                    "Islam",
                    "Hinduism",
                    "Zoroastrianism",
                    "Christianity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Islam",
                  "explanation": "Akbar was born into a Muslim family and originally followed Islam."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's spiritual advisor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sheikh Salim Chishti",
                    "Rumi",
                    "Guru Nanak",
                    "Kabir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sheikh Salim Chishti",
                  "explanation": "Sheikh Salim Chishti was Akbar's spiritual advisor and played a key role in his life."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the religious text that Akbar commissioned?",
                  "options": [
                    "Akbar Nama",
                    "Din-i Ilahi",
                    "Bhagavad Gita",
                    "Quran"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Akbar Nama",
                  "explanation": "Akbar commissioned the Akbar Nama, a historical chronicle of his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Akbar's land revenue system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Zabt",
                    "Mansabdari",
                    "Jagirdari",
                    "Revenue Administration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Zabt",
                  "explanation": "The land revenue system introduced by Akbar was known as Zabt."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's chief minister?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abu'l-Fazl",
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Birbal",
                    "Shaikh Abu'l-Fath"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Raja Todar Mal",
                  "explanation": "Raja Todar Mal was Akbar's chief minister and played a crucial role in administrative reforms."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the military unit created by Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mansabdari System",
                    "Jagirdari System",
                    "Akbari Army",
                    "Karkhanas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mansabdari System",
                  "explanation": "Akbar created the Mansabdari System, which was a military and administrative unit."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the famous painter during Akbar's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ustad Mansur",
                    "Ravi Varma",
                    "Basawan",
                    "Jahangir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Basawan",
                  "explanation": "Basawan was a famous painter during Akbar's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Akbar's capital city?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Fatehpur Sikri", "Lahore"],
                  "answer": "Fatehpur Sikri",
                  "explanation": "Akbar established Fatehpur Sikri as his capital city."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous historical text was translated into Persian during Akbar's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahabharata",
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Bhagavad Gita",
                    "Upanishads"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mahabharata",
                  "explanation": "The Mahabharata was translated into Persian during Akbar's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the architect of Akbar's tomb?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ustad Ahmad Lahori",
                    "Mirza Ghiyas",
                    "Shah Jahan",
                    "Sir Edwin Lutyens"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Ghiyas",
                  "explanation": "The architect of Akbar's tomb was Mirza Ghiyas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous battle did Akbar fight against Hemu?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Khanwa",
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Battle of Chausa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Chausa",
                  "explanation": "Akbar fought against Hemu in the Battle of Chausa."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which kingdom did Akbar conquer in the south?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "Deccan Sultanates",
                    "Maratha Kingdom",
                    "Golkonda Sultanate"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan Sultanates",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered the Deccan Sultanates in the south."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's ambassador to the court of Elizabeth I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abu'l-Fazl",
                    "Mirza Ruyun",
                    "Mulla Do Piyaza",
                    "Raja Todar Mal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Ruyun",
                  "explanation": "Mirza Ruyun was Akbar's ambassador to the court of Elizabeth I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many wives did Akbar have?",
                  "options": ["3", "6", "12", "24"],
                  "answer": "24",
                  "explanation": "Akbar had 24 wives."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's favorite son?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jahangir",
                    "Shah Jahan",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Aurangzeb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Jahangir was Akbar's favorite son and succeeded him as the emperor."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's famous advisor known for his wisdom?",
                  "options": ["Birbal", "Tansen", "Chanakya", "Man Singh"],
                  "answer": "Birbal",
                  "explanation": "Birbal was a trusted court advisor known for his wisdom and wit."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following Mughal emperor’s original names was Jalaluddin?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Humayun", "Akbar", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "The original name of the Mughal emperor Akbar was Jalaluddin."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year was the Mughal emperor Akbar born?",
                  "options": ["1542", "1545", "1540", "1550"],
                  "answer": "1542",
                  "explanation": "The Mughal emperor Akbar was born on 15 October 1542 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following is a title of the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Emperor of the South",
                    "Arsh-Ashiyani",
                    "Jagdishwar",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of the above",
                  "explanation": "Emperor of the South, Arsh-Ashiyani, and Jagdishwar are all titles that belong to the Mughal emperor Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following conferred the title 'Arsh-Ashiyani' to Emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Jahangir conferred the title 'Arsh-Ashiyani' to Emperor Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which titles were conferred on Emperor Akbar after the announcement of Mazhar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Imam",
                    "Adil",
                    "Amir al-Mu’minin",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of the above",
                  "explanation": "After the announcement of Mazhar, the titles Imam, Adil, and Amir al-Mu’minin were conferred on Emperor Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following rulers is known as the 'Enlightened Autocratic Ruler'?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar is known as the 'Enlightened Autocratic Ruler'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was called by Dr. R. P Tripathi 'both the son and father of his era'?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Dr. R. P Tripathi referred to the Mughal emperor Akbar as 'both the son and father of his era'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor has been called by Smith the 'born ruler of men'?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Smith called the Mughal emperor Akbar 'born ruler of men'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which one of the following writers called Akbar 'the first national ruler of medieval India'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dr. R. P Tripathi",
                    "Smith",
                    "Elphinstone",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Elphinstone",
                  "explanation": "Elphinstone referred to Akbar as 'the first national ruler of medieval India'."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following Mughal emperor was illiterate?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "The Mughal emperor Akbar was illiterate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following places was the Mughal emperor Akbar born?",
                  "options": [
                    "Umarkot",
                    "Kalanaur",
                    "Gwalior",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Umarkot",
                  "explanation": "Mughal emperor Akbar was born in Umarkot."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following Mughal emperors used to go among the subjects in disguise?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Shahjahan", "Babur", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "The Mughal emperor Akbar used to go among the subjects in disguise."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where was the coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Umarkot",
                    "Kalanaur",
                    "Gwalior",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kalanaur",
                  "explanation": "The coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar took place in Kalanaur (Punjab)."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When was the coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": ["1542", "1546", "1550", "1556"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "The coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar took place on 14 February 1556."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following coronated the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abul Qasim",
                    "Abul Maali",
                    "Bairam Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abul Qasim",
                  "explanation": "The coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar was done by Abul Qasim."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following opposed the coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abul Qasim",
                    "Abul Maali",
                    "Bairam Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abul Maali",
                  "explanation": "The coronation of the Mughal emperor Akbar was opposed by Abul Maali."
                },
                {
                  "question": "On whose death did Akbar get his head shaved?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maham Anga",
                    "GG Anga",
                    "Ruqaiya Begum",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "GG Anga",
                  "explanation": "Akbar had his head shaved on the death of GG Anga."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was the first biographer of Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bayazid Bayat",
                    "Abul Fazl",
                    "Sheikh Mubarak",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bayazid Bayat",
                  "explanation": "The first biographer of Akbar was Bayazid Bayat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was known as 'Khan Baba' by Akbar like Bairam Khan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Munim Khan",
                    "Abul Qasim",
                    "Abul Maali",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Munim Khan",
                  "explanation": "Akbar referred to Munim Khan as 'Khan Baba', similar to Bairam Khan."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the Second Battle of Panipat fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "The Second Battle of Panipat took place on 5 November 1556 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the Battle of Haldighati fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1576",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Haldighati took place on 18 June 1576 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the battle of Sarkhej fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1584",
                  "explanation": "The battle of Sarkhej took place in 1584 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who led the army of Emperor Akbar in the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bairam Khan",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Man Singh",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bairam Khan",
                  "explanation": "In the Second Battle of Panipat, the army of Emperor Akbar was led by Bairam Khan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who led the army of Adilshah in the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hemu",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Man Singh",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hemu",
                  "explanation": "Adilshah’s army was led by Hemu in the Second Battle of Panipat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following historians was an eyewitness to the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Arif Kandhari",
                    "Amir Khusrow",
                    "Abul-Fazl",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Arif Kandhari",
                  "explanation": "The eyewitness of the Second Battle of Panipat was historian Arif Kandhari."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following killed Bairam Khan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Aadham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                  "explanation": "Bairam Khan was murdered by Mubarak Khan Lohani."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When did Emperor Akbar conquer Malwa?",
                  "options": ["1560", "1562", "1576", "1549"],
                  "answer": "1562",
                  "explanation": "Emperor Akbar conquered Malwa in 1562. This was Akbar’s first campaign to expand the kingdom."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Kabul?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1581",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Kabul in 1581. Emperor Akbar was the first Mughal ruler to enter the city of Kabul."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Kashmir?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1585",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Kashmir in 1585 AD."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Sindh?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1591",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Sindh in 1591 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Odisha?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1592",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Odisha in 1592 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Khandesh?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1591",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Khandesh in 1591 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Ahmednagar?",
                  "options": ["1595", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1595",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Ahmednagar in 1595 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Asirgarh?",
                  "options": ["1595", "1585", "1591", "1601"],
                  "answer": "1601",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Asirgarh in 1601 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Baz Bahadur was the ruler of which of the following states?",
                  "options": ["Malwa", "Mewar", "Gujarat", "Kabul"],
                  "answer": "Malwa",
                  "explanation": "The ruler of the Malwa kingdom was Baz Bahadur. This emperor was a contemporary ruler of Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was sent by Akbar for the Malwa campaign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adham Khan",
                  "explanation": "Akbar had sent Adham Khan for the Malwa campaign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the Mughal commander in the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "In the Battle of Haldighati, the Mughal general was Man Singh, while the deputy general was Asaf Khan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the commander of Maharana Pratap in the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Hakim Khan Sur",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hakim Khan Sur",
                  "explanation": "Hakim Khan Sur was the general of Maharana Pratap in the Battle of Haldighati."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following historians was an eyewitness to the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Badayuni",
                    "Abul Fazl",
                    "Arif Kandhari",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Badayuni",
                  "explanation": "Badayuni was an eyewitness historian of the Battle of Haldighati."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the first Mughal emperor to rule over India?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Humayun", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Babur",
                  "explanation": "Babur was the founder of the Mughal Empire and the first Mughal emperor to rule over India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is known for the construction of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan commissioned the construction of the Taj Mahal in memory of his wife Mumtaz Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary language used in the Mughal court during Akbar's reign?",
                  "options": ["Persian", "Sanskrit", "Hindustani", "Arabic"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "Persian was the primary language used in the Mughal court during Akbar's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is known for his policy of religious tolerance?",
                  "options": ["Aurangzeb", "Akbar", "Babur", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar is known for his policy of religious tolerance and for promoting a syncretic religion called Din-i Ilahi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar's wife who played a significant role in Mughal politics?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Empress Nur Jahan",
                    "Ruqaiya Sultan Begum",
                    "Jodha Bai"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ruqaiya Sultan Begum",
                  "explanation": "Ruqaiya Sultan Begum was Akbar's first wife and played a significant role in Mughal politics."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the end of the Mughal Empire's dominance in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Plassey",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Buxar",
                    "Battle of Haldighati"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Buxar",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Buxar (1764) marked the end of the Mughal Empire's dominance in India as the British East India Company emerged as a dominant power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler was known for his persecution of Hindus and the destruction of temples?",
                  "options": ["Aurangzeb", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb is known for his persecution of Hindus, destruction of temples, and strict adherence to Islamic principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Akbar as the Mughal emperor?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Jahangir, Akbar's son, succeeded him as the Mughal emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is known for the establishment of the Mughal navy?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan is known for the establishment of the Mughal navy to protect maritime interests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is credited with introducing the policy of Sulh-i-Kul (Universal Tolerance)?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar introduced the policy of Sulh-i-Kul, which aimed at universal tolerance and the inclusion of all religions."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 11,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the Din-i-Ilahi?",
                  "options": [
                    "A religion founded by Akbar",
                    "A tax system",
                    "A military strategy",
                    "A palace"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A religion founded by Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Din-i-Ilahi was a syncretic religion introduced by Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the Second Battle of Panipat fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1556",
                  "explanation": "The Second Battle of Panipat took place on 5 November 1556 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the Battle of Haldighati fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1576",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Haldighati took place on 18 June 1576 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year was the battle of Sarkhej fought?",
                  "options": ["1556", "1576", "1584", "1562"],
                  "answer": "1584",
                  "explanation": "The battle of Sarkhej took place in 1584 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who led the army of Emperor Akbar in the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bairam Khan",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Man Singh",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bairam Khan",
                  "explanation": "In the Second Battle of Panipat, the army of Emperor Akbar was led by Bairam Khan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who led the army of Adilshah in the second battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hemu",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Man Singh",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hemu",
                  "explanation": "Adilshah’s army was led by Hemu in the Second Battle of Panipat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following historians was an eyewitness to the Second Battle of Panipat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Arif Kandhari",
                    "Amir Khusrow",
                    "Abul-Fazl",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Arif Kandhari",
                  "explanation": "The eyewitness of the Second Battle of Panipat was historian Arif Kandhari."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following killed Bairam Khan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Aadham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                  "explanation": "Bairam Khan was murdered by Mubarak Khan Lohani."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When did Emperor Akbar conquer Malwa?",
                  "options": ["1560", "1562", "1576", "1549"],
                  "answer": "1562",
                  "explanation": "Emperor Akbar conquered Malwa in 1562. This was Akbar’s first campaign to expand the kingdom."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Kabul?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1581",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Kabul in 1581. Emperor Akbar was the first Mughal ruler to enter the city of Kabul."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 12,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Kashmir?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1585",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Kashmir in 1585 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Odisha?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1592",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Orissa in 1592 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Khandesh?",
                  "options": ["1581", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1591",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Khandesh in 1591 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Ahmednagar?",
                  "options": ["1595", "1585", "1591", "1592"],
                  "answer": "1595",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Ahmednagar in 1595 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which of the following year did Akbar conquer Asirgarh?",
                  "options": ["1595", "1585", "1591", "1601"],
                  "answer": "1601",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Asirgarh in 1601 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Baz Bahadur was the ruler of which of the following states?",
                  "options": ["Malwa", "Mewar", "Gujarat", "Kabul"],
                  "answer": "Malwa",
                  "explanation": "The ruler of the Malwa kingdom was Baz Bahadur. This emperor was a contemporary ruler of Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was sent by Akbar for the Malwa campaign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adham Khan",
                  "explanation": "Akbar had sent Adham Khan for the Malwa campaign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the Mughal commander in the battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Mubarak Khan Lohani",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "In the battle of Haldighati, the Mughal general was Man Singh, while the deputy general was Asaf Khan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the commander of Maharana Pratap in the battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Hakim Khan Sur",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hakim Khan Sur",
                  "explanation": "Hakim Khan Sur was the general of Maharana Pratap in the battle of Haldighati."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following historians was an eyewitness to the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Badayuni",
                    "Abul Fazl",
                    "Arif Kandhari",
                    "None of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Badayuni",
                  "explanation": "Badayuni was an eyewitness historian of the Battle of Haldighati."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 13,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "At what age was Akbar crowned as the Emperor of the Mughal Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "10 years",
                    "13 years and 4 months",
                    "16 years",
                    "20 years"
                  ],
                  "answer": "13 years and 4 months",
                  "explanation": "Akbar was crowned at the age of 13 years and 4 months in 1556 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who acted as Akbar’s regent during the initial years of his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bairam Khan",
                    "Humayun",
                    "Maham Anaga",
                    "Mirza Hakim"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bairam Khan",
                  "explanation": "Bairam Khan was Akbar’s regent until he came of age."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle was pivotal in Akbar’s early consolidation of power, involving a key defeat of Hemu Vikramaditya?",
                  "options": [
                    "First Battle of Panipat",
                    "Second Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Haldighati",
                    "Battle of Chittor"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Second Battle of Panipat",
                  "explanation": "The Second Battle of Panipat in 1556 was crucial for Akbar’s consolidation of power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important Mughal territory was captured during Bairam Khan’s regency?",
                  "options": ["Kashmir", "Malwa", "Gujarat", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Gujarat",
                  "explanation": "Gujarat was captured during Bairam Khan’s regency in 1572."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the fate of Bairam Khan after he was dismissed from Akbar’s service?",
                  "options": [
                    "Appointed governor",
                    "Killed by an Afghan",
                    "Exiled to Mecca",
                    "Military commander in Deccan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Killed by an Afghan",
                  "explanation": "Bairam Khan was killed by an Afghan near Patan in 1561."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal official was known for his cruelty and was eventually thrown from the Agra Fort by Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Hakim",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Tansen"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adham Khan",
                  "explanation": "Adham Khan, known for his cruelty, was thrown from the Agra Fort by Akbar in 1560."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Akbar’s half-brother who seized Kabul and later besieged Lahore?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Hakim",
                    "Jahangir",
                    "Jahandar",
                    "Dara Shikoh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Hakim",
                  "explanation": "Mirza Hakim seized Kabul and later besieged Lahore."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the end of the rebellion by the Mirzas and Uzbeks?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Chittor",
                    "Battle of Haldighati",
                    "Battle of Sikandarabad",
                    "Battle of Kabul"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Sikandarabad",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Sikandarabad in 1582 marked the end of the Mirzas and Uzbeks rebellion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key fortress in Rajasthan fell to Akbar after a six-month siege?",
                  "options": ["Ranthambore", "Kalinjar", "Chittor", "Merta"],
                  "answer": "Chittor",
                  "explanation": "Chittor fell after a six-month siege in 1568."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significant policy Akbar adopted towards the Rajput states that led to their eventual integration into the Mughal Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Imposing high taxes",
                    "Marrying Rajput princesses",
                    "Forcible conversion",
                    "Total military conquest"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marrying Rajput princesses",
                  "explanation": "Akbar married Rajput princesses to integrate Rajput states into the Mughal Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 14,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which province did Akbar conquer in 1572, after the death of its ruler Bahadur Shah?",
                  "options": ["Gujarat", "Bihar", "Bengal", "Kashmir"],
                  "answer": "Gujarat",
                  "explanation": "Akbar conquered Gujarat in 1572 after the death of its ruler Bahadur Shah."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant architectural achievement did Akbar undertake to commemorate his victory over Gujarat?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Red Fort",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Buland Darwaza",
                    "Taj Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Buland Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "The Buland Darwaza was constructed by Akbar to commemorate his victory over Gujarat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was appointed the governor of Gujarat after its initial conquest by Akbar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Bhagwant Das",
                    "Man Singh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                  "explanation": "Mirza Aziz Koka was appointed as the governor of Gujarat after its conquest."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ruler’s rebellion was particularly focused in Bengal and led to the declaration of independence by Daud Khan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Muzaffar Shah",
                    "Daud Khan",
                    "Hemu Vikramaditya",
                    "Mirza Hakim"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Daud Khan",
                  "explanation": "Daud Khan's rebellion was focused in Bengal and led to his declaration of independence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What policy did Akbar implement to control the jagirdars and curb rebellion during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dagh system (branding of horses)",
                    "Jizya tax",
                    "Abolition of pilgrim tax",
                    "Conversion of land grants"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dagh system (branding of horses)",
                  "explanation": "Akbar implemented the Dagh system to control jagirdars and reduce rebellion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal governor was sent to conquer Orissa during Akbar’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                    "Raja Man Singh",
                    "Asaf Khan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Raja Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "Raja Man Singh was appointed to conquer Orissa during Akbar’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant fortress in the Deccan was captured by the Mughals after a series of battles involving Chand Bibi?",
                  "options": ["Berar", "Ahmednagar", "Asirgarh", "Bijapur"],
                  "answer": "Asirgarh",
                  "explanation": "Asirgarh fortress in the Deccan was captured by the Mughals after several battles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for the rebellion in Gujarat during Akbar’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "High taxes",
                    "Religious intolerance",
                    "Military aggression",
                    "Administrative neglect"
                  ],
                  "answer": "High taxes",
                  "explanation": "The rebellion in Gujarat was mainly due to high taxes imposed during Akbar's administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the famous Rajput general appointed by Akbar and became governor of Bihar and Bengal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhagwant Das",
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Adham Khan",
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "Man Singh was the famous Rajput general appointed by Akbar as governor of Bihar and Bengal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Akbar’s strategy in dealing with the rebellious tribes of the Khyber Pass?",
                  "options": [
                    "Negotiation and peace treaties",
                    "Military expeditions and conquests",
                    "Cultural diplomacy",
                    "Financial incentives"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military expeditions and conquests",
                  "explanation": "Akbar employed military expeditions and conquests to deal with the rebellious tribes of the Khyber Pass."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 15,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the city built by Akbar near Agra, known for its architectural splendor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Agra Fort",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Lahore Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fatehpur Sikri",
                  "explanation": "Fatehpur Sikri was the city built by Akbar near Agra, renowned for its architectural splendor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Akbar’s architectural projects was built to commemorate his victory over Gujarat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Buland Darwaza",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Sikandra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Buland Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "The Buland Darwaza was constructed by Akbar to commemorate his victory over Gujarat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal structure was completed by Akbar’s son Jahangir?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Jahangir Mahal",
                    "Taj Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jahangir Mahal",
                  "explanation": "The Jahangir Mahal was completed by Akbar’s son Jahangir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Akbar’s court artist renowned for illustrating the Persian versions of Mahabharata and Ramayana?",
                  "options": ["Tulsidas", "Baswan", "Miskina", "Abul Fazl"],
                  "answer": "Baswan",
                  "explanation": "Baswan was a renowned court artist known for illustrating the Persian versions of Mahabharata and Ramayana."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text was illustrated under Akbar’s patronage, known for its elaborate paintings and historical content?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hamzanama",
                    "Akbarnama",
                    "Ain-i-Akbari",
                    "Ramacharitmanas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hamzanama",
                  "explanation": "The Hamzanama was illustrated under Akbar’s patronage, famous for its elaborate paintings and historical content."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major contribution of Tansen during Akbar’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing new literary styles",
                    "Composing new ragas and music",
                    "Leading military campaigns",
                    "Building architectural structures"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Composing new ragas and music",
                  "explanation": "Tansen is renowned for his major contribution to composing new ragas and music during Akbar’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Indian poet was associated with Akbar’s court and is known for the Hindi version of Ramayana?",
                  "options": ["Kabir", "Tulsidas", "Mirabai", "Surdas"],
                  "answer": "Tulsidas",
                  "explanation": "Tulsidas was associated with Akbar’s court and is known for his Hindi version of the Ramayana."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In what year was the Buland Darwaza constructed?",
                  "options": ["1564 CE", "1571 CE", "1572 CE", "1580 CE"],
                  "answer": "1572 CE",
                  "explanation": "The Buland Darwaza was constructed in 1572 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which language gained prominence and widespread use in the Mughal court during Akbar’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Sanskrit", "Arabic", "Persian", "Hindi"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "Persian gained prominence and widespread use in the Mughal court during Akbar’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which prominent historian and scholar wrote the Ain-i-Akbari and Akbarnama during Akbar’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Abul Fazl", "Abul Faizi", "Utbi", "Naziri"],
                  "answer": "Abul Fazl",
                  "explanation": "Abul Fazl was the prominent historian and scholar who wrote the Ain-i-Akbari and Akbarnama during Akbar’s reign."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 16,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Akbar’s major policy towards the Rajput rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Forced conversion",
                    "Military conquest",
                    "Alliance and integration",
                    "Exile and punishment"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alliance and integration",
                  "explanation": "Akbar's major policy towards the Rajput rulers was alliance and integration, which involved forming alliances through marriage and diplomacy rather than forced conversion or military conquest."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which fortress was considered crucial for controlling central Rajasthan and fell to Akbar after a prolonged siege?",
                  "options": ["Ranthambore", "Chittor", "Merta", "Kalinjar"],
                  "answer": "Ranthambore",
                  "explanation": "The fortress of Ranthambore was crucial for controlling central Rajasthan and fell to Akbar after a prolonged siege."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler’s policy included the abolition of the jizya tax and the pilgrim tax?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Babur", "Humayun", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar implemented the policy of abolishing the jizya tax and the pilgrim tax as part of his broader approach to religious tolerance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal governor was responsible for bringing Kathiawar under Mughal control?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Man Singh",
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Raja Todar Mal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                  "explanation": "Mirza Aziz Koka was responsible for bringing Kathiawar under Mughal control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which prominent Mughal general was known for his defeat of Rana Pratap Singh in the Battle of Haldighati?",
                  "options": [
                    "Man Singh",
                    "Bhagwant Das",
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "Man Singh was the prominent Mughal general known for his role in the Battle of Haldighati against Rana Pratap Singh."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Akbar’s approach to dealing with the Deccan Sultanates?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diplomacy and alliances",
                    "Military conquest and annexation",
                    "Ignoring their existence",
                    "Forming economic treaties"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military conquest and annexation",
                  "explanation": "Akbar’s approach to the Deccan Sultanates involved military conquest and annexation to consolidate Mughal power in the southern territories of India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal military campaign was aimed at consolidating power in the southern territories of India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Conquest of Gujarat",
                    "Campaigns in Deccan",
                    "Siege of Chittor",
                    "Campaign in Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Campaigns in Deccan",
                  "explanation": "The campaigns in Deccan were aimed at consolidating Mughal power in the southern territories of India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main objective behind Akbar’s policy of Sulh-e-Kul?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promoting religious tolerance",
                    "Expanding the empire’s territory",
                    "Increasing military strength",
                    "Reforming administrative practices"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoting religious tolerance",
                  "explanation": "The main objective behind Akbar’s policy of Sulh-e-Kul was to promote religious tolerance and harmony among the diverse communities in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal official was known for his role in negotiating peace treaties with various Rajput rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Mirza Aziz Koka",
                    "Bhagwant Das",
                    "Raja Man Singh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Raja Man Singh",
                  "explanation": "Raja Man Singh was known for his role in negotiating peace treaties with various Rajput rulers and integrating them into the Mughal Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important political strategy did Akbar employ to maintain stability in the newly acquired territories?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing local assemblies",
                    "Appointing loyalists as governors",
                    "Imposing high taxes",
                    "Relocating populations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Appointing loyalists as governors",
                  "explanation": "To maintain stability in newly acquired territories, Akbar employed the strategy of appointing loyalists as governors."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Aurangzeb",
          "description": [
            "Aurangzeb was the last powerful Mughal emperor, known for his military campaigns and religious policies.",
            "He was very strict and harsh in his rule.",
            "He tried to make everyone follow his religion, but this caused problems.",
            "During his time, art and culture became less important.",
            "People didn't like Aurangzeb's ways, and the Mughal Empire became weaker."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "When did Aurangzeb ascend the throne?",
                  "options": ["1658", "1605", "1707", "1526"],
                  "answer": "1658",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb became emperor in 1658 after a war of succession."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb was the _______ Mughal Emperor.",
                  "options": ["Fifth", "Sixth", "Seventh", "Eighth"],
                  "answer": "Seventh",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was the seventh Mughal Emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign as emperor lasted for approximately ______ years.",
                  "options": ["20", "30", "40", "50"],
                  "answer": "50",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's reign lasted for approximately 50 years."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb was the son of which Mughal Emperor?",
                  "options": ["Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Akbar", "Babur"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was the son of Emperor Shah Jahan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religious group faced strict policies under Aurangzeb's rule?",
                  "options": ["Hindus", "Sikhs", "Christians", "Buddhists"],
                  "answer": "Hindus",
                  "explanation": "Hindus faced strict policies under Aurangzeb's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb imposed a tax on non-Muslims known as:",
                  "options": ["Zakat", "Jizya", "Khums", "Sadaqah"],
                  "answer": "Jizya",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb imposed the Jizya tax on non-Muslims."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb is known for his successful campaigns in which region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Deccan",
                    "Central Asia",
                    "Persia",
                    "North Africa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb is known for his successful campaigns in the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb shifted the Mughal capital from Delhi to:",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Agra", "Jaipur", "Aurangabad"],
                  "answer": "Aurangabad",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb shifted the Mughal capital to Aurangabad."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policy of demolishing Hindu temples was known as:",
                  "options": [
                    "Rajputana Policy",
                    "Iconoclastic Policy",
                    "Sufi Policy",
                    "Dhimmi Policy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Iconoclastic Policy",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policy of demolishing Hindu temples is known as the Iconoclastic Policy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb had a strained relationship with his:",
                  "options": ["Sons", "Brothers", "Father", "Grandfather"],
                  "answer": "Brothers",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb had a strained relationship with his brothers."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "The famous Sikh Guru Tegh Bahadur was executed during Aurangzeb's reign for:",
                  "options": [
                    "Refusing to convert to Islam",
                    "Leading a rebellion against the Mughals",
                    "Conspiring against the emperor",
                    "Engaging in illegal trade activities"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Refusing to convert to Islam",
                  "explanation": "Guru Tegh Bahadur was executed for refusing to convert to Islam."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies were influenced by his conservative interpretation of:",
                  "options": ["Hinduism", "Christianity", "Buddhism", "Islam"],
                  "answer": "Islam",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies were influenced by his conservative interpretation of Islam."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor did Aurangzeb imprison to seize power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jahangir",
                    "Akbar",
                    "Shah Jahan",
                    "Bahadur Shah I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb imprisoned his father, Shah Jahan, to seize power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign witnessed the decline of the Mughal Empire due to:",
                  "options": [
                    "External invasions",
                    "Economic instability",
                    "Rebellion by regional kingdoms",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of the above",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's reign witnessed the decline of the Mughal Empire due to external invasions, economic instability, and rebellion by regional kingdoms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's attempts to suppress Hinduism resulted in the rise of a new Hindu kingdom known as the:",
                  "options": [
                    "Marathas",
                    "Rajputs",
                    "Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "Mysore Kingdom"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marathas",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's attempts to suppress Hinduism contributed to the rise of the Maratha Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb was known for his simplicity and:",
                  "options": [
                    "Humility",
                    "Extravagance",
                    "Tolerance",
                    "Religious syncretism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Humility",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was known for his simplicity and humility."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign marked the decline of the Mughal patronage of:",
                  "options": [
                    "Art and architecture",
                    "Literature",
                    "Music and dance",
                    "Science and technology"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Art and architecture",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's reign marked the decline of Mughal patronage of art and architecture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb banned the practice of:",
                  "options": [
                    "Sati",
                    "Child marriage",
                    "Dowry",
                    "Devadasi system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Devadasi system",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb banned the Devadasi system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's religious policies led to conflicts with the Sikh community, resulting in the establishment of the Sikh state of:",
                  "options": ["Punjab", "Bihar", "Rajasthan", "Assam"],
                  "answer": "Punjab",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies led to conflicts with the Sikh community, contributing to the establishment of the Sikh state of Punjab."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb imposed a tax on non-Muslims known as:",
                  "options": ["Zakat", "Jizya", "Khums", "Sadaqah"],
                  "answer": "Jizya",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb imposed the Jizya tax on non-Muslims."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Sikhs softened after he was influenced by:",
                  "options": [
                    "Guru Nanak",
                    "Guru Angad",
                    "Guru Arjan Dev",
                    "Guru Gobind Singh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Guru Gobind Singh",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s policies towards the Sikhs softened under the influence of Guru Gobind Singh, the tenth Sikh Guru."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Maratha king who challenged Aurangzeb's authority was:",
                  "options": [
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Rana Pratap",
                    "Akbar the Great",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shivaji",
                  "explanation": "Shivaji, the founder of the Maratha Empire, was a prominent figure who challenged Aurangzeb's authority."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies led to a rebellion in the region of:",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Punjab", "Awadh"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies led to significant unrest and rebellion in the region of Bengal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb is buried in a mausoleum located in:",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Delhi", "Aurangabad", "Lahore"],
                  "answer": "Aurangabad",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb is buried in a mausoleum in Aurangabad, Maharashtra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb was succeeded by his son:",
                  "options": [
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Shah Alam II",
                    "Bahadur Shah Zafar",
                    "Muhammad Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahadur Shah I",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was succeeded by his son Bahadur Shah I, also known as Bahadur Shah I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Rajputs resulted in the decline of their influence, except in the kingdom of:",
                  "options": ["Mewar", "Jaipur", "Jodhpur", "Bundi"],
                  "answer": "Mewar",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's policies, the Rajput kingdom of Mewar maintained its influence and resisted Mughal dominance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb issued a royal order banning the use of:",
                  "options": ["Tobacco", "Alcohol", "Opium", "Coffee"],
                  "answer": "Tobacco",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb issued a royal order banning the use of tobacco as part of his religious and moral reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign witnessed a decline in the Mughal control over:",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Deccan", "Punjab", "Rajasthan"],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "During Aurangzeb's reign, the Mughal control over the Deccan region witnessed significant decline due to ongoing conflicts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous Mughal painting style known as 'Aurangzeb's Black' was developed during his reign in which city?",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Delhi", "Jaipur", "Bijapur"],
                  "answer": "Bijapur",
                  "explanation": "'Aurangzeb’s Black' painting style, characterized by its distinct style, was developed in Bijapur during Aurangzeb’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's religious policies were influenced by the teachings of the Islamic scholar:",
                  "options": [
                    "Al-Ghazali",
                    "Ibn Arabi",
                    "Imam Abu Hanifa",
                    "Shah Waliullah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Al-Ghazali",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s religious policies were influenced by the teachings of the Islamic scholar Al-Ghazali, known for his works on Islamic jurisprudence and mysticism."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Sufis resulted in the decline of their influence, except in the region of:",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Punjab", "Kashmir", "Rajasthan"],
                  "answer": "Kashmir",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s policies against the Sufis led to their decline in most regions, but Kashmir remained a significant center for Sufism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's construction of the Badshahi Mosque took place in which city?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Lahore",
                  "explanation": "The Badshahi Mosque, one of the largest mosques in the world, was constructed by Aurangzeb in Lahore."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's efforts to expand the Mughal Empire towards the south were largely focused on:",
                  "options": ["Vijayanagara", "Golconda", "Bijapur", "Madurai"],
                  "answer": "Golconda",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb concentrated his efforts on the conquest of Golconda as part of his expansion into the southern territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Shia Muslims resulted in tensions with which neighboring empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ottoman Empire",
                    "Safavid Empire",
                    "Timurid Empire",
                    "Mamluk Sultanate"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Safavid Empire",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies against Shia Muslims caused conflicts with the Safavid Empire, which was Shia Muslim and a rival to the Sunni Mughals."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous battle in which Aurangzeb defeated his brother Dara Shikoh was:",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Haldighati",
                    "Battle of Plassey",
                    "Battle of Samugarh",
                    "Battle of Panipat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Samugarh",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb defeated his brother Dara Shikoh in the Battle of Samugarh, which was a significant turning point in Aurangzeb's rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in a protracted conflict known as the:",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Carnatic Wars",
                    "Mughal-Maratha Wars",
                    "Battle of Buxar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mughal-Maratha Wars",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's conflict with the Marathas led to a series of prolonged battles collectively known as the Mughal-Maratha Wars."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Jats resulted in a rebellion led by which Jat leader?",
                  "options": [
                    "Suraj Mal",
                    "Maharana Pratap",
                    "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
                    "Chhatrapati Shivaji"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Suraj Mal",
                  "explanation": "Suraj Mal was a prominent Jat leader who led a significant rebellion against Aurangzeb's policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Mughal nobility resulted in the decline of their loyalty, except for the nobles from which region?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Punjab", "Awadh"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's policies, the nobles from Bengal remained relatively loyal and influential."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Portuguese led to the capture of which famous fort?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Golconda Fort",
                    "Agra Fort",
                    "Haldighati Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Red Fort",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s policies and military actions eventually led to the capture of the Red Fort, although it was more directly related to Mughal internal conflicts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in the execution of which Maratha leader?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
                    "Bajirao I",
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Rana Pratap"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shivaji",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies against the Marathas included the execution of key leaders, including Shivaji, although Shivaji's direct execution is historically debated."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Bengal region resulted in the establishment of a semi-independent state known as:",
                  "options": ["Awadh", "Hyderabad", "Murshidabad", "Sindh"],
                  "answer": "Murshidabad",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's administration led to the rise of Murshidabad as a semi-independent state within Bengal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Deccan region resulted in the decline of the:",
                  "options": [
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "Qutb Shahi dynasty",
                    "Mysore Kingdom"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutb Shahi dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's military campaigns in the Deccan led to the decline of the Qutb Shahi dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Rajputs resulted in the decline of their power, except for the kingdom of:",
                  "options": ["Jaisalmer", "Kota", "Bikaner", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Jaipur",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's policies, the kingdom of Jaipur managed to retain its influence and power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Sikhs resulted in the construction of the famous Sikh shrine known as:",
                  "options": [
                    "Golden Temple",
                    "Harmandir Sahib",
                    "Hemkund Sahib",
                    "Gurudwara Bangla Sahib"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Golden Temple",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's persecution of Sikhs led to the construction of the Golden Temple, a central religious site for Sikhs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in the establishment of their capital in which city?",
                  "options": ["Pune", "Mumbai", "Kolhapur", "Nagpur"],
                  "answer": "Pune",
                  "explanation": "Pune became the center of Maratha administration and resistance against Aurangzeb's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Jats resulted in the establishment of a semi-independent state known as:",
                  "options": ["Bharatpur", "Alwar", "Kota", "Gwalior"],
                  "answer": "Bharatpur",
                  "explanation": "The Jats, under leaders like Suraj Mal, established Bharatpur as a semi-independent state."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Portuguese resulted in the capture of which important trading port?",
                  "options": ["Goa", "Surat", "Chennai", "Kolkata"],
                  "answer": "Goa",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies led to the capture of Goa, which was a crucial Portuguese trading port."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Mughal nobility resulted in the decline of their loyalty, except for the nobles from which region?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Punjab", "Awadh"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Nobles from Bengal remained relatively loyal to Aurangzeb despite his policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in the execution of which Maratha leader?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
                    "Bajirao I",
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Rana Pratap"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shivaji",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's conflict with the Marathas included the execution of key leaders, including Shivaji, although this is debated historically."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Bengal region resulted in the establishment of a semi-independent state known as:",
                  "options": ["Awadh", "Hyderabad", "Murshidabad", "Sindh"],
                  "answer": "Murshidabad",
                  "explanation": "Murshidabad emerged as a semi-independent state in Bengal due to Aurangzeb's policies."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which temple was destroyed by Aurangzeb in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Somnath Temple",
                    "Brihadeeswarar Temple",
                    "Meenakshi Temple",
                    "Ranganathaswamy Temple"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Somnath Temple",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb is known for the destruction of the Somnath Temple as part of his efforts to enforce Islamic principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Aurangzeb’s policy towards the Marathas known as?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tolerant Policy",
                    "Deccan Policy",
                    "Rajput Policy",
                    "Hindu Policy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan Policy",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s Deccan Policy focused on suppressing the Marathas and consolidating Mughal power in the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler established the practice of Tuladan?",
                  "options": ["Humayun", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar introduced the practice of Tuladan, where rulers were weighed against gold and the value distributed to the poor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was NOT a noted painter during Jahangir’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mir Sayyad Ali",
                    "Abdus Samad",
                    "Daswant",
                    "Abul Hasan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abul Hasan",
                  "explanation": "Abul Hasan was a noted painter during Jahangir’s reign, while Daswant was not."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Englishman received a Mansab of 400 and was known as 'English Khan'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fitch",
                    "Mildenhall",
                    "Hawkins",
                    "Sir Thomas Roe"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sir Thomas Roe",
                  "explanation": "Sir Thomas Roe received a Mansab of 400 and was known as 'English Khan' or Firangi Khan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the Jizya tax imposed by Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": [
                    "A tax on trade",
                    "A poll tax on non-Muslims",
                    "A land tax",
                    "A religious tax on Muslims"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A poll tax on non-Muslims",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb reimposed the Jizya tax as a poll tax on non-Muslims."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which language did Babur write his autobiography?",
                  "options": ["Persian", "Arabic", "Turkish", "None of these"],
                  "answer": "Turkish",
                  "explanation": "Babur wrote his autobiography in Turkish."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When was the Treaty of Chittor signed during Jahangir’s reign?",
                  "options": ["1605 AD", "1610 AD", "1615 AD", "1620 AD"],
                  "answer": "1615 AD",
                  "explanation": "The Treaty of Chittor was signed in 1615 AD during Jahangir’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ruler's will instructed his sons to continue Asad Khan as the Vazir?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's will instructed his sons to continue Asad Khan as the Vazir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the percentage of the extra tax charged by Sher Shah for emergencies?",
                  "options": ["7.5%", "5.0%", "2.5%", "1.5%"],
                  "answer": "1.5%",
                  "explanation": "Sher Shah imposed an extra tax of 1.5% for general welfare during emergencies."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the infamous Qazi Fazihat during Sher Shah’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Governor of Bengal",
                    "Qazi-i-Lashkar",
                    "Qazi-ul-Qazzat",
                    "Qazi of Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qazi-ul-Qazzat",
                  "explanation": "Qazi Fazihat was known as Qazi-ul-Qazzat during Sher Shah’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was favored by Mir Khalifa as Babur’s successor instead of Humayun?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Suleiman",
                    "Mirza Kamran",
                    "Mirza Askari",
                    "Mehdi Khwaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mirza Kamran",
                  "explanation": "Mir Khalifa favored Mirza Kamran as Babur’s successor instead of Humayun."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler was defeated by the Mughals under Governor Shaista Khan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maratha chief",
                    "Arakanese ruler",
                    "Bijapur ruler",
                    "Qutbshahi ruler"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Arakanese ruler",
                  "explanation": "The Mughal army under Governor Shaista Khan defeated the Arakanese ruler."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the Mughal emperor during the capture of Bijapur fort?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was the Mughal emperor during the capture of Bijapur fort."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which two sons did Khurram send to Jahangir’s court after his revolt?",
                  "options": [
                    "Murad and Aurangzeb",
                    "Murad and Shah Shuja",
                    "Shah Shuja and Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara and Aurangzeb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dara and Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Khurram sent his sons Dara and Aurangzeb to Jahangir’s court after his revolt."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the percentage of the extra tax imposed by Sher Shah for general welfare?",
                  "options": ["7.5%", "5.0%", "2.5%", "1.5%"],
                  "answer": "2.5%",
                  "explanation": "Sher Shah imposed an extra tax of 2.5% for general welfare."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is known for introducing the month scale in the Mansabdari system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jahangir",
                    "Shah Jahan",
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "None of these"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan is known for introducing the month scale in the Mansabdari system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the Year 1639 during Shah Jahan’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Treaty of Chittor",
                    "Construction of Red Fort",
                    "Establishment of the Mughal School of Painting",
                    "Rebellion of the Marathas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Construction of Red Fort",
                  "explanation": "The year 1639 marked the beginning of the construction of the Red Fort during Shah Jahan’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the Mughal approach towards the administrative system during Jahangir's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized with fewer regional powers",
                    "Decentralized with regional powers",
                    "Completely new administrative reforms",
                    "None of these"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized with fewer regional powers",
                  "explanation": "During Jahangir’s reign, the Mughal administration was centralized with fewer regional powers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the only Mughal emperor to build a new city besides Delhi?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was the only Mughal emperor to build a new city, namely Shahjahanabad, besides Delhi."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Rajputs resulted in the decline of their power, except for the kingdom of:",
                  "options": ["Jaisalmer", "Kota", "Bikaner", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Jaipur",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's policies, the kingdom of Jaipur managed to retain its influence and power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Sikhs resulted in the construction of the famous Sikh shrine known as:",
                  "options": [
                    "Golden Temple",
                    "Harmandir Sahib",
                    "Hemkund Sahib",
                    "Gurudwara Bangla Sahib"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Golden Temple",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's persecution of Sikhs led to the construction of the Golden Temple, a central religious site for Sikhs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in the establishment of their capital in which city?",
                  "options": ["Pune", "Mumbai", "Kolhapur", "Nagpur"],
                  "answer": "Pune",
                  "explanation": "Pune became the center of Maratha administration and resistance against Aurangzeb's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Jats resulted in the establishment of a semi-independent state known as:",
                  "options": ["Bharatpur", "Alwar", "Kota", "Gwalior"],
                  "answer": "Bharatpur",
                  "explanation": "The Jats, under leaders like Suraj Mal, established Bharatpur as a semi-independent state."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Portuguese resulted in the capture of which important trading port?",
                  "options": ["Goa", "Surat", "Chennai", "Kolkata"],
                  "answer": "Goa",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies led to the capture of Goa, which was a crucial Portuguese trading port."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Mughal nobility resulted in the decline of their loyalty, except for the nobles from which region?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Punjab", "Awadh"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Nobles from Bengal remained relatively loyal to Aurangzeb despite his policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Marathas resulted in the execution of which Maratha leader?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
                    "Bajirao I",
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Rana Pratap"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shivaji",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's conflict with the Marathas included the execution of key leaders, including Shivaji, although this is debated historically."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Bengal region resulted in the establishment of a semi-independent state known as:",
                  "options": ["Awadh", "Hyderabad", "Murshidabad", "Sindh"],
                  "answer": "Murshidabad",
                  "explanation": "Murshidabad emerged as a semi-independent state in Bengal due to Aurangzeb's policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Deccan region resulted in the decline of the:",
                  "options": [
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "Qutb Shahi dynasty",
                    "Mysore Kingdom"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutb Shahi dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's military campaigns in the Deccan led to the decline of the Qutb Shahi dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policies towards the Rajputs resulted in the decline of their power, except for the kingdom of:",
                  "options": ["Jaisalmer", "Kota", "Bikaner", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Jaipur",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's policies, the kingdom of Jaipur managed to retain its influence and power."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's military campaigns in the Deccan were part of his effort to:",
                  "options": [
                    "Expand Mughal influence",
                    "Defend against foreign invasions",
                    "Promote trade",
                    "Support local rulers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expand Mughal influence",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's campaigns in the Deccan were aimed at expanding Mughal influence in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor's reign was characterized by the consolidation of the Mughal Empire's southern territories?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Akbar", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's reign saw the consolidation of the Mughal Empire's southern territories, particularly through his Deccan campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb’s policies towards religious minorities included:",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased patronage of Hindu temples",
                    "Promotion of religious tolerance",
                    "Reinstatement of the Jizya tax",
                    "Encouragement of interfaith dialogue"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reinstatement of the Jizya tax",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb reinstated the Jizya tax on non-Muslims, which was a significant aspect of his policies towards religious minorities."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which prominent figure opposed Aurangzeb's rule and led a significant uprising in the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shivaji Maharaj",
                    "Ranjit Singh",
                    "Guru Gobind Singh",
                    "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shivaji Maharaj",
                  "explanation": "Shivaji Maharaj led a significant uprising against Aurangzeb's rule, establishing the Maratha Empire as a prominent force in the Deccan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign saw a decline in which of the following aspects of Mughal administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military expansion",
                    "Economic prosperity",
                    "Cultural patronage",
                    "Centralized control"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cultural patronage",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's reign marked a decline in Mughal patronage of culture and the arts, contrasting with the more vibrant cultural scene under his predecessors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Aurangzeb's policies was seen as an attempt to reinforce Islamic orthodoxy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Encouragement of Persian literature",
                    "Support for Sufi practices",
                    "Destruction of Hindu temples",
                    "Promotion of Mughal architecture"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Destruction of Hindu temples",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s destruction of Hindu temples was seen as an attempt to reinforce Islamic orthodoxy and diminish Hindu influence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "During Aurangzeb's rule, which of the following regions did not come under Mughal control?",
                  "options": ["Punjab", "Gujarat", "Bengal", "South India"],
                  "answer": "South India",
                  "explanation": "Despite Aurangzeb's efforts, South India remained largely outside Mughal control and saw the rise of regional powers such as the Marathas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's approach to governance was characterized by:",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralization of power",
                    "Decentralization of authority",
                    "Increased religious tolerance",
                    "Expansion of trade networks"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralization of power",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's approach to governance involved centralizing power and reducing the autonomy of regional rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The establishment of which institution was a result of Aurangzeb’s religious policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mughal Imperial Court",
                    "The Sikh Empire",
                    "The Rajput Confederation",
                    "The Maratha Confederacy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Sikh Empire",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's religious policies and conflicts with the Sikh community contributed to the establishment of the Sikh Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policy towards the Rajputs was aimed at:",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthening alliances",
                    "Punishing rebellions",
                    "Encouraging conversion to Islam",
                    "Securing trade routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Punishing rebellions",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policy towards the Rajputs was often aimed at punishing rebellions and asserting Mughal control over Rajput territories."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which significant Mughal architectural project was completed during Aurangzeb's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Taj Mahal",
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jama Masjid",
                  "explanation": "The Jama Masjid in Delhi was completed during Aurangzeb’s reign, reflecting his focus on Islamic religious architecture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's rule was marked by his efforts to:",
                  "options": [
                    "Expand the Mughal Empire's territory",
                    "Promote religious harmony",
                    "Increase trade with Europe",
                    "Support local arts and culture"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expand the Mughal Empire's territory",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb focused on expanding the Mughal Empire's territory, especially through his campaigns in the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb’s policies led to significant conflicts with which of the following groups?",
                  "options": ["Marathas", "Rajputs", "Mysoreans", "Sikhs"],
                  "answer": "Marathas",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb's policies, particularly in the Deccan, led to significant conflicts with the Marathas, who emerged as a major regional power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb’s attempt to capture which territory was a significant part of his military campaigns?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Delhi", "Kabul", "Golconda"],
                  "answer": "Golconda",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s military campaigns included significant efforts to capture Golconda, a major fortress in the Deccan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was known for his detailed chronicle of Aurangzeb's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Abu'l-Fazl",
                    "Badayuni",
                    "Khafi Khan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Khafi Khan",
                  "explanation": "Khafi Khan was a prominent historian who chronicled Aurangzeb’s reign, providing valuable insights into that period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's military expeditions were primarily focused on which region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Central Asia",
                    "The Deccan",
                    "The Punjab",
                    "The Ganges Valley"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb’s military expeditions were largely focused on the Deccan region, where he sought to expand Mughal control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical event marked the end of Aurangzeb’s extensive military campaigns in the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Treaty of Purandar",
                    "The Battle of Talikota",
                    "The Fall of Bijapur",
                    "The Siege of Golconda"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Fall of Bijapur",
                  "explanation": "The fall of Bijapur in 1686 marked a significant end to Aurangzeb’s extensive military campaigns in the Deccan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's reign is often associated with which significant architectural project?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Taj Mahal",
                    "Badshahi Mosque"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Badshahi Mosque",
                  "explanation": "The Badshahi Mosque, constructed during Aurangzeb’s reign, is one of the notable architectural projects from his period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key region was notably resistant to Aurangzeb's rule during his reign?",
                  "options": ["Punjab", "Bengal", "Kashmir", "South India"],
                  "answer": "South India",
                  "explanation": "South India remained resistant to Mughal control during Aurangzeb’s reign, with several regional powers, including the Marathas, maintaining independence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Aurangzeb's policy on religious matters included:",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebuilding Hindu temples",
                    "Supporting Hindu festivals",
                    "Imposing stricter Islamic laws",
                    "Encouraging Hindu-Muslim dialogue"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Imposing stricter Islamic laws",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb imposed stricter Islamic laws and was known for his conservative approach to religion."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Shah Jahan",
          "description": [
            "Shah Jahan is best known for commissioning the construction of the Taj Mahal.",
            "Shah Jahan was a Mughal emperor who loved his wife very much.",
            "When his wife died, he was very sad, To remember his wife, he built a beautiful tomb called the Taj Mahal.",
            "The Taj Mahal is one of the most famous buildings in the world.",
            "Shah Jahan was also known for his beautiful gardens and palaces."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahān's father?",
                  "options": ["Jahangir", "Akbar", "Babur", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān was the third son of the Mughal emperor Jahangir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which city did Shah Jahān build the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Lahore", "Agra", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Agra",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal, Shah Jahān's masterpiece, is located in Agra, India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahān's original name before he became emperor?",
                  "options": ["Khurram", "Babur", "Akbar", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Khurram",
                  "explanation": "Before becoming emperor, Shah Jahān was known as Prince Khurram."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor built the Red Fort in Delhi?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahān", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahān",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān commissioned the construction of the Red Fort in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Shah Jahān's favorite queen?",
                  "options": [
                    "Arjūmand Bānū Begum",
                    "Nur Jahan",
                    "Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Razia Sultana"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mumtaz Mahal",
                  "explanation": "Mumtaz Mahal, Shah Jahān's favorite queen, is honored with the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Shah Jahān transfer his capital to in 1648?",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Delhi", "Lahore", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān moved his capital from Agra to Delhi in 1648, creating Shāhjahānābād."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahān’s reign saw the annexation of which Deccan state?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ahmadnagar",
                    "Bijapur",
                    "Golconda",
                    "Vijayanagara"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ahmadnagar",
                  "explanation": "Ahmadnagar was annexed during Shah Jahān's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler built the Pearl Mosque in Agra?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Akbar", "Shah Jahān", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahān",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān built the Pearl Mosque (Motī Masjid) in Agra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Shah Jahān as Mughal emperor?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb", "Dara Shikoh"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb succeeded Shah Jahān after a struggle for succession."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahān’s approach towards his Hindu subjects?",
                  "options": ["Orthodox", "Intolerant", "Tolerant", "Neutral"],
                  "answer": "Tolerant",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān was relatively tolerant toward his Hindu subjects compared to some of his successors."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the birth name of Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": ["Khurram", "Shahab-ud-din", "Jahangir", "Akbar"],
                  "answer": "Khurram",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was born as Khurram before ascending to the Mughal throne."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Shah Jahan ascend to the Mughal throne?",
                  "options": ["1615", "1628", "1631", "1658"],
                  "answer": "1628",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan ascended the throne in 1628 following the death of his father, Jahangir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the mother of Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jodha Bai",
                    "Noor Jahan",
                    "Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Hamida Banu Begum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mumtaz Mahal",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan’s mother was Mumtaz Mahal, for whom the Taj Mahal was built."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan is best known for building which iconic monument?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Taj Mahal",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taj Mahal",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal, a mausoleum for his wife Mumtaz Mahal, is one of Shah Jahan’s most famous architectural achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Shah Jahan choose as the new capital of the Mughal Empire?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Agra", "Delhi", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan moved the Mughal capital to Delhi and constructed the Red Fort there."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan built the Peacock Throne, which was adorned with precious stones. Which gemstone was most prominent on the throne?",
                  "options": ["Ruby", "Diamond", "Emerald", "Sapphire"],
                  "answer": "Ruby",
                  "explanation": "The Peacock Throne featured a prominent ruby, making it a symbol of opulence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahan's favorite wife and the inspiration behind the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jodha Bai",
                    "Noor Jahan",
                    "Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Roshanara Begum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mumtaz Mahal",
                  "explanation": "Mumtaz Mahal, Shah Jahan’s favorite wife, was the inspiration for the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was Shah Jahan's father?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Humayun", "Akbar", "Jahangir"],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was the son of Emperor Jahangir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan was imprisoned by his own son. Which son was responsible for his imprisonment?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Shah Alam II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb imprisoned his father Shah Jahan after a struggle for power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is often referred to as the 'Golden Age' of which dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maurya Dynasty",
                    "Gupta Dynasty",
                    "Mughal Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mughal Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan’s reign is considered the 'Golden Age' of the Mughal Dynasty due to its architectural and cultural achievements."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan built many architectural marvels during his reign. Which of the following is NOT attributed to him?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Shalimar Gardens",
                    "Diwan-i-Khas",
                    "Lal Qila"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shalimar Gardens",
                  "explanation": "The Shalimar Gardens were built by Shah Jahan's grandfather, Akbar, not by Shah Jahan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was Shah Jahan's immediate successor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Jahandar Shah",
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Alamgir II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb succeeded Shah Jahan as the Mughal Emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The construction of the Taj Mahal began in which year?",
                  "options": ["1605", "1628", "1631", "1652"],
                  "answer": "1631",
                  "explanation": "Construction of the Taj Mahal began in 1631 and was completed in 1653."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which gemstone was used in abundance for the inlay work of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["Emerald", "Sapphire", "Jade", "Jasper"],
                  "answer": "Sapphire",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal’s inlay work prominently featured sapphires among other precious stones."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the original name of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qila-i-Mubarak",
                    "Rauza-i-Munawwara",
                    "Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Rohtas Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rauza-i-Munawwara",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was originally named Rauza-i-Munawwara, meaning 'Illuminated Tomb.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which city is the Red Fort located, which was built by Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Agra", "Delhi", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "The Red Fort, also known as Lal Qila, is located in Delhi and was constructed by Shah Jahan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which two rivers flank the city of Agra, where the Taj Mahal is located?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ganges and Yamuna",
                    "Indus and Jhelum",
                    "Godavari and Krishna",
                    "Tapti and Narmada"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ganges and Yamuna",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal is situated on the banks of the Yamuna River, and the city of Agra is near the confluence with the Ganges River."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Taj Mahal is primarily built using which architectural style?",
                  "options": ["Persian", "Ottoman", "Mughal", "Rajput"],
                  "answer": "Mughal",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal is a prime example of Mughal architecture, combining elements from Persian and Indian styles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many minarets surround the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["1", "2", "4", "8"],
                  "answer": "4",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal is surrounded by four minarets, one at each corner of the mausoleum."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan was known for his patronage of which art form?",
                  "options": [
                    "Miniature painting",
                    "Sculpture",
                    "Calligraphy",
                    "Dance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Calligraphy",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was a patron of calligraphy, which is reflected in the inscriptions and decorations of the Taj Mahal."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural marvel in Delhi was built by Shah Jahan to serve as his private audience hall?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diwan-i-Khas",
                    "Diwan-i-Am",
                    "Sheesh Mahal",
                    "Jahangir Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diwan-i-Khas",
                  "explanation": "The Diwan-i-Khas was built by Shah Jahan as his private audience hall, where he held private meetings with nobles and dignitaries."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign witnessed the completion of which monumental mosque in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Nizamuddin Dargah",
                    "Hazrat Qutub Sahib Dargah",
                    "Feroz Shah Kotla"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jama Masjid",
                  "explanation": "The Jama Masjid in Delhi, one of the largest mosques in India, was completed during Shah Jahan’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which fort was constructed by Shah Jahan in Lahore, Pakistan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Lahore Fort",
                    "Agra Fort",
                    "Shalimar Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Lahore Fort",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan commissioned the construction of the Lahore Fort, which stands as a testament to Mughal architecture in Pakistan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The construction of the Shalimar Bagh in Srinagar, Kashmir, was commissioned by Shah Jahan. Which Mughal garden does it resemble?",
                  "options": [
                    "Nishat Bagh",
                    "Shalamar Gardens, Lahore",
                    "Brindavan Gardens",
                    "Pinjore Gardens"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nishat Bagh",
                  "explanation": "The Shalimar Bagh in Srinagar closely resembles the Nishat Bagh in its layout and design, both being classic Mughal gardens."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is associated with the establishment of a new Mughal architectural style. What is it called?",
                  "options": [
                    "Indo-Islamic",
                    "Rajput-Mughal",
                    "Persian-Mughal",
                    "Deccan-Mughal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Persian-Mughal",
                  "explanation": "The Persian-Mughal architectural style, characterized by grand structures and intricate designs, flourished during Shah Jahan’s rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The construction of which city began during Shah Jahan's reign and was completed by his son Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": ["Fatehpur Sikri", "Jaipur", "Agra", "Hyderabad"],
                  "answer": "Hyderabad",
                  "explanation": "Hyderabad was established during Shah Jahan's reign and was completed by his successor, Aurangzeb."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Shah Jahan's eldest son, who was initially considered his heir?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Jahandar Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dara Shikoh",
                  "explanation": "Dara Shikoh was Shah Jahan’s eldest son and was initially seen as his successor before being overtaken by Aurangzeb."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Taj Mahal is dedicated to the memory of Shah Jahan's wife. How many years did it take to complete its construction?",
                  "options": ["10", "15", "20", "25"],
                  "answer": "20",
                  "explanation": "Construction of the Taj Mahal took approximately 20 years, from 1631 to 1653."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which precious gemstone was used for the finial of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["Sapphire", "Emerald", "Diamond", "Amethyst"],
                  "answer": "Emerald",
                  "explanation": "The finial of the Taj Mahal was adorned with a large emerald, along with other precious stones."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Shah Jahan's daughter, who was an accomplished poetess and was imprisoned by Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jahanara Begum",
                    "Roshanara Begum",
                    "Zeb-un-Nisa",
                    "Nadira Banu Begum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Zeb-un-Nisa",
                  "explanation": "Zeb-un-Nisa, Shah Jahan’s daughter, was known for her poetry and was imprisoned by Aurangzeb."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan introduced a new silver coin during his reign. What was it called?",
                  "options": ["Mohur", "Rupiya", "Dam", "Tanka"],
                  "answer": "Rupiya",
                  "explanation": "The Rupiya was introduced as a new silver coin during Shah Jahan’s rule and became widely used."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Persian poet was appointed as Shah Jahan's court poet?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Ghalib",
                    "Amir Khusrau",
                    "Faiz Ahmed Faiz",
                    "Mir Taqi Mir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Amir Khusrau",
                  "explanation": "Amir Khusrau, a renowned Persian poet, was appointed as the court poet during Shah Jahan’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous diamond, currently part of the British Crown Jewels, was owned by Shah Jahan before it was seized by the British?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hope Diamond",
                    "Koh-i-Noor",
                    "Orlov Diamond",
                    "Cullinan Diamond"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Koh-i-Noor",
                  "explanation": "The Koh-i-Noor diamond, once owned by Shah Jahan, is now part of the British Crown Jewels."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's rule saw significant advancements in which field of science?",
                  "options": ["Astronomy", "Medicine", "Chemistry", "Physics"],
                  "answer": "Astronomy",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan’s reign was marked by significant advancements in astronomy, including the construction of astronomical observatories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which European traveler visited Shah Jahan's court and wrote extensively about Mughal India in his travelogue?",
                  "options": [
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Vasco da Gama",
                    "Niccolò Machiavelli"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marco Polo",
                  "explanation": "Marco Polo, though his travels predated Shah Jahan, is often associated with extensive descriptions of Mughal India, albeit through historical accounts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary religion of Shah Jahan's court?",
                  "options": ["Islam", "Hinduism", "Sikhism", "Buddhism"],
                  "answer": "Islam",
                  "explanation": "The primary religion at Shah Jahan’s court was Islam, reflecting the Mughal Emperor's adherence to Islamic traditions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan built the city of Shahjahanabad, which later became known as:",
                  "options": ["Mumbai", "Delhi", "Lahore", "Kolkata"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Shahjahanabad, the city built by Shah Jahan, later became known as Delhi, which remains its name today."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign witnessed the expansion of Mughal territories in which direction?",
                  "options": ["North", "South", "East", "West"],
                  "answer": "East",
                  "explanation": "During Shah Jahan’s reign, the Mughal Empire expanded its territories primarily towards the East."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural feature of the Taj Mahal symbolizes the gateway to paradise?",
                  "options": ["Dome", "Minaret", "Arch", "Garden"],
                  "answer": "Minaret",
                  "explanation": "The minarets of the Taj Mahal are symbolic of the gateway to paradise, framing the central mausoleum."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan commissioned the translation of which ancient Hindu text into Persian during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahabharata",
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Bhagavad Gita",
                    "Rigveda"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ramayana",
                  "explanation": "The Ramayana was translated into Persian during Shah Jahan’s reign, reflecting his interest in cultural and literary works."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahān’s primary motivation behind the construction of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "To commemorate his wife",
                    "To celebrate his reign",
                    "To honor his father",
                    "To establish a new capital"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To commemorate his wife",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was built by Shah Jahān in memory of his favorite queen, Mumtaz Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler’s rule saw the annexation of Ahmadnagar?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahān", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahān",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān’s reign saw the annexation of the Deccan state of Ahmadnagar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the outcome of Shah Jahān’s attempts to reconquer Balkh?",
                  "options": [
                    "Success",
                    "Failure",
                    "Partial success",
                    "No attempt"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Failure",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān’s attempts to reconquer Balkh were unsuccessful, and it was ultimately lost."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant fortress did the Persians recapture from the Mughals during Shah Jahān’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Kandahār", "Balkh", "Badakhshān", "Agra"],
                  "answer": "Kandahār",
                  "explanation": "The Persians recaptured the fortress of Kandahār from the Mughals in 1649."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Shah Jahān’s sons emerged victorious in the struggle for succession?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Murād Bakhsh",
                    "Shah Shujāʿ"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb emerged victorious in the struggle for succession and declared himself emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahān’s primary architectural achievement in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Humayun's Tomb",
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Rashtrapati Bhavan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jama Masjid",
                  "explanation": "In Delhi, Shah Jahān’s significant architectural achievement was the Jama Masjid."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Shah Jahān’s reign impact the Mughal treasury?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased revenues",
                    "Financial stability",
                    "Significant depletion",
                    "No impact"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Significant depletion",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān’s extensive building projects and military campaigns significantly depleted the Mughal treasury."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major building project was commissioned by Shah Jahān in Agra besides the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri",
                    "Motī Masjid",
                    "Qutub Minar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Motī Masjid",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān commissioned the Motī Masjid (Pearl Mosque) in Agra in addition to the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahān’s approach to religious tolerance during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Highly orthodox",
                    "Very tolerant",
                    "Moderately tolerant",
                    "Indifferent"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Moderately tolerant",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān was more orthodox than his grandfather Akbar but less so than Aurangzeb, showing moderate tolerance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important Mughal city did Shah Jahān establish as a new capital?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Delhi", "Agra", "Fatehpur Sikri"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān established Delhi as the new Mughal capital and named it Shāhjahānābād."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "In which city was Shah Jahan born?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Delhi", "Agra", "Mumbai"],
                  "answer": "Lahore",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was born in Lahore, which is now in Pakistan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahan's father?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb", "Babur"],
                  "answer": "Jahangir",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was the son of Emperor Jahangir."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was Shah Jahan's grandfather?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Akbar",
                  "explanation": "Akbar the Great was Shah Jahan's grandfather."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahan's beloved wife, known for whom the Taj Mahal was built?",
                  "options": [
                    "Arjaumnad Banu",
                    "Nur Jahan",
                    "Ruqaiya Sultan Begum",
                    "Jodha Bai"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Arjaumnad Banu",
                  "explanation": "Arjaumnad Banu, also known as Mumtaz Mahal, was Shah Jahan's beloved wife for whom the Taj Mahal was constructed."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which event marked Shah Jahan's end of reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "His assassination",
                    "His abdication",
                    "His imprisonment",
                    "His death"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His death",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's reign ended with his death in 1666."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who executed Shah Jahan's brother Shahyar?",
                  "options": ["Jahangir", "Akbar", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan executed his brother Shahyar, who conspired against him."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous monument did Shah Jahan commission for his wife?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Taj Mahal",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taj Mahal",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was commissioned by Shah Jahan in memory of his wife Mumtaz Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main architectural material used for the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red sandstone",
                    "Limestone",
                    "Marble",
                    "Granite"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marble",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal is constructed primarily of white marble."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahan’s son that assumed power during his illness?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Shah Shuja",
                    "Jahangir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb seized power while Shah Jahan was ill."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Persian poet wrote poems dedicated to Dara Shikoh, Shah Jahan’s son?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mirza Ghalib",
                    "Amir Khusrau",
                    "Saadi Shirazi",
                    "Hafez Shirazi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Saadi Shirazi",
                  "explanation": "Saadi Shirazi wrote a collection of poems dedicated to Dara Shikoh."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What year did Shah Jahan begin the construction of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["1620", "1632", "1648", "1656"],
                  "answer": "1632",
                  "explanation": "The construction of the Taj Mahal began in 1632."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many artisans were involved in building the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": ["10,000", "15,000", "20,000", "25,000"],
                  "answer": "20,000",
                  "explanation": "Around 20,000 artisans were employed in the construction of the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor is credited with defeating Mewar?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan defeated Mewar, a state his grandfather Akbar could not."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Shah Jahan's significant military contributions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing naval fleets",
                    "Producing armaments",
                    "Forming alliances with foreign powers",
                    "Reforming tax policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Producing armaments",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan contributed to the Mughal military by producing armaments."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What architectural feature is prominent in the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Minarets",
                    "Golden dome",
                    "Stone carvings",
                    "Reflecting pool"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Minarets",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal is well-known for its minarets, which contribute to its symmetrical design."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Shah Jahan’s approach to administration before becoming emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Administering Bengal and Gujarat",
                    "Studying at a royal academy",
                    "Engaging in diplomatic missions",
                    "Leading military campaigns in Central Asia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administering Bengal and Gujarat",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan governed regions such as Bengal and Gujarat before becoming emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who were the rivals Shah Jahan eliminated to secure his position?",
                  "options": [
                    "Nawab of Bengal",
                    "Brothers and other claimants",
                    "Rajput rulers",
                    "Safavid Empire representatives"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Brothers and other claimants",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan eliminated rivals, including his brother Shahyar, to secure his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the primary theme represented in the Taj Mahal’s inscriptions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hindu scriptures",
                    "Islamic prayers",
                    "Buddhist texts",
                    "Persian literature"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Islamic prayers",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal's inscriptions are primarily Islamic in nature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Shah Jahan's eldest son who was a rival during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Shah Shuja",
                    "Jahangir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was Shah Jahan's son who rivaled Dara Shikoh during Shah Jahan's illness."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for the Taj Mahal’s protection during WWII?",
                  "options": [
                    "To prevent theft",
                    "To avoid air raids",
                    "To maintain structural integrity",
                    "To safeguard from vandalism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To avoid air raids",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was protected during WWII to prevent damage from potential air raids."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a region governed by Shah Jahan before he became emperor?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Deccan", "Gujarat", "Punjab"],
                  "answer": "Punjab",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan governed regions such as Bengal, Deccan, and Gujarat, but not Punjab, before becoming emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the predominant architectural style used in the construction of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Persian",
                    "Islamic",
                    "Indian",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of the above",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal features an amalgamation of Persian, Islamic, and Indian architectural styles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal institution declined during Shah Jahan's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mansabdari system",
                    "Jagirdari system",
                    "Zamindari system",
                    "Sufi order"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mansabdari system",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's reign saw the decline of the Mansabdari system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of the Diwan-i-Am built by Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Judicial proceedings",
                    "Public gatherings",
                    "Royal banquets",
                    "Royal coronations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public gatherings",
                  "explanation": "The Diwan-i-Am was used for public gatherings and receiving citizens."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the architect primarily responsible for the design of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ustad Ahmad Lahori",
                    "Ismail Khan",
                    "Mirza Ghiyas",
                    "Shah Jahan himself"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ustad Ahmad Lahori",
                  "explanation": "Ustad Ahmad Lahori was the chief architect of the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant event occurred in the Mughal Empire during Shah Jahan's reign related to the Deccan region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion into Deccan",
                    "Rebellion in Deccan",
                    "Treaty with Deccan sultanates",
                    "Establishment of a new capital in Deccan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion into Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan expanded Mughal territories into the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal ruler attempted to rival Shah Jahan's architectural achievements?",
                  "options": ["Aurangzeb", "Jahangir", "Akbar", "Babur"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb, Shah Jahan's successor, is noted for his own architectural projects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Shah Jahan's sons was known for his Sufi influence?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Shah Shuja",
                    "Jahangir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dara Shikoh",
                  "explanation": "Dara Shikoh was known for his interest in Sufism and his attempts to reconcile Hinduism and Islam."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Shah Jahan's reign impact the Mughal art and culture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promoted Indo-Persian art",
                    "Declined architectural projects",
                    "Reduced courtly patronage",
                    "Shifted focus to military conquests"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoted Indo-Persian art",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's reign is renowned for its promotion of Indo-Persian art and culture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major change did Shah Jahan make to the Mughal Empire’s administrative structure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized administration",
                    "Decentralized power to regional rulers",
                    "Increased autonomy for nobles",
                    "Established a new judicial system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized administration",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan worked on centralizing the administration of the Mughal Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What specific event led Shah Jahan to build the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military victory",
                    "Death of Mumtaz Mahal",
                    "Coronation",
                    "Rebellion suppression"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Death of Mumtaz Mahal",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was built in memory of Shah Jahan’s wife, Mumtaz Mahal, who died during childbirth."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary feature of Shah Jahan’s rule that was emphasized in his architectural projects?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military fortifications",
                    "Religious monuments",
                    "Symbol of love and luxury",
                    "Economic development"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Symbol of love and luxury",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan’s architectural projects, including the Taj Mahal, emphasized symbols of love and luxury."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major city did Shah Jahan move the Mughal capital to?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore", "Fatehpur Sikri"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan moved the Mughal capital from Agra to Delhi, where he established Shahjahanabad."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Shah Jahan belong to?",
                  "options": ["Ghaznavid", "Mughal", "Suri", "Rajput"],
                  "answer": "Mughal",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan was a member of the Mughal dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Persian ruler’s ambassador was a notable figure during Shah Jahan’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shah Abbas I",
                    "Nader Shah",
                    "Khalid I",
                    "Akbar II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shah Abbas I",
                  "explanation": "Shah Abbas I of Persia had notable diplomatic interactions with Shah Jahan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for the construction delay of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lack of resources",
                    "Political instability",
                    "Natural calamities",
                    "Artistic design changes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Political instability",
                  "explanation": "Political instability and conflicts delayed the construction of the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the fate of Shah Jahan after he was deposed by Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": [
                    "Executed",
                    "Imprisoned in Agra Fort",
                    "Exiled to Persia",
                    "Placed under house arrest in Delhi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Imprisoned in Agra Fort",
                  "explanation": "After being deposed by Aurangzeb, Shah Jahan was imprisoned in Agra Fort."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor's reign saw the largest number of architectural projects in the empire?",
                  "options": ["Babur", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan"],
                  "answer": "Shah Jahan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan’s reign is known for its numerous and grand architectural projects, including the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the significance of the reflecting pool in the Taj Mahal’s design?",
                  "options": [
                    "Water source for the mausoleum",
                    "Symbol of eternal love",
                    "Cooling mechanism",
                    "Decoration only"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Symbol of eternal love",
                  "explanation": "The reflecting pool in front of the Taj Mahal symbolizes the eternal love between Shah Jahan and Mumtaz Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which notable Mughal emperor was Shah Jahan’s contemporary and rival for power?",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb", "Babur"],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was Shah Jahan's contemporary and eventually rival for power, leading to Shah Jahan's imprisonment."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 11,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Shah Jahān become emperor?",
                  "options": ["1627", "1628", "1629", "1630"],
                  "answer": "1628",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān declared himself emperor in February 1628 after Jahāngīr’s death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant architectural project did Shah Jahān undertake in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Hawa Mahal",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Red Fort",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān built the Red Fort in Delhi, which remains a significant landmark."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Deccan state was forced to become a tributary during Shah Jahān’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Bijapur", "Golconda", "Mysore", "Vijayanagara"],
                  "answer": "Golconda",
                  "explanation": "Golconda was forced to become a tributary of the Mughal Empire during Shah Jahān’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the Persian governor who surrendered Kandahār to the Mughals?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ali Mardan Khan",
                    "Mirza Kamran",
                    "Shah Abbas",
                    "Nizam Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ali Mardan Khan",
                  "explanation": "Ali Mardan Khan, the Persian governor of Kandahār, surrendered the fortress to the Mughals."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Shah Jahān build in Agra besides the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Fatehpur Sikri"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jama Masjid",
                  "explanation": "Besides the Taj Mahal, Shah Jahān also built the Jama Masjid in Agra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Shah Jahān transfer his capital to Delhi?",
                  "options": ["1645", "1646", "1647", "1648"],
                  "answer": "1648",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān transferred his capital from Agra to Delhi in 1648."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Shah Jahān’s sons was NOT involved in the struggle for succession?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Dara Shikoh",
                    "Shah Shuja",
                    "Murad Bakhsh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shah Shuja",
                  "explanation": "Shah Shuja was involved in the struggle for succession, along with Dara Shikoh, Aurangzeb, and Murad Bakhsh."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the reason for the Mughal Empire’s financial strain during Shah Jahān’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Wars in the Deccan",
                    "Building projects",
                    "External invasions",
                    "Religious conflicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Wars in the Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān’s wars in the Deccan and attempts to recover territories caused financial strain."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the architect of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ustad Ahmad Lahori",
                    "Chand Bibi",
                    "Raja Todar Mal",
                    "Ali Mardan Khan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ustad Ahmad Lahori",
                  "explanation": "The Taj Mahal was designed by Ustad Ahmad Lahori, a prominent Mughal architect."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Shah Jahān’s reign influence the decline of the Mughal Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military defeats",
                    "Economic strain",
                    "Religious intolerance",
                    "Political instability"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Economic strain",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahān’s military campaigns and extensive building projects contributed to the economic strain and eventual decline of the empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 12,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which city served as the Mughal capital before Shah Jahan moved it to Delhi?",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Lahore", "Jaipur", "Fatehpur Sikri"],
                  "answer": "Fatehpur Sikri",
                  "explanation": "Before Shah Jahan moved the capital to Delhi, Fatehpur Sikri served as the Mughal capital under Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who served as the chief architect of the Taj Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ustad Ahmad Lahauri",
                    "Ustad Isa",
                    "Ustad Hamid",
                    "Ustad Mirza Ghiyas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ustad Ahmad Lahauri",
                  "explanation": "Ustad Ahmad Lahauri, a prominent architect of the Mughal era, was the chief architect behind the Taj Mahal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is often referred to as the 'Diamond Age' due to his fondness for which precious gemstone?",
                  "options": ["Ruby", "Diamond", "Emerald", "Amethyst"],
                  "answer": "Diamond",
                  "explanation": "The term 'Diamond Age' reflects Shah Jahan's significant use and admiration for diamonds in his architectural works and personal treasures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important Mughal administrative post did Shah Jahan create during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diwan-i-Wazarat",
                    "Mir Bakshi",
                    "Qazi-ul-Quzat",
                    "Wazir-e-Ala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mir Bakshi",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan established the post of Mir Bakshi, responsible for military and financial administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's rule saw the growth of which form of poetry that became popular in the Mughal court?",
                  "options": ["Ghazal", "Sonnet", "Haiku", "Ballad"],
                  "answer": "Ghazal",
                  "explanation": "The Ghazal, a form of lyrical poetry, flourished during Shah Jahan's reign and was a significant aspect of Mughal court culture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor succeeded Shah Jahan after his death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Alamgir II",
                    "Muhammad Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb, Shah Jahan's son, succeeded him as the Mughal emperor after his death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign witnessed the construction of which famous astronomical observatory in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jantar Mantar",
                    "Nila Gumbad",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Buland Darwaza"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jantar Mantar",
                  "explanation": "The Jantar Mantar in Delhi, constructed during Shah Jahan's reign, was an important astronomical observatory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous historical figure was a contemporary of Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Julius Caesar",
                    "Genghis Khan",
                    "Queen Elizabeth I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Queen Elizabeth I",
                  "explanation": "Queen Elizabeth I was a contemporary of Shah Jahan, both of whom ruled during the 16th and 17th centuries."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The construction of the Shalimar Bagh in Srinagar, Kashmir, was commissioned by Shah Jahan. Which Mughal garden does it resemble?",
                  "options": [
                    "Nishat Bagh",
                    "Shalamar Gardens, Lahore",
                    "Brindavan Gardens",
                    "Pinjore Gardens"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nishat Bagh",
                  "explanation": "The Shalimar Bagh in Srinagar bears resemblance to the Nishat Bagh, both being exquisite examples of Mughal garden design."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural feature of the Red Fort in Delhi is associated with the Mughal emperor Shah Jahan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Moti Masjid",
                    "Rang Mahal",
                    "Diwan-i-Khas",
                    "Hayat Bakhsh Bagh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diwan-i-Khas",
                  "explanation": "The Diwan-i-Khas, or Hall of Private Audience, is a notable feature of the Red Fort built by Shah Jahan."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 13,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "The construction of which grand mosque in Lahore was started by Shah Jahan but completed by his son Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": [
                    "Badshahi Mosque",
                    "Wazir Khan Mosque",
                    "Sunehri Mosque",
                    "Masjid-e-Zeb-un-Nisa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Badshahi Mosque",
                  "explanation": "The Badshahi Mosque, an architectural masterpiece, was initiated by Shah Jahan and finished by Aurangzeb."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was born to Shah Jahan and Mumtaz Mahal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Muhammad Shah",
                    "Aurangzeb",
                    "Alamgir II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aurangzeb",
                  "explanation": "Aurangzeb was the son of Shah Jahan and Mumtaz Mahal, and he succeeded his father as the Mughal emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan built a white marble mausoleum in memory of his father. What is it called?",
                  "options": [
                    "Humayun's Tomb",
                    "Safdarjung's Tomb",
                    "Akbar's Tomb",
                    "Sher Shah Suri's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Humayun's Tomb",
                  "explanation": "Humayun's Tomb, constructed by Shah Jahan, is a notable example of Mughal architecture and is dedicated to his father, Humayun."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Mughal garden in Delhi was commissioned by Shah Jahan and is now a UNESCO World Heritage Site?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shalimar Bagh",
                    "Nishat Bagh",
                    "Mehtab Bagh",
                    "Roshanara Bagh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mehtab Bagh",
                  "explanation": "Mehtab Bagh, located in Delhi, was commissioned by Shah Jahan and is renowned for its scenic beauty and historical significance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the fort built by Shah Jahan in Agra, which served as the main residence of the Mughal emperors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Agra Fort",
                    "Jaipur Fort",
                    "Golconda Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Agra Fort",
                  "explanation": "The Agra Fort, built by Shah Jahan, served as a primary residence for Mughal emperors before the construction of the Red Fort."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan established a new city, Shahjahanabad, in which present-day country?",
                  "options": ["India", "Pakistan", "Bangladesh", "Afghanistan"],
                  "answer": "India",
                  "explanation": "Shahjahanabad, founded by Shah Jahan, is located in present-day India and is now known as Old Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Mughal general and noble served as Shah Jahan's prime minister?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mir Jumla",
                    "Raja Man Singh",
                    "Asaf Khan",
                    "Raja Todar Mal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Asaf Khan",
                  "explanation": "Asaf Khan was a prominent Mughal noble and served as the prime minister during Shah Jahan's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is known for its remarkable achievements in which form of Mughal art?",
                  "options": [
                    "Miniature painting",
                    "Sculpture",
                    "Calligraphy",
                    "Tapestry"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Miniature painting",
                  "explanation": "The Mughal era under Shah Jahan is renowned for its exquisite miniature paintings, which flourished during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary language of Shah Jahan's court?",
                  "options": ["Persian", "Urdu", "Hindi", "Arabic"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "Persian was the main language of the Mughal court during Shah Jahan's reign, used for administrative and cultural purposes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mughal emperor was born during Shah Jahan's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bahadur Shah I",
                    "Muhammad Shah",
                    "Alamgir II",
                    "Shah Alam II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahadur Shah I",
                  "explanation": "Bahadur Shah I was born during Shah Jahan's reign and succeeded him as the Mughal emperor."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 14,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which European power established trade relations with the Mughal Empire during Shah Jahan's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "British East India Company",
                    "Dutch East India Company",
                    "French East India Company",
                    "Portuguese East India Company"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dutch East India Company",
                  "explanation": "The Dutch East India Company established trade relations with the Mughal Empire during Shah Jahan's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is associated with the flourishing of which form of Mughal literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Persian poetry",
                    "Urdu poetry",
                    "Sanskrit literature",
                    "Tamil literature"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Persian poetry",
                  "explanation": "Persian poetry flourished during Shah Jahan's reign, reflecting the rich literary culture of the Mughal court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's love for architecture and construction was greatly influenced by which historical figure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Akbar the Great",
                    "Ashoka the Great",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Harsha Vardhana"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Akbar the Great",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's architectural ambitions were influenced by Akbar the Great's earlier contributions to Mughal architecture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous diamond, known as the 'Great Table Diamond,' was owned by Shah Jahan before it was lost?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hope Diamond",
                    "Koh-i-Noor",
                    "Orlov Diamond",
                    "Cullinan Diamond"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hope Diamond",
                  "explanation": "The Hope Diamond, once owned by Shah Jahan, is renowned for its historical significance and unique blue color."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which event marked the end of Shah Jahan's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "His assassination",
                    "His abdication",
                    "His imprisonment",
                    "His death"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His death",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's reign ended with his death, after which his son Aurangzeb succeeded him as emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is known for its splendid court culture and luxurious lifestyle influenced by the Persian:",
                  "options": [
                    "Safavid Empire",
                    "Ottoman Empire",
                    "Achaemenid Empire",
                    "Sasanian Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Safavid Empire",
                  "explanation": "The court culture and luxurious lifestyle during Shah Jahan's reign were influenced by the Persian Safavid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The construction of which grand mosque in Delhi was started by Shah Jahan but completed by his son Aurangzeb?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Moti Masjid",
                    "Fatehpuri Masjid",
                    "Sunni Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jama Masjid",
                  "explanation": "The Jama Masjid in Delhi, a prominent Mughal mosque, was initiated by Shah Jahan and completed by Aurangzeb."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main material used in the construction of the Red Fort in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red sandstone",
                    "Marble",
                    "Limestone",
                    "Granite"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Red sandstone",
                  "explanation": "The Red Fort in Delhi is primarily constructed from red sandstone, giving it its distinctive color and name."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan built the Diwan-i-Am, which served as the public audience hall. What was its purpose?",
                  "options": [
                    "Judicial proceedings",
                    "Royal banquets",
                    "Public gatherings",
                    "Royal coronations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public gatherings",
                  "explanation": "The Diwan-i-Am was used for public gatherings where the emperor interacted with his subjects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Shah Jahan's reign is often described as the peak of Mughal:",
                  "options": [
                    "Military power",
                    "Art and architecture",
                    "Economic prosperity",
                    "Political stability"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Art and architecture",
                  "explanation": "Shah Jahan's reign is celebrated as the pinnacle of Mughal art and architecture, marked by masterpieces like the Taj Mahal."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },

    {
      "topicName": "Vijayanagara Empire",
      "subtopics": [
        {
          "subtopicName": "Krishna Deva Raya",
          "description": [
            "Krishna Deva Raya was the most celebrated ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire.",
            "Krishna Deva Raya was a king of the Vijayanagara Empire in South India.",
            "He was a very wise and powerful king.",
            "Krishna Deva Raya built many beautiful temples and palaces.",
            "He was a great warrior and fought many battles to protect his kingdom.",
            "He loved art, music, and literature."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Krishnadeva Raya’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military expansion",
                    "Cultural development",
                    "Trade improvement",
                    "Religious reform"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cultural development",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya focused on cultural development, particularly in promoting Telugu literature and art."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which poet was part of Krishnadeva Raya's court?",
                  "options": ["Vijayananda", "Peddanna", "Nannaya", "Bhadra"],
                  "answer": "Peddanna",
                  "explanation": "Peddanna, also known as Ayyalaraju Ramabhadra, was a prominent poet in Krishnadeva Raya's court and contributed significantly to Telugu literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the key diplomatic strategies used by Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alliances with neighboring kingdoms",
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Trade agreements",
                    "Religious conversions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alliances with neighboring kingdoms",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya formed strategic alliances with neighboring kingdoms to strengthen his empire’s position."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous temple was constructed during Krishnadeva Raya's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Meenakshi Temple",
                    "Virupaksha Temple",
                    "Ramanathaswamy Temple",
                    "Kailasanath Temple"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Virupaksha Temple",
                  "explanation": "The Virupaksha Temple in Hampi was one of the significant architectural projects during Krishnadeva Raya's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Krishnadeva Raya's contribution to South Indian trade?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing new trade routes",
                    "Expanding maritime trade",
                    "Promoting local crafts",
                    "Enhancing internal trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expanding maritime trade",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya expanded maritime trade, which contributed to the economic prosperity of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these was not a part of Krishnadeva Raya's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land revenue reforms",
                    "Artistic patronage",
                    "Religious persecution",
                    "Military campaigns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious persecution",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was known for his patronage of arts and military campaigns, but he did not engage in religious persecution."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant achievement in architecture during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Building a massive fort",
                    "Constructing a grand palace",
                    "Developing extensive irrigation systems",
                    "Erecting monumental gateways"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Developing extensive irrigation systems",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya is renowned for his development of extensive irrigation systems, which greatly benefited agriculture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian provides detailed accounts of Krishnadeva Raya's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sleeman",
                    "Abdur Razzaq",
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Marco Polo"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abdur Razzaq",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzaq, a Persian ambassador, provides detailed accounts of Krishnadeva Raya’s reign and the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural style was prominent during Krishnadeva Raya's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dravidian",
                    "Indo-Saracenic",
                    "Islamic",
                    "Gothic"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dravidian",
                  "explanation": "The Dravidian architectural style was prominent during Krishnadeva Raya's rule, characterized by elaborate temples and structures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which literary work is attributed to Krishna Deva Raya, reflecting his patronage of literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Amuktamalyada",
                    "Vasavadatta",
                    "Padmavat",
                    "Kumarasambhavam"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Amuktamalyada",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Deva Raya is renowned for his patronage of literature, and 'Amuktamalyada' is a famous work attributed to him, written in Telugu."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Krishnadeva Raya’s role in the arts?",
                  "options": [
                    "Collector of artworks",
                    "Patron and promoter",
                    "Art critic",
                    "Museum curator"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patron and promoter",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was a patron and promoter of the arts, supporting various artists and poets during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Krishnadeva Raya's rule on literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decline of literary traditions",
                    "Increased literary output",
                    "Restriction on literary freedom",
                    "Promotion of foreign literature"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased literary output",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya's rule saw an increase in literary output, particularly in Telugu literature, due to his support and patronage."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these was a key military campaign led by Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Campaign against the Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Invasion of Sri Lanka",
                    "Campaign in Gujarat",
                    "Conflict with the Mughals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Campaign against the Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya led successful military campaigns against the Bahmani Sultanate, expanding the Vijayanagara Empire’s territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Krishnadeva Raya contribute to the administration of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "By establishing a code of laws",
                    "By organizing efficient revenue collection",
                    "By decentralizing power",
                    "By limiting bureaucratic roles"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By organizing efficient revenue collection",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya improved the administration of his empire by organizing efficient revenue collection systems."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary language of the court during Krishnadeva Raya's rule?",
                  "options": ["Kannada", "Tamil", "Telugu", "Sanskrit"],
                  "answer": "Telugu",
                  "explanation": "Telugu was the primary language of the court during Krishnadeva Raya's rule, reflecting his promotion of the language."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a major architectural feature during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Step wells",
                    "Fortified cities",
                    "Grand palaces",
                    "Victory arches"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Step wells",
                  "explanation": "Step wells were a major architectural feature during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign, designed to manage water resources effectively."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Krishnadeva Raya’s approach to education?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing schools",
                    "Promoting Sanskrit education",
                    "Supporting scholars and poets",
                    "Focusing on military training"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Supporting scholars and poets",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya supported scholars and poets, contributing to the flourishing of literature and education in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the key achievements of Krishna Deva Raya’s reign in the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of the empire into South East Asia",
                    "Establishment of a new capital city",
                    "Revival of the empire’s economy and trade",
                    "Introduction of a new legal code"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Revival of the empire’s economy and trade",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Deva Raya is known for reviving the economy and enhancing trade during his reign, contributing significantly to the prosperity of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous work was written during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Amuktamalyada",
                    "Mahabharata",
                    "Bhagavad Gita"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Amuktamalyada",
                  "explanation": "The epic poem 'Amuktamalyada,' written in Telugu, was composed during Krishnadeva Raya's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major trade commodity during Krishnadeva Raya’s era?",
                  "options": [
                    "Spices",
                    "Textiles",
                    "Jewelry",
                    "Precious metals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spices",
                  "explanation": "Spices were a major trade commodity during Krishnadeva Raya’s era, contributing to the empire’s economic prosperity."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which city was the capital of Krishnadeva Raya’s empire?",
                  "options": ["Hampi", "Delhi", "Jaipur", "Hyderabad"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "Hampi was the capital city of Krishnadeva Raya’s Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a notable feature of Krishnadeva Raya’s military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Naval dominance",
                    "Guerrilla warfare",
                    "Use of war elephants",
                    "Siege tactics"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Use of war elephants",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was known for effectively using war elephants in his military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Krishnadeva Raya’s approach towards education?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promotion of Persian education",
                    "Support for Sanskrit learning",
                    "Encouragement of Telugu scholars",
                    "Focus on military training"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Encouragement of Telugu scholars",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya supported and encouraged Telugu scholars and literary figures during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous poet was a contemporary of Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Tulsidas",
                    "Vijayananda",
                    "Tenali Raman"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tenali Raman",
                  "explanation": "Tenali Raman was a renowned poet and court jester who lived during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant aspect of Krishnadeva Raya’s foreign policy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alliance with the Portuguese",
                    "Expanding trade with China",
                    "Neutrality in regional conflicts",
                    "Military campaigns in South East Asia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alliance with the Portuguese",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya maintained an alliance with the Portuguese to strengthen his empire's trade and military positions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a notable architectural achievement during Krishna Deva Raya's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hampi's Virupaksha Temple",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Gateway of India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hampi's Virupaksha Temple",
                  "explanation": "During Krishna Deva Raya's reign, the Virupaksha Temple in Hampi was significantly developed and is a notable architectural achievement from that period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religious community did Krishnadeva Raya support?",
                  "options": ["Hinduism", "Islam", "Buddhism", "Jainism"],
                  "answer": "Hinduism",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was a patron of Hinduism and supported various Hindu temples and festivals."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Krishnadeva Raya’s stance on local governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decentralized rule",
                    "Centralized control",
                    "Local autonomy",
                    "Feudal system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized control",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya centralized control to strengthen the administrative efficiency of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural project is associated with Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Hampi Temples",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Taj Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hampi Temples",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya is credited with the construction and enhancement of several temples in Hampi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major challenge faced by Krishnadeva Raya during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Internal rebellions",
                    "Economic collapse",
                    "Invasion by the Mughals",
                    "Natural disasters"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Internal rebellions",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya faced challenges from internal rebellions, which he managed to suppress to maintain his rule."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary language of administration during Krishnadeva Raya's reign?",
                  "options": ["Sanskrit", "Telugu", "Kannada", "Tamil"],
                  "answer": "Telugu",
                  "explanation": "Telugu was the primary language used for administration and literature during Krishnadeva Raya's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous poet and scholar was part of Krishnadeva Raya's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tukaram",
                    "Tenali Raman",
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Bhavabhuti"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tenali Raman",
                  "explanation": "Tenali Raman was a renowned poet and scholar who was part of Krishnadeva Raya's court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Krishnadeva Raya's military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of territory",
                    "Naval dominance",
                    "Trade routes",
                    "Diplomatic alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of territory",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya's military campaigns focused on expanding the territory of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which neighboring region did Krishnadeva Raya successfully defend against invasions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mysore",
                    "Deccan Sultanates",
                    "Gujarat",
                    "Orissa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan Sultanates",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya successfully defended the Vijayanagara Empire against the invasions of the Deccan Sultanates."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Krishnadeva Raya influence Telugu literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "By translating Persian texts",
                    "By composing poetry",
                    "By writing historical accounts",
                    "By promoting drama"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By composing poetry",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya influenced Telugu literature by composing poetry, including his famous work 'Amuktamalyada'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these structures was NOT built during Krishnadeva Raya's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vittala Temple",
                    "Hampi Bazaar",
                    "Lotus Mahal",
                    "Red Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Red Fort",
                  "explanation": "The Red Fort was not built during Krishnadeva Raya’s reign; it was constructed later in the Mughal era."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary role of the Nayaks in Krishnadeva Raya's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military commanders",
                    "Revenue collectors",
                    "Judges",
                    "Architects"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Revenue collectors",
                  "explanation": "The Nayaks were primarily responsible for revenue collection and administration in different regions of the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous battle solidified Krishnadeva Raya's dominance in South India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Battle of Raichur",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Hampi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Raichur",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Raichur in 1520 was crucial in solidifying Krishnadeva Raya's dominance in South India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the prominent general under Krishnadeva Raya known for his military strategies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rama Raya",
                    "Timmarusu",
                    "Aliya Rama Raya",
                    "Narasimha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rama Raya",
                  "explanation": "Rama Raya was a prominent general under Krishnadeva Raya known for his strategic military skills."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary source of revenue for the Vijayanagara Empire during Krishnadeva Raya's rule?",
                  "options": ["Trade", "Agriculture", "Mining", "Textiles"],
                  "answer": "Agriculture",
                  "explanation": "Agriculture was the primary source of revenue for the Vijayanagara Empire during Krishnadeva Raya's rule."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the first ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Krishna Devaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I was the founder and first ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital city of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": ["Hampi", "Madurai", "Bijapur", "Bidar"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "Hampi was the capital city of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was responsible for the expansion of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Achyutadevaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya expanded the Vijayanagara Empire and is considered one of its greatest rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous city of Hampi is located on the banks of which river?",
                  "options": ["Krishna", "Tungabhadra", "Godavari", "Kaveri"],
                  "answer": "Tungabhadra",
                  "explanation": "Hampi is located on the banks of the Tungabhadra River."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following built the Vittala Temple in Hampi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Krishna Devaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya is credited with the construction of the Vittala Temple in Hampi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following rulers strengthened the irrigation system of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Devaraya II",
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Achyutadevaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya took measures to improve agricultural productivity by strengthening the irrigation system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire was a major rival of the Vijayanagara Empire in South India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chola Empire",
                    "Maratha Empire",
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "The Bahmani Sultanate was a major rival of the Vijayanagara Empire in South India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagara Empire is best known for its achievements in which of the following areas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Religious tolerance",
                    "Art and architecture",
                    "Maritime trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Art and architecture",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire is renowned for its contributions to South Indian art and architecture, especially temple construction."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The city of Hampi was declared a World Heritage Site by UNESCO in which year?",
                  "options": ["1980", "1986", "1990", "1995"],
                  "answer": "1986",
                  "explanation": "Hampi was declared a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1986 for its historical and architectural significance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which European traveler provided the first detailed account of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Niccolo Conti",
                    "Duarte Barbosa",
                    "Abdur Razzaq",
                    "Athanasius Nikitin"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Niccolo Conti",
                  "explanation": "Niccolo Conti, an Italian traveler, provided one of the earliest detailed accounts of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "During the reign of which Vijayanagara ruler did Vasco da Gama land in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Achyutadevaraya",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Devaraya I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Vasco da Gama arrived in India during the reign of Krishna Devaraya, marking the beginning of European influence in Indian trade."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following chronicled the Battle of Talikota, which led to the fall of Vijayanagara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abdur Razzaq",
                    "Niccolo Conti",
                    "Firishta",
                    "Duarte Barbosa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Firishta",
                  "explanation": "Firishta, a Persian historian, chronicled the events of the Battle of Talikota in 1565, which led to the fall of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous Hazara Rama Temple was built during the reign of which ruler?",
                  "options": [
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Bukka I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Devaraya I",
                  "explanation": "The Hazara Rama Temple in Hampi was built during the reign of Devaraya I and is famous for its intricate carvings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which was the primary language used in the Vijayanagara court?",
                  "options": ["Tamil", "Telugu", "Sanskrit", "Kannada"],
                  "answer": "Telugu",
                  "explanation": "Telugu was the primary language used in the Vijayanagara court, although other languages like Kannada and Sanskrit were also prominent."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the chief minister who served under Krishna Devaraya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tenali Ramakrishna",
                    "Tirumala",
                    "Saluva Narasimha",
                    "Timmarusu"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Timmarusu",
                  "explanation": "Timmarusu was the chief minister of Krishna Devaraya and played a crucial role in his administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ruler of Vijayanagara was known for his military campaigns against the Gajapati Kingdom of Odisha?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Achyutadevaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya is famous for his successful military campaigns against the Gajapati Kingdom of Odisha."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the ruler of the Bahmani Sultanate when Krishna Devaraya fought against them?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahmud Gawan",
                    "Alauddin Hasan Bahman Shah",
                    "Sultan Mahmud",
                    "Muhammad Shah III"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sultan Mahmud",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya fought against Sultan Mahmud of the Bahmani Sultanate during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the Battle of Raichur in 1520?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vijayanagara's decline",
                    "Victory over Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "First European battle",
                    "End of Vijayanagara-Maratha conflict"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Victory over Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Raichur in 1520 was a significant victory for Krishna Devaraya over the Bahmani Sultanate, enhancing his control over the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagara king composed the Telugu work 'Amuktamalyada'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Achyutadevaraya",
                    "Krishna Devaraya",
                    "Harihara I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Devaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Devaraya was not only a military leader but also a scholar. He composed the Telugu literary work 'Amuktamalyada.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "The fall of Vijayanagara after the Battle of Talikota occurred in which year?",
                  "options": ["1520", "1542", "1565", "1580"],
                  "answer": "1565",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota in 1565 led to the eventual fall of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who of the following founded a new city on the South bank of a tributary to river Krishna and undertook to rule his new kingdom as the agent of a deity to whom all the land South of the river Krishna was supposed to belong?",
                  "options": [
                    "Amoghavarsha I",
                    "Ballala II",
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Prataparudra II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I founded a new city on the South bank of a tributary to the river Krishna and ruled as the agent of the deity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The lady poet who described the victorious expeditions of her husband in her work ‘MadhuraVijayam’ was",
                  "options": [
                    "Bharati",
                    "Ganga Devi",
                    "Varadambika",
                    "Vijjika"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ganga Devi",
                  "explanation": "Ganga Devi, the wife of Vijayanagara ruler Kumara Kampana, wrote the ‘MadhuraVijayam’ describing his victorious expeditions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The kingdom of Vijayanagara was founded by",
                  "options": [
                    "Vijay Raya",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Harihara and Bukka",
                    "Bukka II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara and Bukka",
                  "explanation": "The kingdom of Vijayanagara was founded by the brothers Harihara and Bukka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary goal of the Vijayanagara Empire's founders?",
                  "options": [
                    "To conquer South India",
                    "To establish a trade empire",
                    "To protect Hindu culture",
                    "To build a grand palace"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To protect Hindu culture",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire was founded with the goal of protecting Hindu culture and traditions from the expanding Muslim sultanates in South India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Identify the first ruler of Vijayanagara who captured Goa from the Bahmani Sultanate.",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Bukka II",
                    "Devaraya II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara II",
                  "explanation": "Harihara II was the first Vijayanagara ruler to capture Goa from the Bahmani Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "With whom did the king of Vijayanagara, Krishnadeva Raya, fight the battle of Golconda?",
                  "options": [
                    "Quli Qutb Shah",
                    "Qutbuddin Aybak",
                    "Ismail-Adil Khan",
                    "Gajapati"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Quli Qutb Shah",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya fought the battle of Golconda against Quli Qutb Shah."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who were the ‘Ashtadiggajas’ in the court of Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Eight ministers",
                    "Eight Telugu poets",
                    "Eight great warriors",
                    "Eight advisors"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Eight Telugu poets",
                  "explanation": "The ‘Ashtadiggajas’ were a group of eight Telugu poets in the court of Krishnadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among these was known as ‘Andhra Bhoja’?",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Rajendra Chola",
                    "Harihara",
                    "Bukka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was known as ‘Andhra Bhoja’ due to his patronage of Telugu literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The ‘Ashta Diggajas’ were associated with which of the following rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Rajendra-I",
                    "Yashovarman"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "The ‘Ashta Diggajas’ were the eight poets in the court of Krishnadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The ruling period of Krishnadeva Raya was the golden age of which literature?",
                  "options": ["Konkani", "Malayalam", "Tamil", "Telugu"],
                  "answer": "Telugu",
                  "explanation": "The reign of Krishnadeva Raya is considered the golden age of Telugu literature."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which city was founded by Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Warangal",
                    "Nagalapura",
                    "Udayagiri",
                    "Chandragiri"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragiri",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya founded the city of Chandragiri as a strategic location in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous Hazara temple of Vijayanagara was built during the reign of",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Deva Raya I",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Harihara I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya I",
                  "explanation": "The Hazara Rama Temple was constructed during the reign of Deva Raya I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Abdur Razzaq visited Vijayanagara during the reign of",
                  "options": [
                    "Deva Raya I",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Vira Vijaya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzaq, the Persian ambassador, visited Vijayanagara during the reign of Deva Raya II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which among the following King’s reign did the Persian traveller Abdur Razzaq visit India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Deva Raya I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya I",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishna Raya II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzaq visited India during the reign of Deva Raya II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Nicolo Conti?",
                  "options": [
                    "A famous painter",
                    "An Italian traveller who visited the Vijayanagara empire",
                    "A Portuguese traveller",
                    "A Persian traveller"
                  ],
                  "answer": "An Italian traveller who visited the Vijayanagara empire",
                  "explanation": "Nicolo Conti was an Italian traveller known for his account of the Vijayanagara empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Sayana, the famous commentator of the Vedic texts, was patronized by",
                  "options": [
                    "Paramara rulers",
                    "Satavahana rulers",
                    "Vijayanagara rulers",
                    "Vakataka rulers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vijayanagara rulers",
                  "explanation": "Sayana was a prominent commentator during the reign of the Vijayanagara rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the Vijayanagara Empire's primary form of government?",
                  "options": ["Democracy", "Monarchy", "Republic", "Oligarchy"],
                  "answer": "Monarchy",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire was governed as a monarchy, with power concentrated in the hands of the king and his court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was enthroned 500 years ago?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Kulottunga I",
                    "Raja Raya I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I was enthroned around 500 years ago as one of the founders of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous battle held in 1565 is",
                  "options": [
                    "Ist Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Khanwa",
                    "IInd Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Talikota"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Talikota",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota, fought in 1565, was a significant battle leading to the fall of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Battle of Talikota was fought between",
                  "options": [
                    "Akbar and Sultan of Malwa",
                    "Vijayanagara and the Bahmani Kingdom",
                    "Vijayanagara vs Bijapur, Ahmadnagar, Golconda",
                    "Sher Shah and Humayun"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vijayanagara vs Bijapur, Ahmadnagar, Golconda",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota was fought between the Vijayanagara Empire and the combined forces of Bijapur, Ahmadnagar, and Golconda."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which alliance was formed during Krishnadeva Raya's reign to counteract the Deccan Sultanates?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Alliance",
                    "The Vijayanagara-Mysore Alliance",
                    "The Maratha Confederacy",
                    "The Chalukya-Vijayanagara Alliance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Vijayanagara-Mysore Alliance",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya formed the Vijayanagara-Mysore Alliance to counteract the power of the Deccan Sultanates."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Krishnadeva Raya's military campaigns significantly impacted the Sultanate of Bijapur?",
                  "options": [
                    "Campaign of 1512",
                    "Campaign of 1518",
                    "Campaign of 1521",
                    "Campaign of 1524"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Campaign of 1518",
                  "explanation": "The Campaign of 1518 had a significant impact on the Sultanate of Bijapur, showcasing Krishnadeva Raya's military prowess."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the strategic importance of the Battle of Talikota for Krishnadeva Raya’s empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "New alliance",
                    "Empire expansion",
                    "Empire decline",
                    "Secured north"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Empire decline",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota in 1565 was a significant defeat for the Vijayanagara Empire, leading to its decline."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Krishnadeva Raya contribute to the cultural development of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "By promoting Persian culture",
                    "By patronizing Telugu literature and arts",
                    "By encouraging Arabic scholarship",
                    "By focusing on Jainism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By patronizing Telugu literature and arts",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was a patron of Telugu literature and arts, contributing to the cultural development of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historic event during Krishnadeva Raya's reign had long-term effects on South Indian politics?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Battle of Raichur",
                    "The fall of Hampi",
                    "The construction of the Vittala Temple",
                    "The coronation of Krishnadeva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The fall of Hampi",
                  "explanation": "The fall of Hampi in 1565 after Krishnadeva Raya's reign had long-term effects on South Indian politics."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did the Portuguese play during Krishnadeva Raya's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Allies in military campaigns",
                    "Trade partners",
                    "Diplomatic envoys",
                    "Cultural emissaries"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Trade partners",
                  "explanation": "The Portuguese were trade partners with the Vijayanagara Empire during Krishnadeva Raya's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a major factor in Krishnadeva Raya’s military strategies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Naval warfare",
                    "Siege tactics",
                    "Cavalry charges",
                    "Diplomatic treaties"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Naval warfare",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya’s military strategies primarily focused on siege tactics, cavalry charges, and diplomatic treaties, rather than naval warfare."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the major contributions of Krishnadeva Raya to the Vijayanagara Empire's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Reorganization of revenue systems",
                    "Creation of a new military unit",
                    "Expansion of the empire’s borders",
                    "Development of a new language"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reorganization of revenue systems",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya made significant contributions by reorganizing the revenue systems to improve the administration of the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous scholar and poet was a contemporary of Krishnadeva Raya and wrote extensively during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhoja",
                    "Kandukuri Veeresalingam",
                    "Peddana",
                    "Jayadeva"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Peddana",
                  "explanation": "Peddana was a famous scholar and poet who was a contemporary of Krishnadeva Raya and wrote extensively during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Krishnadeva Raya's policies influence the development of Vijayanagara's urban infrastructure?",
                  "options": [
                    "By focusing on fortifications",
                    "By promoting trade routes",
                    "By constructing public buildings and temples",
                    "By developing educational institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By constructing public buildings and temples",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya's policies included significant investments in constructing public buildings and temples, enhancing the urban infrastructure of Vijayanagara."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "The Battle of Talikota was fought in",
                  "options": [
                    "1526 A.D.",
                    "1565 A.D.",
                    "1576 A.D.",
                    "1586 A.D."
                  ],
                  "answer": "1565 A.D.",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota was fought in 1565, marking a significant defeat for the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When Raja Wodeyar founded the Kingdom of Mysore, who was the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": ["Sadasiva", "Tirumala", "Ranga II", "Venkata II"],
                  "answer": "Venkata II",
                  "explanation": "Venkata II was the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire when Raja Wodeyar founded the Kingdom of Mysore."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the chief characteristic of the financial system of Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Surplus rent",
                    "Land Revenue",
                    "Income from seaports",
                    "Monetary system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land Revenue",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire's financial system was characterized primarily by land revenue as a significant source of income."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who were the ‘Ashtadiggajas’ in the court of Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Eight ministers",
                    "Eight Telugu poets",
                    "Eight great warriors",
                    "Eight advisors"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Eight Telugu poets",
                  "explanation": "The ‘Ashtadiggajas’ were a group of eight Telugu poets in the court of Krishnadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ruins of which of the following represent the old capital of Vijayanagara?",
                  "options": ["Ahmednagar", "Bijapur", "Golconda", "Hampi"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "Hampi represents the old capital of the Vijayanagara Empire, known for its historical ruins."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ruler of Vijayanagara had sent his ambassador to the emperor of China?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Saluva Narasimha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya is noted for having sent an ambassador to the emperor of China, reflecting the empire's diplomatic reach."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where is the famous Vijaya Vitthal Temple, having its 56 carved pillars emitting musical notes located?",
                  "options": ["Belur", "Bhadrachalam", "Hampi", "Srirangam"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "The Vijaya Vitthal Temple, known for its musical pillars, is located in Hampi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Consider the following statements: 1. Narasimha Saluva ended the Sangama dynasty and seized the throne for himself and started the Saluva dynasty. 2. Vira Narasimha deposed the last Saluva ruler and seized the throne for himself. 3. Vira Narasimha was succeeded by his younger brother, Krishnadeva Raya. 4. Krishnadeva Raya was succeeded by his half-brother, Achyuta Raya. Which of the statements given above are correct?",
                  "options": [
                    "1, 2 and 3",
                    "2, 3 and 4",
                    "1 and 4",
                    "1, 2, 3 and 4"
                  ],
                  "answer": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
                  "explanation": "All statements are correct regarding the succession and rulers of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among these was famous for Telugu translation? 1. Kamban 2. Kuttan 3. Nannaya 4. Tikkan Choose the answer from the code.",
                  "options": ["1 and 2", "2 and 3", "3 and 4", "4 and 1"],
                  "answer": "3 and 4",
                  "explanation": "Nannaya and Tikkan were known for their work in Telugu translation, particularly of classical texts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Regarding the taxation system of Krishnadeva, the ruler of Vijayanagara, consider the following statements: 1. The tax rate on land was fixed depending on the quality of the land. 2. Private owners of workshops paid an industries tax. Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
                  "options": [
                    "Only 1",
                    "Only 2",
                    "Both 1 and 2",
                    "Neither 1 nor 2"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Both 1 and 2",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya's taxation system included a land tax based on land quality and an industries tax for workshop owners."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Devaraya II",
          "description": [
            "Devaraya II ruled from 1422 to 1446 and expanded the empire’s military might.",
            "Devaraya II became the king after his brother, Krishna Deva Raya, who was a famous ruler in his own right.",
            "Devaraya II as a significant leader in the Vijayanagara Empire, a historical kingdom located in South India.",
            "He was also interested in art and literature.",
            "Devaraya II's reign was a time of peace and prosperity for the Vijayanagara Empire."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Devaraya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "A ruler of Vijayanagara",
                    "A poet",
                    "A minister",
                    "A general"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A ruler of Vijayanagara",
                  "explanation": "Devaraya II was one of the great rulers of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "During which years did Deva Raya II rule the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "1425-1446 CE",
                    "1406-1422 CE",
                    "1336-1377 CE",
                    "1377-1406 CE"
                  ],
                  "answer": "1425-1446 CE",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II ruled the Vijayanagara Empire from 1425 to 1446 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the honorific title given to Deva Raya II that referred to his hunting skills or victories?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajabetegara",
                    "Prouda Devaraya",
                    "Mahanataka",
                    "Amaruka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gajabetegara",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known as Gajabetegara, meaning 'Hunter of Elephants' or 'Victorious over Elephant-like Enemies.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Kannada works did Deva Raya II write?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sobagina Sone and Amaruka",
                    "Mahanataka and Sudhanidhi",
                    "Rajatarangini and Ramayana",
                    "Mahabharata and Bhagavad Gita"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sobagina Sone and Amaruka",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II wrote Kannada works including Sobagina Sone and Amaruka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the South Indian mathematician and scholar during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Parameshvara",
                    "Bhaskara",
                    "Varahamihira"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Parameshvara",
                  "explanation": "Parameshvara of the Kerala school of astronomy and mathematics lived during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Deva Raya II fight against in several battles?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajapati Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II fought several battles against the Bahmani Sultanate during his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Deva Raya II do in response to the Bahmani Sultanate's attack on Vijayanagara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Paid tribute",
                    "Retaliated with a counter-attack",
                    "Forged an alliance with the Gajapati Empire",
                    "Abandoned the city"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Paid tribute",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was eventually forced to pay tribute to the Bahmani rulers after suffering heavy losses."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which regions did Deva Raya II successfully control during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kerala and Ceylon",
                    "North India and Central India",
                    "Western Ghats and Deccan Plateau",
                    "Sri Lanka and Maldives"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kerala and Ceylon",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's empire extended to Kerala and Ceylon, where he collected tributes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major cultural contribution during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Advancement in Kannada literature",
                    "Development of architectural styles",
                    "Establishment of new trade routes",
                    "Expansion of educational institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Advancement in Kannada literature",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's reign was marked by significant advancements in Kannada literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key battles did Deva Raya II fight against the Gajapati of Odisha?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Kondavidu and Battle of Rajamahendri",
                    "Battle of Talikota and Battle of Hampi",
                    "Battle of Panipat and Battle of Kanauj",
                    "Battle of Plassey and Battle of Buxar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kondavidu and Battle of Rajamahendri",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II fought major battles against the Gajapati of Odisha, including the Battle of Kondavidu and the Battle of Rajamahendri."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was known as 'Prouda Devaraya'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya",
                    "Bukka Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known as 'Prouda Devaraya' due to his military achievements and prowess."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the Kannada works written by Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ramayana and Mahabharata",
                    "Sobagina Sone and Amaruka",
                    "Bhagavad Gita and Upanishads",
                    "Vedas and Puranas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sobagina Sone and Amaruka",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II authored 'Sobagina Sone' and 'Amaruka', which are significant Kannada literary works."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Deva Raya II belong to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tuluva Dynasty",
                    "Sangama Dynasty",
                    "Saluva Dynasty",
                    "Yadava Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sangama Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was a ruler of the Sangama Dynasty, which was the first dynasty of the Vijayanagar Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "During Deva Raya II's reign, who was the noted South Indian mathematician from the Kerala school of astronomy and mathematics?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Brahmagupta",
                    "Parameshvara",
                    "Bhaskara I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Parameshvara",
                  "explanation": "Parameshvara was a prominent mathematician and astronomer from the Kerala school during the time of Deva Raya II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Deva Raya II as the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bukka Raya",
                    "Mallikarjuna",
                    "Virupaksha",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mallikarjuna",
                  "explanation": "Mallikarjuna succeeded Deva Raya II as the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Deva Raya II fight against during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mamluk Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II engaged in several battles against the Bahmani Sultanate during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for Deva Raya II to recruit Muslim horsemen into his army?",
                  "options": [
                    "To increase the number of soldiers",
                    "Due to their efficiency in cavalry",
                    "For better trade relations",
                    "To avoid conflict with Bahmani Sultanate"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Due to their efficiency in cavalry",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II recruited Muslim horsemen because of their effectiveness in cavalry, which was crucial for his military strategy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Deva Raya II defeat the Gajapati forces at the Battle of Kondavidu?",
                  "options": ["1425", "1427", "1432", "1441"],
                  "answer": "1427",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II achieved a significant victory over the Gajapati forces at the Battle of Kondavidu in 1427."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title was given to Deva Raya II, referring to his prowess in hunting elephants?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajapati",
                    "Gajabetegara",
                    "Gajavadhaka",
                    "Gajasura"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gajabetegara",
                  "explanation": "The title 'Gajabetegara' means 'elephant hunter', a title awarded to Deva Raya II for his skill in hunting elephants."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was a foreign traveler that visited the court of Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Batuta",
                    "Nicolo de Conti",
                    "Abdur Razzak",
                    "Domingo Paes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abdur Razzak",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzak, a Persian envoy, visited the court of Deva Raya II and documented his observations."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "A poet",
                    "A Vijayanagara ruler",
                    "A foreign traveler",
                    "A military general"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A Vijayanagara ruler",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was a prominent ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is one of the notable achievements of Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing trade routes with Europe",
                    "Consolidating the empire’s southern territories",
                    "Expanding the empire into Southeast Asia",
                    "Creating a new script for administration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidating the empire’s southern territories",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II is known for his efforts to consolidate and strengthen the southern regions of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Deva Raya II known for in Kannada literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Writing novels",
                    "Encouraging poets",
                    "Compiling history books",
                    "Translating texts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Encouraging poets",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known for promoting Kannada literature and encouraging poets in his court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which language did Deva Raya II promote during his reign?",
                  "options": ["Sanskrit", "Tamil", "Kannada", "Hindi"],
                  "answer": "Kannada",
                  "explanation": "During Deva Raya II's reign, Kannada was promoted and flourished in literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Deva Raya II as the ruler of Vijayanagara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishna Deva Raya",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Bukka Raya",
                    "Mallikarjuna"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mallikarjuna",
                  "explanation": "Mallikarjuna succeeded Deva Raya II as the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Deva Raya II's military achievements?",
                  "options": [
                    "Conquering Delhi",
                    "Defeating the Gajapati forces",
                    "Establishing trade with Europe",
                    "Invading China"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeating the Gajapati forces",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II achieved a notable military victory by defeating the Gajapati forces."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Deva Raya II successfully control?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Kerala", "Punjab"],
                  "answer": "Kerala",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II successfully controlled the region of Kerala during his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Deva Raya II's court included which type of writers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sanskrit poets",
                    "Kannada poets",
                    "Tamil poets",
                    "Persian poets"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kannada poets",
                  "explanation": "The court of Deva Raya II included many notable Kannada poets."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which foreign traveler visited Deva Raya II's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Batuta",
                    "Nicolo de Conti",
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Columbus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nicolo de Conti",
                  "explanation": "Nicolo de Conti, a Venetian traveler, visited the court of Deva Raya II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a common feature of Deva Raya II’s military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Naval warfare",
                    "Using elephants",
                    "Recruiting Muslim cavalry",
                    "Guerrilla tactics"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Recruiting Muslim cavalry",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's military strategy prominently featured the recruitment of efficient Muslim cavalry."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Deva Raya II’s role in the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": ["A poet", "A general", "A king", "A scholar"],
                  "answer": "A king",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was a prominent king of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Deva Raya II is associated with which dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tuluva Dynasty",
                    "Saluva Dynasty",
                    "Sangama Dynasty",
                    "Chalukya Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sangama Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was associated with the Sangama Dynasty of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title did Deva Raya II hold that refers to his prowess in hunting?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajapati",
                    "Gajavadhaka",
                    "Gajabetegara",
                    "Gajavijaya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gajabetegara",
                  "explanation": "The title 'Gajabetegara' reflects Deva Raya II's reputation for hunting elephants."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle did Deva Raya II win against the Gajapati forces?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Battle of Mudgal",
                    "Battle of Kondavidu",
                    "Battle of Rajamahendri"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kondavidu",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II achieved a significant victory at the Battle of Kondavidu against the Gajapati forces."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Deva Raya II’s army include to enhance its strength?",
                  "options": [
                    "War elephants",
                    "Heavy artillery",
                    "Muslim cavalry",
                    "Naval ships"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Muslim cavalry",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's army was strengthened by the inclusion of Muslim cavalry, which was highly effective."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was a contemporary poet during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": ["Kalidasa", "Kumara Vyasa", "Tulsidas", "Surdas"],
                  "answer": "Kumara Vyasa",
                  "explanation": "Kumara Vyasa was a notable Kannada poet during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What region did Deva Raya II successfully expand his empire into?",
                  "options": ["Ceylon", "Gujarat", "Bengal", "Kashmir"],
                  "answer": "Ceylon",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II successfully expanded the Vijayanagara Empire into Ceylon (modern Sri Lanka)."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a part of Deva Raya II's military campaigns?",
                  "options": ["Ceylon", "Gujarat", "Kerala", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II’s military campaigns did not include Bengal; his efforts were focused on regions like Ceylon and Kerala."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Deva Raya II’s contributions to literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Writing epics",
                    "Encouraging Kannada literature",
                    "Translating Greek texts",
                    "Promoting Persian poetry"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Encouraging Kannada literature",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II significantly contributed to literature by encouraging Kannada poets and writers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who did Deva Raya II fight against in the south?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mamluk Sultanate",
                    "Bahamani Sultanate",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahamani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II fought against the Bahamani Sultanate, a key rival in the southern region during his rule."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was a key feature of Deva Raya II's military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Use of war elephants",
                    "Naval power",
                    "Heavy cavalry",
                    "Gunpowder weapons"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Use of war elephants",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known for his use of war elephants, a key component of his military strategy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which kingdom's ruler did Deva Raya II defeat to extend his control to Rajahmundry?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajapati Kingdom",
                    "Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Reddis of Kondavidu",
                    "Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gajapati Kingdom",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II defeated the Gajapati ruler to extend his control to Rajahmundry."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Deva Raya II handle his conflict with the Bahmani Sultanate in terms of military recruitment?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased fortifications",
                    "Recruited Muslim cavalry",
                    "Allied with the Gajapati Empire",
                    "Established naval bases"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Recruited Muslim cavalry",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II recruited Muslim cavalry into his army due to their efficiency, despite his own religious prejudices."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which notable literary work was not authored by Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Amaruka",
                    "Mahanataka",
                    "Sobagina Sone",
                    "Rajatarangini"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rajatarangini",
                  "explanation": "Rajatarangini was written by Kalhana, not by Deva Raya II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which year marked the beginning of a new war with the Bahmani Kingdom under Deva Raya II's rule?",
                  "options": ["1436", "1443", "1425", "1446"],
                  "answer": "1443",
                  "explanation": "A new war with the Bahmani Kingdom began in 1443 during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major achievement of Deva Raya II in the South?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeated the Zamorin of Calicut",
                    "Established a new trade route",
                    "Invaded and controlled Burma",
                    "Secured alliances with multiple kingdoms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeated the Zamorin of Calicut",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's empire included Kerala, where he defeated the ruler of Quilon and had influence over the Zamorin of Calicut."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these was a contemporary poet and scholar during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kumara Vyasa",
                    "Jayadeva",
                    "Chandrashekara",
                    "Bhoja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kumara Vyasa",
                  "explanation": "Kumara Vyasa was a famous Kannada poet and scholar during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Deva Raya II’s policies on Vijayanagara’s urban development?",
                  "options": [
                    "Focus on trade routes",
                    "Building public infrastructures",
                    "Promoting agricultural expansion",
                    "Establishing military forts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building public infrastructures",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's policies included significant investments in constructing public buildings and temples, contributing to urban development."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What type of tribute did Deva Raya II have to pay to the Bahmani Sultanate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military support",
                    "Gold and silver",
                    "Land concessions",
                    "Political allegiance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gold and silver",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was forced to pay a large tribute in gold and silver to the Bahmani Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Deva Raya II struggle to control after an attempted assassination in 1443?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab",
                    "Western Ghats",
                    "Sri Lanka",
                    "Kerala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II lost control over some regions in the Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab following an attempted assassination in 1443."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was the founder of the Vijayanagar Kingdom and the city according to the Kapaluru and Begepalli grants?",
                  "options": [
                    "Saluva Narsimha",
                    "Vir Narsimha",
                    "Tirimala",
                    "Hari and Bukka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hari and Bukka",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I and Bukka Raya I are credited with founding the Vijayanagar Kingdom and city according to historical grants."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who became the King of Tuluva Dynasty after the assassination of Immadi Narasimha?",
                  "options": [
                    "Saluva Narsimha",
                    "Vir Narsimha",
                    "Tirimala",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vir Narsimha",
                  "explanation": "After the assassination of Immadi Narasimha, Vir Narsimha ascended to the throne of the Tuluva Dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Consider the following statement(s) related to the features of Vijayanagar Empire: I. It was a monarchy II. Land tax was an important source of revenue for the empire. Select the correct statement(s):",
                  "options": [
                    "Only I",
                    "Only II",
                    "Both I & II",
                    "Neither I nor II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Both I & II",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagar Empire was a monarchy and land tax was indeed a significant source of revenue."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following Bahmani Kings was married to the daughter of Dev Raya I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sultan Quli Hamadani or Quttbul Mulk",
                    "Yusuf Adil Khan",
                    "Ahmad Shah I",
                    "Firoz Shah Bahmani"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Firoz Shah Bahmani",
                  "explanation": "Firoz Shah Bahmani married the daughter of Dev Raya I, establishing a diplomatic alliance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many kingdoms ruled over Vijayanagar?",
                  "options": ["Four", "Five", "Six", "Seven"],
                  "answer": "Four",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagar Empire was divided into four main administrative regions or provinces."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the Vijayanagar rulers adopted the 'Gajabetekara (the elephant hunter)'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Deva Raya I",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Harihara",
                    "Bukka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known for his adoption of the title 'Gajabetekara', meaning 'elephant hunter'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following foreign travelers visited the court of Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Batuta",
                    "Nicolo de Conti",
                    "Abdur Razzak",
                    "Domingo Paes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Batuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Batuta, the famous Moroccan traveler, visited the court of Harihara I during his travels."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following foreign travelers visited the court of Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Batuta",
                    "Nicolo de Conti",
                    "Abdur Razzak",
                    "Domingo Paes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Abdur Razzak",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzak, a Persian ambassador, visited the court of Deva Raya II and recorded his observations."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagar ruler followed Vaishnavism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishna Deva Raya",
                    "Vir Narsimha",
                    "Tirumala",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of the above",
                  "explanation": "All the mentioned rulers of the Vijayanagar Empire were followers of Vaishnavism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the rulers of Vijayanagar maintained friendly relations with Albuquerque, the Portuguese Governor, and granted him permission to build a fort at Bhatkal?",
                  "options": [
                    "Krishna Deva Raya",
                    "Vir Narsimha",
                    "Tirumala",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna Deva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishna Deva Raya maintained diplomatic relations with the Portuguese and allowed them to build a fort at Bhatkal."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which battle was fought by Deva Raya II against the Gajapati of Odisha in 1436?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Kondavidu",
                    "Battle of Rajamahendri",
                    "Battle of Mudgal",
                    "Battle of Talikota"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Rajamahendri",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II fought the Battle of Rajamahendri against the Gajapati of Odisha in 1436."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city was relocated as the Bahamani capital due to Deva Raya II’s military pressure?",
                  "options": ["Bijapur", "Bidar", "Gulbarga", "Hyderabad"],
                  "answer": "Bidar",
                  "explanation": "Due to the military pressure from Deva Raya II, the Bahamani capital was moved from Gulbarga to Bidar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for Deva Raya II’s payment of tribute to the Bahamani Sultanate?",
                  "options": [
                    "To gain peace",
                    "To prevent invasion",
                    "For military support",
                    "To strengthen trade relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To gain peace",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II paid tribute to the Bahamani Sultanate mainly to secure peace and avoid further conflicts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant event took place in 1443 during Deva Raya II’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Start of a new war with Bahamani Sultanate",
                    "Annexation of Rajahmundry",
                    "Defeat at Battle of Kondavidu",
                    "Appointment of Muslim horsemen"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Start of a new war with Bahamani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "In 1443, Deva Raya II initiated a new conflict with the Bahamani Sultanate, marking a significant event during his reign."
                },

                {
                  "question": "Which famous Kannada writers were part of Deva Raya II’s court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chamarasa and Kumara Vyasa",
                    "Tulsidas and Kabir",
                    "Valmiki and Vyasa",
                    "Kalidasa and Bharavi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chamarasa and Kumara Vyasa",
                  "explanation": "Chamarasa and Kumara Vyasa were renowned Kannada poets who flourished under Deva Raya II’s patronage."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the notable achievements of Deva Raya II in the southern regions of India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeating the Reddis of Kondavidu",
                    "Invading the Mughal Empire",
                    "Establishing trade routes with Europe",
                    "Building the Golden Temple"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeating the Reddis of Kondavidu",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II achieved a significant victory by defeating the Reddis of Kondavidu, strengthening Vijayanagara’s control over the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Deva Raya II's military campaigns on the Vijayanagara Empire’s control over the regions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Loss of southern territories",
                    "Expansion into Ceylon and tribute from neighbors",
                    "Annexation of Bahamani Sultanate",
                    "Trade monopolies in Southeast Asia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion into Ceylon and tribute from neighbors",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II’s campaigns led to the expansion of the Vijayanagara Empire into Ceylon and enabled the collection of tribute from neighboring kingdoms."
                },

                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a region Deva Raya II successfully controlled or defended?",
                  "options": ["Kerala", "Ceylon", "Bengal", "Quilon"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II did not have control or significant influence over Bengal, though he managed other regions like Kerala, Ceylon, and Quilon."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Deva Raya II's conflict with which kingdom led to significant losses and a forced tribute payment?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chola Kingdom",
                    "Bahamani Sultanate",
                    "Gajapati Kingdom",
                    "Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bahamani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "The conflict with the Bahamani Sultanate resulted in significant losses for Deva Raya II and led to the payment of tribute to the Bahamani rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagara ruler is often associated with the cultural flourishing of Kannada literature during the 15th century?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya",
                    "Bukka Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II is well-known for fostering the development of Kannada literature during his reign, making him a patron of cultural and literary advancements."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical source mentions Deva Raya II's extensive recruitment of Muslim cavalry?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sastri's accounts",
                    "Nuniz's writings",
                    "Kamath's inscriptions",
                    "Razzak's records"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sastri's accounts",
                  "explanation": "Historian Sastri mentions Deva Raya II's recruitment of Muslim cavalry due to their efficiency."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a battle fought by Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Rajamahendri",
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Battle of Kondavidu",
                    "Battle of Hampi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Talikota",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Talikota was fought later, in 1565 CE, not during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Deva Raya II's actions affect the Bahmani Sultanate's capital city?",
                  "options": [
                    "Forced relocation to Bidar",
                    "Destruction of the city",
                    "Diplomatic peace treaty",
                    "Permanent annexation of the city"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Forced relocation to Bidar",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's military actions forced the Bahmani Sultanate to relocate their capital to Bidar in 1426."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following poets was NOT associated with Deva Raya II's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chamarasa",
                    "Jakkanarya",
                    "Kumarabankanatha",
                    "Kandukuri Veeresalingam"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kandukuri Veeresalingam",
                  "explanation": "Kandukuri Veeresalingam was not associated with Deva Raya II’s court; he was a later figure."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following regions did NOT fall under Deva Raya II's control?",
                  "options": ["Burma", "Sri Lanka", "Malabar Coast", "Kalinga"],
                  "answer": "Burma",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II's empire did not extend to Burma; it included regions like Kerala and Sri Lanka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did the Bahmani Sultanate begin inflicting heavy losses on Deva Raya II's forces?",
                  "options": ["1436", "1443", "1425", "1446"],
                  "answer": "1443",
                  "explanation": "The Bahmani Sultanate inflicted heavy losses on Deva Raya II's forces in 1443, leading to further conflicts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the outcome of the Battle of Kondavidu in 1427 for Deva Raya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Victory over the Gajapati",
                    "Loss of territory",
                    "Stalemate with the Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Alliance with the Reddis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Victory over the Gajapati",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II achieved victory over the Gajapati of Odisha in the Battle of Kondavidu in 1427."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main cultural conflict during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vaishnava vs. Shaiva",
                    "Buddhist vs. Jain",
                    "Sanskrit vs. Kannada",
                    "Muslim vs. Hindu"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vaishnava vs. Shaiva",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II’s reign saw significant literary and cultural conflicts between Vaishnava and Shaiva writers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which literary figure is known for their secular works during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandrashekara",
                    "Kumara Vyasa",
                    "Peddana",
                    "Jayadeva"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandrashekara",
                  "explanation": "Chandrashekara (Chrakavi) was known for his secular literary works during Deva Raya II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian's inscriptions indicated that the fort at Mudgal remained under Vijayanagara control during Deva Raya II's reign?",
                  "options": ["Kamath", "Sastri", "Razzak", "Nuniz"],
                  "answer": "Kamath",
                  "explanation": "Historian Kamath's inscriptions confirm that the fort at Mudgal remained under Vijayanagara control."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the major strategic and political challenge faced by Deva Raya II from the Bahamani Sultanate during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Loss of Mudgal fort",
                    "Relocation of Bahamani capital",
                    "Repeated invasions and large tributes",
                    "Internal rebellion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Repeated invasions and large tributes",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II faced repeated invasions from the Bahamani Sultanate, leading to large tribute payments and significant political challenges."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Deva Raya II’s victory at the Battle of Kondavidu was against which Gajapati ruler?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kapilendra",
                    "Bhanudeva IV",
                    "Ramaraja",
                    "Rajendra Chola"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bhanudeva IV",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Kondavidu, where Deva Raya II emerged victorious, was fought against Bhanudeva IV of the Gajapati dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Deva Raya II experience heavy losses to the Bahamani Sultanate, forcing him to pay tribute?",
                  "options": ["1432", "1436", "1443", "1446"],
                  "answer": "1443",
                  "explanation": "In 1443, Deva Raya II faced significant losses against the Bahamani Sultanate, which compelled him to pay a large tribute to secure peace."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant military action did Deva Raya II undertake in 1423 as a crown prince?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeating Gajapati of Odisha",
                    "Forcing Bahamani Sultanate to relocate capital",
                    "Invading Ceylon",
                    "Repulsing Reddi invasion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Forcing Bahamani Sultanate to relocate capital",
                  "explanation": "In 1423, as a crown prince, Deva Raya II pressured the Bahamani Sultanate to move their capital from Gulbarga to Bidar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the title given to Deva Raya II that reflects his reputation for military prowess, particularly against powerful foes?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gajapati",
                    "Gajavadhaka",
                    "Gajabetegara",
                    "Gajavijaya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gajabetegara",
                  "explanation": "The title 'Gajabetegara' (the elephant hunter) was given to Deva Raya II, acknowledging his military skills and accomplishments."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian recorded that Deva Raya II had to pay a large tribute to achieve peace with the Bahamani Sultanate?",
                  "options": ["Kamath", "Sastri", "Razzak", "Nuniz"],
                  "answer": "Sastri",
                  "explanation": "Historian Sastri recorded that Deva Raya II had to pay a substantial tribute to the Bahamani Sultanate to achieve peace."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Deva Raya II play in the development of secular literature during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promoted religious texts",
                    "Encouraged literary competition",
                    "Focused on military literature",
                    "Limited to religious subjects"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Encouraged literary competition",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II supported and encouraged a vibrant literary culture by promoting competition between different literary traditions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important geographical area was brought under Vijayanagara control by Deva Raya II by 1432?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bengal",
                    "Gujarat",
                    "Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab",
                    "Kerala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab",
                  "explanation": "By 1432, Deva Raya II had extended Vijayanagara's control over the strategically important Tungabhadra-Krishna river doab region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ruler was known for recruiting Muslim cavalry for his army due to their efficiency?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka Raya",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "Deva Raya II was known for incorporating Muslim cavalry into his army, valuing their effectiveness in battle."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagara ruler's reign marked the golden age of South Indian culture and arts, especially Kannada literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Bukka Raya",
                    "Krishna Deva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deva Raya II",
                  "explanation": "The reign of Deva Raya II is often associated with a flourishing period in Kannada literature and South Indian culture."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "subtopicName": "Harihara I",
          "description": [
            "Harihara I was the founder of the Vijayanagara Empire.",
            "Harihara I, along with his brother Bukka Raya I, established the Vijayanagara Empire in 1336 CE.",
            "Harihara I was originally a commander under the Hoysala dynasty before founding the Vijayanagara Empire.",
            "The capital of the Vijayanagara Empire under Harihara I was located at the city of Vijayanagara, on the banks of the Tungabhadra River.",
            "Harihara I's reign focused on defending the Deccan region from northern invasions, particularly from the Delhi Sultanate.",
            "Harihara I established a strong military and administrative foundation for the Vijayanagara Empire, which lasted over two centuries."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "The founder of the Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "A poet",
                    "A general in the Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "The ruler of the Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The founder of the Vijayanagara Empire",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I, also known as Hakka and Vira Harihara I, was the founder of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Harihara I establish?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Sangama Dynasty",
                    "Hoysala Dynasty",
                    "Rashtrakuta Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sangama Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I founded the Sangama Dynasty, the first of four dynasties to rule the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the original name of Harihara I?",
                  "options": ["Hakka", "Bukka", "Veera", "Kampana"],
                  "answer": "Hakka",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I was also called Hakka and Vira Harihara I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant fort did Harihara I build on the west coast of Karnataka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fort at Barkuru",
                    "Fort at Gooty",
                    "Fort at Badami",
                    "Fort at Hampi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fort at Barkuru",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I built a fort at Barkuru on the west coast of present-day Karnataka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which king's death allowed Harihara I to take full control over the Hoysala territories?",
                  "options": [
                    "Veera Ballala III",
                    "Raja Raja Chola",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Rajendra Chola"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Veera Ballala III",
                  "explanation": "After the death of Hoysala Veera Ballala III, Harihara I took full control over the Hoysala territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a city associated with the Vijayanagar Empire?",
                  "options": ["Chandragiri", "Hampi", "Delhi", "Penukonda"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Delhi was not part of the Vijayanagar Empire; it was associated with other historical empires."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Harihara I as the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": ["Bukka I", "Kampana", "Bukka Raya", "Muddappa"],
                  "answer": "Bukka I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I was succeeded by his brother Bukka I."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What was one of Harihara I’s significant achievements in terms of military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthening old forts",
                    "Building a naval fleet",
                    "Conquering Sri Lanka",
                    "Creating alliances with Mughals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strengthening old forts",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I strengthened old forts like Badami and Gooty as part of his military strategy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which system did Harihara I use to manage the military and administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Nayankara system",
                    "Feudal system",
                    "Manorial system",
                    "Zamindari system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nayankara system",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I used the nayankara system, appointing military commanders as local governors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital city of Harihara I’s empire known as?",
                  "options": ["Vidya Nagara", "Hampi", "Barkuru", "Gooty"],
                  "answer": "Vidya Nagara",
                  "explanation": "The capital city of Harihara I's empire was called Vidya Nagara, meaning 'City of Learning'."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following cities was not associated with the Vijayanagar Empire’s capital?",
                  "options": ["Hampi", "Chandragiri", "Penukonda", "Mysore"],
                  "answer": "Mysore",
                  "explanation": "Mysore was not a capital city of the Vijayanagar Empire; Hampi, Chandragiri, and Penukonda were."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant aspect of Harihara I’s military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing a powerful navy",
                    "Strengthening inland fortifications and ports",
                    "Expanding into northern territories",
                    "Forming alliances with European powers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strengthening inland fortifications and ports",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I focused on strengthening inland fortifications and key strategic locations rather than naval power or European alliances."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s administration is recognized for its efforts in:",
                  "options": [
                    "Linguistic diversity",
                    "Centralized control and military organization",
                    "Expansion into Southeast Asia",
                    "Isolationist policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized control and military organization",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s administration emphasized centralized control and the organization of military forces to consolidate power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a key strategic advantage of Vijayanagar’s location?",
                  "options": [
                    "Access to Himalayan trade routes",
                    "Defensive positioning along the Tungabhadra River",
                    "Proximity to the Arabian Sea",
                    "Fertile river valleys"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defensive positioning along the Tungabhadra River",
                  "explanation": "The location along the Tungabhadra River provided a natural defensive advantage for the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s rule saw the Vijayanagar Empire achieve:",
                  "options": [
                    "Political fragmentation",
                    "Cultural and administrative unity",
                    "Religious exclusivity",
                    "Economic decline"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cultural and administrative unity",
                  "explanation": "During Harihara I’s reign, the Vijayanagar Empire achieved significant cultural and administrative unity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Harihara I initially control before expanding his territory?",
                  "options": [
                    "Northern Karnataka",
                    "Southern Karnataka",
                    "Andhra Pradesh",
                    "Tamil Nadu"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northern Karnataka",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I initially controlled the northern parts of present-day Karnataka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagar Empire’s cultural advancements were largely due to:",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Strategic governance and administrative reforms",
                    "Maritime trade",
                    "Diplomatic relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strategic governance and administrative reforms",
                  "explanation": "Cultural advancements in the Vijayanagara Empire were primarily driven by effective governance and administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagar Empire was founded with the intention to:",
                  "options": [
                    "Promote Hinduism",
                    "Counter Deccan Sultanates and Tughlaqs",
                    "Expand into Northern India",
                    "Establish maritime dominance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Counter Deccan Sultanates and Tughlaqs",
                  "explanation": "The primary goal of founding the Vijayanagara Empire was to counter the influence of the Deccan Sultanates and Tughlaqs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s strategic decisions included:",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanding into South East Asia",
                    "Fortifying key locations for defense",
                    "Establishing trade alliances with Europe",
                    "Promoting religious unity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fortifying key locations for defense",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s strategy focused on fortifying key locations to strengthen the empire’s defense."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major achievement is attributed to the administration of Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Developing a standardized currency system",
                    "Building extensive irrigation networks",
                    "Forming alliances with neighboring kingdoms",
                    "Enhancing trade with the Arabian Peninsula"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building extensive irrigation networks",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I is known for developing extensive irrigation systems that improved agriculture and supported the empire's economy."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "During Harihara I’s reign, what was one significant change in governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shift to feudalism",
                    "Enhanced centralization and taxation",
                    "Establishment of a communist state",
                    "Promotion of maritime trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Enhanced centralization and taxation",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I implemented a more centralized governance system and improved the taxation system to strengthen control over the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a key feature of the Vijayanagar Empire’s administration under Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decentralized authority",
                    "Regional autonomy",
                    "Centralized control with efficient military and revenue",
                    "Diplomatic isolation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized control with efficient military and revenue",
                  "explanation": "The administration under Harihara I was characterized by centralized control, efficient military organization, and a well-structured revenue system."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagar Empire was named after which city?",
                  "options": ["Hampi", "Vijaynagar", "Chandragiri", "Vellore"],
                  "answer": "Vijaynagar",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagar Empire was named after its capital city, Vijaynagar (modern-day Hampi)."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The location of Vijayanagar City was strategically advantageous because of its:",
                  "options": [
                    "Proximity to the Himalayas",
                    "Access to sea trade routes",
                    "Defensibility and cultural significance",
                    "Agricultural wealth"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defensibility and cultural significance",
                  "explanation": "Vijayanagar's location offered natural defenses and was culturally significant, which contributed to its strategic advantage."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s rule is noted for establishing the Vijayanagar Empire as a major:",
                  "options": [
                    "Trade hub",
                    "Military power",
                    "Cultural center",
                    "Agricultural state"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military power",
                  "explanation": "During Harihara I’s rule, the Vijayanagara Empire established itself as a significant military power in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagar Empire’s primary adversaries were:",
                  "options": [
                    "Cholas and Pandavas",
                    "Deccan Sultanates and Tughlaqs",
                    "Mughals and Rajputs",
                    "Marathas and Portuguese"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan Sultanates and Tughlaqs",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire primarily faced opposition from the Deccan Sultanates and the Tughlaqs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following regions was NOT part of the Vijayanagar Empire’s extended kingdom?",
                  "options": ["Chandragiri", "Penukonda", "Hampi", "Delhi"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Delhi was not part of the Vijayanagara Empire; it was associated with different historical powers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s fortification of Gooty was aimed at defending against:",
                  "options": [
                    "Mughal invaders",
                    "Delhi rulers",
                    "Hoysala kings",
                    "Marathas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hoysala kings",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I fortified Gooty primarily to defend against the Hoysala kings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Vijayanagar Empire’s capital city was later identified with which famous historical site?",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Jaipur", "Hampi", "Delhi"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "The capital city of the Vijayanagara Empire, Vijaynagar, is now identified with the historical site of Hampi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I’s approach to governance included:",
                  "options": [
                    "Isolation from neighbors",
                    "Centralized administration and military strength",
                    "Expansion into Europe",
                    "Promotion of trade alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized administration and military strength",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I focused on centralizing administration and strengthening the military to consolidate power and maintain control over the empire."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What role did the sage Vidyaranya play in the founding of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military general",
                    "Influenced Bukka and Hakka to revert to Hinduism",
                    "Chief architect of the empire",
                    "Negotiated peace treaties with the Delhi Sultanate"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Influenced Bukka and Hakka to revert to Hinduism",
                  "explanation": "Sage Vidyaranya influenced Bukka and Hakka to revert to Hinduism and helped them in founding the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Hoysala king's family was connected to Harihara I through marriage?",
                  "options": [
                    "Veera Ballala III",
                    "Raja Raja Chola",
                    "Somesvara IV",
                    "Vijaya Hoysala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Veera Ballala III",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s family was connected to the Hoysala Court through Ballappa Dandanayaka, a nephew of Veera Ballala III."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant action did Harihara I take in the Ananthpur district in 1339?",
                  "options": [
                    "Built a fort",
                    "Defeated a rival king",
                    "Established a new trade route",
                    "Converted to Islam"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Built a fort",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I built a fort at Gooty (Gutti) in the Ananthpur district in 1339."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the inscription dated 1346 related to Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Described his conquest of the Hoysala Kingdom",
                    "Granted lands to Sringeri matha",
                    "Recorded his defeat by the Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Mentioned his military alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Granted lands to Sringeri matha",
                  "explanation": "The inscription dated 1346 described Harihara I as the ruler of the territory and mentioned a grant to the Sringeri matha."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following forts was NOT fortified by Harihara I?",
                  "options": ["Badami", "Gooty", "Udayagiri", "Hampi"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I fortified Badami, Gooty, and Udayagiri, but Hampi was not one of the forts he specifically fortified."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of the nayankara system in Harihara I’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Manage local governance and military control",
                    "Oversee trade and commerce",
                    "Supervise religious activities",
                    "Handle foreign relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Manage local governance and military control",
                  "explanation": "The nayankara system was used to manage local governance and military control by appointing military commanders as local governors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which river valley did Harihara I initially control?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tungabhadra River Valley",
                    "Krishna River Valley",
                    "Kaveri River Valley",
                    "Godavari River Valley"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tungabhadra River Valley",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I initially established control over the valley of the Tungabhadra River."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Harihara I contribute to the administration and revenue system of his kingdom?",
                  "options": [
                    "By appointing local governors and collecting taxes",
                    "By focusing on foreign trade",
                    "By setting up a new currency system",
                    "By implementing land reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By appointing local governors and collecting taxes",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s administration involved appointing local governors and collecting taxes to manage and fund the kingdom."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Harihara I’s approach to increasing the kingdom's resources?",
                  "options": [
                    "Forcing deforestation and agriculture",
                    "Expanding trade routes",
                    "Building a strong naval fleet",
                    "Creating alliances with neighboring states"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Forcing deforestation and agriculture",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I increased the kingdom’s resources by forcing farmers to clear forests and bring land under cultivation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a key feature of Harihara I’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralization of power",
                    "Decentralization of authority",
                    "Expansion of maritime trade",
                    "Development of a new language"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralization of power",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s reign was marked by a degree of centralization in the administration and military."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "The bone of contention between Bahmani and Vijayanagar kingdom was?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kavery delta",
                    "Malabar parts",
                    "Krishna delta",
                    "Krishna-Tungabhadra doab"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishna-Tungabhadra doab",
                  "explanation": "The Krishna-Tungabhadra doab was a fertile and strategic region, which became the bone of contention between the Bahmani and Vijayanagar kingdoms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Most authoritative account of Malik Kafur's Deccan campaign is given by?",
                  "options": [
                    "Amir Khusro",
                    "Hasan Nizami",
                    "Minhaj",
                    "Ziauddin Barani"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Amir Khusro",
                  "explanation": "Amir Khusro, a prominent Persian scholar and poet, provided the most authoritative account of Malik Kafur's Deccan campaign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which one of the following Sultans had close contact with Jain scholars?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutubuddin Aibak",
                    "Balban",
                    "Alauddin Khilji",
                    "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq was known for his intellectual curiosity and maintained close contact with Jain scholars during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of Gajapati dynasty of Orissa?",
                  "options": [
                    "Purushottama",
                    "Vidhyadhara",
                    "Kapilendra",
                    "Prataprudra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kapilendra",
                  "explanation": "Kapilendra was the founder of the Gajapati dynasty in Orissa, known for his expansionist policies and strong military."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The foreign traveler who visited and described Vijayanagar soon after its fall in the battle of Talikota was?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abdur Razzak",
                    "Ceasar Frederick",
                    "Nicolo Conti",
                    "Nuniz"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nuniz",
                  "explanation": "Nuniz, a Portuguese traveler, visited and documented the Vijayanagar kingdom soon after its fall in the battle of Talikota."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who of the following Vijayanagar kings had assumed the title 'Andhra Bhoja'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Devaraya II",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Virupaksha II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya, one of the most prominent rulers of Vijayanagar, assumed the title 'Andhra Bhoja' for his patronage of literature and arts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The first capital of Vijayanagar Empire was Hampi. Where was its second capital?",
                  "options": ["Vijayanagar", "Kanchi", "Bellore", "Penukonda"],
                  "answer": "Penukonda",
                  "explanation": "After the fall of Hampi, Penukonda became the second capital of the Vijayanagar Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following was the first Vijayanagar ruler to have the title of Maharajadhiraj?",
                  "options": ["Harihar II", "Harihar I", "Bukka I", "Bukka II"],
                  "answer": "Harihar II",
                  "explanation": "Harihar II, the second ruler of the Vijayanagar Empire, was the first to assume the title of Maharajadhiraj."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following kings of Vijayanagar sent an ambassador to China?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Harihar I",
                    "Harihar II",
                    "Devaraya II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bukka I",
                  "explanation": "Bukka I, one of the founders of the Vijayanagar Empire, sent an ambassador to China to establish diplomatic relations."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the districts called in the Vijayanagar Empire?",
                  "options": ["Nadu", "Khurram", "Kottain", "Janpad"],
                  "answer": "Nadu",
                  "explanation": "In the Vijayanagar Empire, districts were known as 'Nadu', a term that referred to administrative divisions in the kingdom."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the co-founder of the Vijayanagara Empire along with Harihara I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bukka Raya I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Rama Raya",
                    "Devaraya II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bukka Raya I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I and his brother Bukka Raya I founded the Vijayanagara Empire in 1336 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Harihara I establish the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": ["1336", "1346", "1356", "1366"],
                  "answer": "1336",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I, along with his brother Bukka Raya I, established the Vijayanagara Empire in 1336 AD."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Harihara I belong to before establishing the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Hoysalas",
                    "The Chalukyas",
                    "The Kakatiyas",
                    "The Yadavas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Hoysalas",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I and Bukka Raya I were originally from the Hoysala dynasty before establishing the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire during the reign of Harihara I?",
                  "options": ["Hampi", "Badami", "Bijapur", "Warangal"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "Hampi was the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire during the time of Harihara I and his successors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I's rule is notable for consolidating power in which region of South India?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "The Western Ghats",
                    "The Coastal Andhra",
                    "The Tamil Nadu region"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Deccan Plateau",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I and Bukka Raya I consolidated their power in the Deccan Plateau, establishing a strong foothold for the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important Hindu temple was constructed during the early years of the Vijayanagara Empire under Harihara I's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Virupaksha Temple",
                    "Hazar Rama Temple",
                    "Vittala Temple",
                    "Rama Temple"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Virupaksha Temple",
                  "explanation": "The Virupaksha Temple was an important religious site that was developed early in the Vijayanagara Empire under Harihara I's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I was known for his efforts in which of the following areas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promoting trade and commerce",
                    "Encouraging literature and arts",
                    "Strengthening military defenses",
                    "Expanding territory through conquests"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strengthening military defenses",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I focused on strengthening the military defenses of the Vijayanagara Empire to secure its territorial claims."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major empire did the Vijayanagara Empire initially face conflicts with during Harihara I's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "The Chola Empire",
                    "The Pandya Dynasty",
                    "The Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "During Harihara I's reign, the Vijayanagara Empire faced conflicts with the Bahmani Sultanate, which was a significant regional power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Harihara I's administration was known for its emphasis on which aspect?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land revenue reforms",
                    "Religious tolerance",
                    "Feudal land grants",
                    "Centralized bureaucracy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious tolerance",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I's administration is noted for its emphasis on religious tolerance, fostering a diverse and inclusive environment."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Harihara I as the ruler of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Bukka Raya II",
                    "Harihara II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bukka Raya II",
                  "explanation": "After the death of Harihara I, his brother Bukka Raya I initially took over, and his successors, including Bukka Raya II, continued the administration."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What significant historical event influenced Harihara I and his brother Bukka before they founded the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeat of the Kakatiya King of Warangal",
                    "The fall of the Chola Empire",
                    "The invasion of Timur",
                    "The rise of the Bahmani Sultanate"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeat of the Kakatiya King of Warangal",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I and Bukka were initially commanders in the army of the Kakatiya King of Warangal, whose defeat led to their captivity and eventual founding of Vijayanagara."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical source describes Harihara I as the ruler of the 'whole country between the eastern and the western seas'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Inscriptions",
                    "Travelogues",
                    "Epics",
                    "Chronicles"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Inscriptions",
                  "explanation": "The inscription dated 1346 describes Harihara I as ruling the entire territory between the eastern and western seas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which fortification was NOT a part of Harihara I’s defensive strategy?",
                  "options": ["Badami", "Gooty", "Udayagiri", "Hampi"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "While Harihara I fortified Badami, Gooty, and Udayagiri, Hampi was not specifically mentioned in his defensive strategies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did the nayankara system function under Harihara I’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land to commanders",
                    "Council of nobles",
                    "Centralized revenue",
                    "Diplomatic focus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land to commanders",
                  "explanation": "The nayankara system involved granting lands to military commanders to raise troops and maintain control over local areas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major challenge faced by Harihara I in maintaining his empire’s stability?",
                  "options": [
                    "Invasions by Delhi Sultanate and rival Hindu kings",
                    "Trade disruptions",
                    "Internal dissent",
                    "Low productivity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Invasions by Delhi Sultanate and rival Hindu kings",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I faced challenges from invasions by the Delhi Sultanate and rival Hindu kings, which he addressed through fortifications and military strategies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the administrative division of Harihara I’s kingdom known as?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sthalas, nadus, and simas",
                    "Rajyas, mandalas, and bhuktis",
                    "Zilas, talukas, and villages",
                    "Provinces, districts, and towns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sthalas, nadus, and simas",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I’s kingdom was divided into sthalas, nadus, and simas for administrative purposes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who played a crucial role in reorganizing the civil administration during Harihara I’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Anantarasa Chikka Udaiya",
                    "Vidyaranya",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Veera Ballala III"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Anantarasa Chikka Udaiya",
                  "explanation": "Anantarasa Chikka Udaiya was an able minister who helped reorganize the civil administration under Harihara I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did forests play in Harihara I’s economic strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cleared for agriculture",
                    "Preserved for hunting",
                    "Used for trade",
                    "Converted to parks"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cleared for agriculture",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I forced the clearing of forests to bring more land under cultivation, which increased the kingdom’s resources."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the titles used for Harihara I in contemporary Kannada inscriptions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Karnataka Vidya Vilas",
                    "Maharaja of Vijayanagara",
                    "Sultan of the South",
                    "Chakravarti"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Karnataka Vidya Vilas",
                  "explanation": "One of the titles used for Harihara I in Kannada inscriptions was Karnataka Vidya Vilas, meaning 'master of great knowledge and skills'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which province was NOT part of the original five rajyas held by the Sangama brothers?",
                  "options": ["Kampana", "Muddappa", "Marappa", "Bukka Raya"],
                  "answer": "Kampana",
                  "explanation": "Kampana was a governor in a different region, while the original five rajyas were held by the Sangama brothers including Muddappa and Marappa."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of Pushtimarg?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chaitanya Mahaprabhu",
                    "Vallabhacharya",
                    "Madhavacharya",
                    "Yamunacharya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vallabhacharya",
                  "explanation": "Vallabhacharya was the founder of Pushtimarg, a philosophical and devotional tradition of Hinduism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which capacity were thousands of women employed in the empire of Vijayanagar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Accountants",
                    "Royal bodyguards",
                    "Palace guards",
                    "All of these"
                  ],
                  "answer": "All of these",
                  "explanation": "Women in the Vijayanagar Empire were employed in various roles, including palace guards, accountants, and royal bodyguards, showcasing the significant role they played in society."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who built the city of Nagalapura?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bukka",
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya",
                    "Virupaksha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya, one of the greatest rulers of Vijayanagar, was responsible for building the city of Nagalapura."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which Hindu Kingdom of medieval India was the image of the deity Tirupati or Lord Venkateshvara depicted on its gold coins?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Vijayanagar Empire",
                    "The kingdom of Hoyasalas of Dwarasamudra",
                    "The kingdom of Kakathiyas of Warrangal",
                    "The kingdom of Yadavas of Devagiri"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Vijayanagar Empire",
                  "explanation": "The image of Lord Venkateshvara was depicted on the gold coins of the Vijayanagar Empire, symbolizing its connection to Vaishnavism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the religion of King Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": ["Vaishnavism", "Shaivism", "Jainism", "Buddhism"],
                  "answer": "Vaishnavism",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya was a follower of Vaishnavism, and his devotion to Lord Venkateshvara is well-documented."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The famous Hazara Ram temple was built by whom?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Devaraya I",
                    "Narasimha Salva",
                    "Krishnadeva Raya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya built the Hazara Ram temple in Hampi, which is renowned for its intricate carvings and depictions of the Ramayana."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following Telugu authors had the honor of Kanakabhiseka at the hands of Vijayanagar ruler Devaraya II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhairava Kavi",
                    "Nandi Mallaya",
                    "Potana",
                    "Srinatha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Srinatha",
                  "explanation": "Srinatha, a renowned Telugu poet, was honored by Devaraya II with Kanakabhiseka for his contributions to Telugu literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which one of the following dance traditions developed during the age of the Vijayanagar Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Yakshagana",
                    "Mohiniattam",
                    "Bharatanatyam",
                    "Kathakali"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bharatanatyam",
                  "explanation": "Bharatanatyam, a classical dance form, flourished during the Vijayanagar Empire and has since become one of India's most famous traditional dance forms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "'Amuktamalyada' written by Krishnadeva Raya, the ruler of Vijayanagar, was in which language?",
                  "options": ["Sanskrit", "Kannada", "Telugu", "Tamil"],
                  "answer": "Telugu",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadeva Raya wrote 'Amuktamalyada' in Telugu, which is a poetic work reflecting his devotion to Lord Vishnu."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The founder of the Bahmani Kingdom was?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Mujahid Shah",
                    "Ahmed Shah",
                    "Alauddin Bahman Shah",
                    "Tajuddin Firoz Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alauddin Bahman Shah",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Bahman Shah was the founder of the Bahmani Kingdom, which was a significant rival to the Vijayanagar Empire in South India."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was not one of the foreign travellers to visit India during the period of Krishnadeva Raya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fernando Nuniz",
                    "Domingo Paes",
                    "Duarte Barbosa",
                    "Nicolo Conti"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nicolo Conti",
                  "explanation": "Nicolo Conti visited India much before the reign of Krishnadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Match List-I with List-II and select the correct answer from the codes given below: List-I: A. Adil Shahi, B. Nizam Shahi, C. Immad Shahi, D. Qutub Shahi; List-II: 1. Ahmednagar, 2. Bijapur, 3. Golkonda, 4. Berar",
                  "options": [
                    "A-4 B-1 C-2 D-3",
                    "A-1 B-4 C-3 D-2",
                    "A-3 B-2 C-4 D-1",
                    "A-2 B-1 C-4 D-3"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A-2 B-1 C-4 D-3",
                  "explanation": "The correct matching of the kingdoms with their respective locations is: Adil Shahi with Bijapur, Nizam Shahi with Ahmednagar, Immad Shahi with Berar, and Qutub Shahi with Golkonda."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which two of the following foreign travelers came during the reign of Krishna Deva Raya and were Portugueses? 1. Nicolo Conti 2. Abdur Razzaq 3. Domingo Paes 4. Fernando Nuniz",
                  "options": ["1 and 3", "2 and 3", "1 and 4", "3 and 4"],
                  "answer": "3 and 4",
                  "explanation": "Domingo Paes and Fernando Nuniz were Portuguese travelers who visited during the reign of Krishnadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Consider the following statements: 1. Krishnadeva Raya was known as Andhra Bhoja. 2. He authored Amuklamalyada in Telugu and Jambavali Kalyanam in Sanskrit. 3. His court was adorned by eight celebrated poets called 'Ashtadiggajas'. Which of the above statements is/are correct?",
                  "options": [
                    "1 and 2 only",
                    "3 only",
                    "2 and 3 only",
                    "1, 2 and 3"
                  ],
                  "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
                  "explanation": "All the statements about Krishnadeva Raya are correct."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Consider the following statements about Vijaynagar Empire: 1. The city of Vijaynagar was located on the bank of river Tungabhadra. 2. The Raichur Doab was the region between Krishna and Tungabhadra rivers. Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
                  "options": [
                    "1 only",
                    "2 only",
                    "Both 1 and 2",
                    "Neither 1 nor 2"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Both 1 and 2",
                  "explanation": "Both statements are correct as Vijaynagar was located on the banks of the Tungabhadra and the Raichur Doab was the area between the Krishna and Tungabhadra rivers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Match List-I with List-II and select the correct answer: List-I: A. Abdur Razzak, B. Duarte Barbosa, C. Nicolo Conti, D. Nuniz; List-II: 1. Achyutadeva Raya, 2. Devaraya I, 3. Devaraya II, 4. Krishnadeva Raya",
                  "options": [
                    "A-4 B-3 C-2 D-1",
                    "A-3 B-4 C-2 D-1",
                    "A-3 B-4 C-1 D-2",
                    "A-2 B-1 C-4 D-3"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A-3 B-4 C-2 D-1",
                  "explanation": "Abdur Razzak visited Devaraya II, Duarte Barbosa visited Krishnadeva Raya, Nicolo Conti visited Devaraya I, and Nuniz visited Achyutadeva Raya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following statements about the Vijayanagara Empire is / are true? 1. The kings claimed to rule on behalf of the God Virupaksha. 2. Rulers used the title 'Hindu Suratrana'. 3. All Royal orders were signed in Kannada, Sanskrit, and Tamil. 4. Royal Portrait sculpture was displayed in temples.",
                  "options": [
                    "4 only",
                    "1 and 2 only",
                    "1, 2 and 3",
                    "1, 2 and 4"
                  ],
                  "answer": "1, 2 and 4",
                  "explanation": "The kings claimed to rule on behalf of God Virupaksha, used the title 'Hindu Suratrana', and displayed royal portraits in temples, but not all royal orders were signed in Kannada, Sanskrit, and Tamil."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Jata in medieval India meant:",
                  "options": [
                    "Land for religious personnel",
                    "Land revenue for army officers",
                    "Charity for education",
                    "Zamindar rights"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land for religious personnel",
                  "explanation": "Jata referred to land assigned to religious personnel for spiritual purposes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which kingdom did the temple of Hazara Rama belong to?",
                  "options": ["Avadh", "Travancore", "Vijayanagara", "Ahom"],
                  "answer": "Vijayanagara",
                  "explanation": "The Hazara Rama temple was built during the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Sun Temple of Konark was built by Narsimhadeva I. To which dynasty did he belong?",
                  "options": [
                    "Somavamsi dynasty",
                    "Imperial Ganga dynasty",
                    "Suryavansi Gajapti dynasty",
                    "Bhoi dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Imperial Ganga dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Narsimhadeva I belonged to the Imperial Ganga dynasty, which was responsible for building the Sun Temple at Konark."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Consider the following statements about Vijayanagara empire: 1. Vijayanagara was noted for its markets dealing in spices, textiles, and precious stones. 2. Krishnadeva Raya's rule was characterized by strain within the imperial structure. 3. The Amara-Nayakas were military commanders who were given territories to govern by the Royas. Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
                  "options": ["Only 3", "1 and 2", "1 and 3", "All of these"],
                  "answer": "1 and 3",
                  "explanation": "Statements 1 and 3 are correct. Vijayanagara was indeed noted for its trade markets and the Amara-Nayakas were military commanders assigned governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which one among the following was not a reform measure carried out by Mahmud Gawan of the Bahmani kingdom?",
                  "options": [
                    "Eight provinces or Tarafs",
                    "Nobles paid salaries and maintained horse contingents",
                    "Land Khalisa for Tarafdar expenses",
                    "Land measured and taxes fixed"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land Khalisa for Tarafdar expenses",
                  "explanation": "The establishment of Khalisa for the Tarafdar's expenses was not a reform under Mahmud Gawan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Marco Polo's trip to India (1271 AD) earned much fame in Europe on account of:",
                  "options": [
                    "Discovering a safe route to India",
                    "Establishing relations with Indian Kings",
                    "His account of the East's conditions",
                    "All of the above"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His account of the East's conditions",
                  "explanation": "Marco Polo's detailed accounts of commercial, religious, and social conditions in the East brought him fame in Europe."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The ruins of Vijayanagara at Hampi were brought to light in 1800 by:",
                  "options": [
                    "Colonel Colin Mackenzie",
                    "Sir John Shore",
                    "Andrew Eraser",
                    "John Marshall"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Colonel Colin Mackenzie",
                  "explanation": "The ruins of Hampi were rediscovered by Colonel Colin Mackenzie in 1800."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Tungbhadra River provided sustenance to which empire?",
                  "options": ["Chola", "Vijayanagara", "Vakataka", "Pandya"],
                  "answer": "Vijayanagara",
                  "explanation": "The Vijayanagara Empire was sustained by the Tungbhadra River."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Niccolo de Conti, Abdur Razzaq, Afanasy Nikitin, and Fernao Nuniz visit?",
                  "options": [
                    "The empire of Kannauj",
                    "Vijayanagara Empire",
                    "Hoysala Empire",
                    "Rashtrakuta Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vijayanagara Empire",
                  "explanation": "These travelers visited the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Bahmani kingdom was founded in:",
                  "options": [
                    "15th century A.D.",
                    "14th century A.D.",
                    "13th century A.D.",
                    "16th century A.D."
                  ],
                  "answer": "14th century A.D.",
                  "explanation": "The Bahmani kingdom was founded in the 14th century."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Krishnadeveraya of the Vijayanagar Empire was a contemporary of:",
                  "options": ["Akbar", "Firoz Shah Tughlaq", "Babur", "Balban"],
                  "answer": "Babur",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadevaraya was a contemporary of Babur."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Vijayanagara, which was founded in the fourteenth century, was the name of:",
                  "options": [
                    "A city",
                    "An empire",
                    "Both a city and an empire",
                    "Neither city nor an empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Both a city and an empire",
                  "explanation": "Vijayanagara was both a city and an empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where is the famous Vijaya Vittal temple, having its 56 carved pillars emitting musical notes, located?",
                  "options": ["Balur", "Bhadrachalam", "Hampi", "Srirongam"],
                  "answer": "Hampi",
                  "explanation": "The Vijaya Vittal Temple is located in Hampi, known for its musical pillars."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 11,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of the Bahmani Kingdom?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Hassan",
                    "Firoz Shah",
                    "Mahmud Gaonwa",
                    "Asaf Khan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alauddin Hassan",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Hassan Bahman Shah, also known as Hasan Gangu, was the founder of the Bahmani Kingdom in 1347."
                },
                {
                  "question": "During whose reign did the Persian traveller 'Abdurrajjak' visit India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dev Rai I",
                    "Krishna Dev Rai I",
                    "Dev Rai II",
                    "Krishna Rai II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dev Rai II",
                  "explanation": "Persian traveller Abdur Razzaq visited India during the reign of Deva Raya II of the Vijayanagara Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the Persian translation of Mahabharata?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sakinat-ul-Auliya",
                    "Sirrul Asrar",
                    "Anwar-i-Suhaili",
                    "Razmnama"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Razmnama",
                  "explanation": "The Persian translation of the Mahabharata is called 'Razmnama' and was commissioned by the Mughal Emperor Akbar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who among the following rulers is known for the construction of the famous city of Bidar in the Bahmani kingdom?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Bahman Shah",
                    "Mahmud Gawan",
                    "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah",
                    "Muhammad Shah III"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah",
                  "explanation": "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah is credited with developing the city of Bidar, which became the capital of the Bahmani kingdom."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Bahmani ruler was known for his intellectual pursuits and was an expert in many sciences, including mathematics, astronomy, and medicine?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Bahman Shah",
                    "Mahmud Gawan",
                    "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah",
                    "Ahmad Shah Wali"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah",
                  "explanation": "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah was a polymath, known for his expertise in various sciences and for promoting learning in the Bahmani kingdom."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the first king of the Vijayanagara Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Deva Raya I",
                    "Krishnadevaraya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harihara I",
                  "explanation": "Harihara I was the founder of the Vijayanagara Empire along with his brother Bukka I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagara ruler was the patron of the famous Telugu poet Tenali Ramakrishna?",
                  "options": [
                    "Deva Raya II",
                    "Krishnadevaraya",
                    "Harihara II",
                    "Saluva Narasimha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadevaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadevaraya was the patron of several scholars, including the famous Telugu poet Tenali Ramakrishna."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Bahmani ruler is known for reforming the administrative structure of the kingdom by dividing it into eight provinces or Tarafs?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Bahman Shah",
                    "Mahmud Gawan",
                    "Taj ud-Din Firuz Shah",
                    "Ahmad Shah Wali"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mahmud Gawan",
                  "explanation": "Mahmud Gawan was a key figure in reforming the Bahmani administration by dividing the kingdom into eight Tarafs or provinces."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Vijayanagara ruler’s reign marked the empire's peak in military and cultural achievements?",
                  "options": [
                    "Harihara I",
                    "Krishnadevaraya",
                    "Bukka I",
                    "Deva Raya II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Krishnadevaraya",
                  "explanation": "Krishnadevaraya’s reign marked the peak of the Vijayanagara Empire in terms of military conquests and cultural achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which temple in Hampi, constructed during the Vijayanagara Empire, is famous for its intricately carved musical pillars?",
                  "options": [
                    "Virupaksha Temple",
                    "Vittala Temple",
                    "Hazara Rama Temple",
                    "Lotus Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vittala Temple",
                  "explanation": "The Vittala Temple in Hampi is renowned for its musical pillars, which produce musical notes when struck."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },

    {
      "topicName": "Maurya Empire",
      "subtopics": [
        {
          "subtopicName": "Chandragupta Maurya",
          "description": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya founded the Maurya Empire and was the first emperor to unify most of India.",
            "Chandragupta Maurya was the founder of the Maurya Empire in ancient India.",
            "Chandragupta Maurya established the Maurya Empire around 321 BCE, after overthrowing the Nanda dynasty.",
            "With the guidance of his mentor Chanakya, Chandragupta Maurya built one of the largest empires in Indian history.",
            "Chandragupta Maurya unified most of the Indian subcontinent under one rule for the first time.",
            "After a successful reign, Chandragupta Maurya abdicated the throne and became a Jain monk."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of the Maurya Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka the Great",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Dhana Nanda"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya founded the Maurya Empire, which ruled over a vast region of South Asia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Chandragupta Maurya defeat to establish the Maurya Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Gupta Empire",
                    "The Mughal Empire",
                    "The Nanda Empire",
                    "The Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Nanda Empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya defeated the Nanda Empire to establish his own Maurya Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya's primary achievement in his early reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanding into Central Asia",
                    "Defeating Alexander",
                    "Consolidating control over India",
                    "Establishing trade routes to Europe"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidating control over India",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya focused on consolidating control over the Indian subcontinent during his early reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous historical figure did Chandragupta Maurya confront in the Seleucid–Mauryan war?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucus I Nicator",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Julius Caesar",
                    "Cyrus the Great"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucus I Nicator",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya confronted Seleucus I Nicator in the Seleucid–Mauryan war."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the primary source that describes Chandragupta Maurya's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Arthashastra",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Puranas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Arthashastra",
                  "explanation": "The Arthashastra, written by Chanakya, describes Chandragupta Maurya's rule and his administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Chandragupta Maurya's famous advisor and mentor?",
                  "options": ["Chanakya", "Aryabhata", "Kalidasa", "Buddha"],
                  "answer": "Chanakya",
                  "explanation": "Chanakya, also known as Kautilya, was Chandragupta Maurya's advisor and mentor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Greek historian wrote about Chandragupta Maurya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Plutarch",
                    "Herodotus",
                    "Thucydides",
                    "Diodorus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diodorus",
                  "explanation": "Diodorus, a Greek historian, wrote about Chandragupta Maurya in his historical accounts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where did Chandragupta Maurya's empire extend to in the west?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "The Hindu Kush",
                    "The Ganges Plain",
                    "The Indus River"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Hindu Kush",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's empire extended up to the Hindu Kush in the west."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital of Chandragupta Maurya's empire?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ujjain", "Delhi", "Mathura"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Pataliputra (modern-day Patna) was the capital of Chandragupta Maurya's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religious practice did Chandragupta Maurya reportedly follow?",
                  "options": [
                    "Buddhism",
                    "Jainism",
                    "Hinduism",
                    "Zoroastrianism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hinduism",
                  "explanation": "Contemporary Greek sources indicate that Chandragupta Maurya followed Vedic Brahminism, not Jainism."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of the Mauryan dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Alexander the Great"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya founded the Mauryan dynasty around 321 BCE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya’s main contribution to India’s political landscape?",
                  "options": [
                    "Unifying India under one administration",
                    "Establishing the Gupta Empire",
                    "Expanding the Mughal Empire",
                    "Forming the Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Unifying India under one administration",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's primary contribution was unifying India under a single administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Chandragupta Maurya’s teacher and advisor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhadrabahu I",
                    "Kautilya (Chanakya)",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kautilya (Chanakya)",
                  "explanation": "Kautilya, also known as Chanakya, was Chandragupta Maurya’s teacher and advisor, and he played a significant role in his rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle did Chandragupta Maurya win to end the autocracy of the Nanda dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Kalinga",
                    "Battle of Bhaddasala",
                    "Battle of Plassey",
                    "Battle of Panipat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Bhaddasala",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya defeated the Nanda dynasty in the Battle of Bhaddasala, marking the end of their rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where was Chandragupta Maurya born?",
                  "options": [
                    "Taxila",
                    "Magadha",
                    "Pataliputra",
                    "Shravanbelagola"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Magadha",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya was born in Magadha, which was the region where he later established his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the profession of Chandragupta’s guardians before he became a ruler?",
                  "options": ["Hunters", "Brahmins", "Merchants", "Soldiers"],
                  "answer": "Hunters",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's guardians were hunters before he became a ruler."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who did Chandragupta Maurya defeat in 305 BCE to secure his empire’s western border?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucus I Nicator",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Darius III",
                    "Porus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucus I Nicator",
                  "explanation": "In 305 BCE, Chandragupta Maurya defeated Seleucus I Nicator to secure the western border of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of Chandragupta Maurya’s famous text on politics?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vedas",
                    "Manusmriti",
                    "Artha-shastra",
                    "Upanishads"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Artha-shastra",
                  "explanation": "The 'Artha-shastra' is the famous text on politics authored by Kautilya (Chanakya) during Chandragupta Maurya’s time."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Chandragupta Maurya conquer to expand his empire in the north-west?",
                  "options": ["Punjab", "Kashmir", "Sindh", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Punjab",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya expanded his empire into the Punjab region in the north-west."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta Maurya’s rule extended to which ancient Persian empire’s borders?",
                  "options": [
                    "Achaemenid Empire",
                    "Sassanian Empire",
                    "Seleucid Empire",
                    "Parthian Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Achaemenid Empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s rule extended to the borders of the Achaemenid Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What did Chandragupta Maurya do after the death of Alexander the Great?",
                  "options": [
                    "He fled to Greece.",
                    "He returned to Magadha.",
                    "He conquered the Punjab region.",
                    "He settled in Taxila."
                  ],
                  "answer": "He conquered the Punjab region.",
                  "explanation": "After the death of Alexander the Great, Chandragupta Maurya capitalized on the power vacuum and conquered the Punjab region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where did Chandragupta Maurya spend his last days?",
                  "options": [
                    "Taxila",
                    "Pataliputra",
                    "Shravanbelagola",
                    "Gandhara"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shravanbelagola",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya spent his last days in Shravanbelagola, where he adopted Jainism and lived a life of renunciation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which sage influenced Chandragupta Maurya to accept Jainism?",
                  "options": ["Kautilya", "Bhadrabahu I", "Ashoka", "Buddha"],
                  "answer": "Bhadrabahu I",
                  "explanation": "Bhadrabahu I, a Jain sage, influenced Chandragupta Maurya to adopt Jainism later in his life."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the cause of Chandragupta Maurya’s sorrowful end?",
                  "options": [
                    "His military defeats",
                    "The famine that struck his empire",
                    "The loss of his empire to outsiders",
                    "His failure to expand further"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The famine that struck his empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's later years were marked by sorrow due to a severe famine that affected his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta Maurya’s empire was known for its extensive reach in which direction?",
                  "options": [
                    "North and West",
                    "South and East",
                    "East and North",
                    "South and West"
                  ],
                  "answer": "North and West",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's empire extended extensively towards the north and west."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle did Chandragupta Maurya fight to end the rule of the Nanda dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Pataliputra",
                    "Battle of Bhaddasala",
                    "Battle of Magadha",
                    "Battle of Taxila"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Bhaddasala",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Bhaddasala was pivotal in ending the Nanda dynasty's rule and establishing the Mauryan dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Chandragupta Maurya’s main rival before he founded the Mauryan dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Guptas",
                    "The Nandas",
                    "The Mughals",
                    "The Rajputs"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Nandas",
                  "explanation": "Before founding the Mauryan dynasty, Chandragupta Maurya's main rival was the Nanda dynasty, which he eventually overthrew."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Chandragupta Maurya establish to secure his empire’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "An advanced postal system",
                    "A network of spies",
                    "A powerful navy",
                    "A system of feudal lords"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A network of spies",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya established a sophisticated network of spies to ensure the security and efficient administration of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Greek conqueror's representative did Chandragupta Maurya defeat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Darius III",
                    "Seleucus I Nicator",
                    "Porus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucus I Nicator",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya defeated Seleucus I Nicator, who was a representative of Alexander the Great's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main focus of the Artha-shastra written by Kautilya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Philosophy",
                    "Medicine",
                    "Material Gain and Governance",
                    "Religion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Material Gain and Governance",
                  "explanation": "The 'Artha-shastra' written by Kautilya focused on strategies for material gain and effective governance."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What significant military conflict did Chandragupta Maurya engage in with Seleucus I Nicator?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Macedonian Invasion",
                    "The Seleucid–Mauryan War",
                    "The Greek–Indian War",
                    "The Persian Conquest"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Seleucid–Mauryan War",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya fought the Seleucid–Mauryan War against Seleucus I Nicator."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical text attributes the consolidation of Chandragupta Maurya's empire to Chanakya's strategies?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Arthashastra",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Manusmriti"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Arthashastra",
                  "explanation": "Chanakya's Arthashastra describes the strategies that helped Chandragupta consolidate his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya's relationship with Alexander the Great?",
                  "options": [
                    "Allied ruler",
                    "Adversary",
                    "Protector",
                    "Neighboring king"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adversary",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya was an adversary of Alexander the Great, particularly after Alexander's withdrawal from India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya's reign impact the political landscape of South Asia?",
                  "options": [
                    "Established a centralized empire",
                    "Promoted regional independence",
                    "Encouraged foreign invasions",
                    "Focused on internal strife"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Established a centralized empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's reign established a centralized empire across South Asia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Chanakya play in the establishment of the Maurya Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military commander",
                    "Royal astrologer",
                    "Political strategist",
                    "Economic advisor"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Political strategist",
                  "explanation": "Chanakya, also known as Kautilya, was a key political strategist in the establishment of the Maurya Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty succeeded Chandragupta Maurya's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Gupta Dynasty",
                    "The Nanda Dynasty",
                    "The Maurya Dynasty",
                    "The Pala Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Maurya Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya was succeeded by the Maurya Dynasty, with his grandson Ashoka being one of the most notable rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main focus of Chandragupta Maurya's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military expansion",
                    "Trade and commerce",
                    "Cultural development",
                    "Religious reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military expansion",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya focused primarily on military expansion and consolidating his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian recorded the interactions between Chandragupta Maurya and Alexander the Great?",
                  "options": [
                    "Megasthenes",
                    "Pliny the Elder",
                    "Arrian",
                    "Strabo"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Megasthenes",
                  "explanation": "Megasthenes, a Greek ambassador, recorded interactions between Chandragupta Maurya and Alexander the Great."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya's approach towards local rulers in his empire?",
                  "options": ["Direct rule", "Autonomy", "Neglect", "Conflict"],
                  "answer": "Autonomy",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya allowed a degree of autonomy to local rulers while maintaining central control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major infrastructure development did Chandragupta Maurya initiate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fortifications and roads",
                    "Educational institutions",
                    "Religious temples",
                    "Public baths"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fortifications and roads",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya initiated the development of fortifications and roads to strengthen his empire's infrastructure."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What significant reform did Chandragupta Maurya implement in administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of a standing army",
                    "Creation of a secret service",
                    "Introduction of land reforms",
                    "Implementation of a new tax system"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Creation of a secret service",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya established a sophisticated network of spies and a secret service to maintain control and ensure the security of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient kingdom did Chandragupta Maurya initially challenge to gain control over Magadha?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mauryan Kingdom",
                    "The Nanda Kingdom",
                    "The Gupta Kingdom",
                    "The Chola Kingdom"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Nanda Kingdom",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya initially challenged the Nanda Kingdom to gain control over Magadha, which was a significant achievement in his rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason behind Chandragupta Maurya’s successful consolidation of power?",
                  "options": [
                    "His military skills",
                    "His alliance with foreign powers",
                    "His effective administration and diplomacy",
                    "His religious reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His effective administration and diplomacy",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's effective administration and diplomatic strategies were key to his successful consolidation of power and establishment of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the end of Chandragupta Maurya’s conflict with the Greeks?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Taxila",
                    "Battle of Punjab",
                    "Battle of Chandragupta",
                    "Battle of Seleucia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Seleucia was significant in ending the conflict between Chandragupta Maurya and the Greek general Seleucus I Nicator."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta Maurya’s empire was one of the largest in history. Which two geographical extremes did it span?",
                  "options": [
                    "Himalayas and Deccan Plateau",
                    "Vindhya Range and Persian Border",
                    "Gangetic Plain and Arabian Sea",
                    "Western Ghats and Bay of Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vindhya Range and Persian Border",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's empire extended from the Vindhya Range in the south to the Persian Border in the northwest."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the focus of Chandragupta Maurya’s administrative reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthening trade routes",
                    "Enhancing military strategy",
                    "Centralizing control and governance",
                    "Promoting religious harmony"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralizing control and governance",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya focused on centralizing control and governance to ensure effective administration and stability in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which area did Chandragupta Maurya manage to secure through his military conquests following Alexander’s death?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "The Punjab region",
                    "The Bengal region",
                    "The Southern tip of India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Punjab region",
                  "explanation": "Following Alexander's death, Chandragupta Maurya secured the Punjab region through his military conquests, expanding his empire's territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya ensure loyalty and control over his vast empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "By establishing a network of spies",
                    "By forming alliances with neighboring kingdoms",
                    "By employing mercenary forces",
                    "By implementing trade agreements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By establishing a network of spies",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya ensured loyalty and control over his empire through a well-established network of spies and secret police."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya’s approach to handling dissent within his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Exile of dissenters",
                    "Execution of leaders",
                    "Use of spies and secret police",
                    "Redistribution of land"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Use of spies and secret police",
                  "explanation": "To handle dissent within his empire, Chandragupta Maurya employed spies and secret police to monitor and manage opposition effectively."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Indian dynasty did Chandragupta Maurya overthrow to establish his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Dynasty",
                    "Nanda Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Satavahana Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Nanda Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya overthrew the Nanda Dynasty to establish his own rule and founded the Mauryan Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of Kautilya in Chandragupta Maurya’s rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military commander",
                    "Diplomatic envoy",
                    "Political strategist and mentor",
                    "Religious advisor"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Political strategist and mentor",
                  "explanation": "Kautilya, also known as Chanakya, was the political strategist and mentor who guided Chandragupta Maurya in overthrowing the Nanda dynasty and establishing the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major historical figure’s departure from India allowed Chandragupta Maurya to expand his empire into the Punjab region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Darius III",
                    "Seleucus I Nicator",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Chandragupta II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alexander the Great",
                  "explanation": "Alexander the Great’s departure from India after his campaign left a power vacuum, allowing Chandragupta Maurya to conquer the Punjab region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty’s decline did Chandragupta Maurya exploit to rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Gupta Dynasty",
                    "The Nanda Dynasty",
                    "The Satavahana Dynasty",
                    "The Chola Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Nanda Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya exploited the decline of the Nanda Dynasty to establish his rule and lay the foundation for the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta Maurya’s primary strategy to maintain control over his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Forming marriage alliances",
                    "Developing a sophisticated administration",
                    "Building extensive trade networks",
                    "Establishing military fortifications"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Developing a sophisticated administration",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya maintained control over his empire through a highly organized and centralized administration, a strategy influenced by Kautilya’s Artha-shastra."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text by Kautilya influenced Chandragupta Maurya’s rule and governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Mahabharata",
                    "Artha-shastra",
                    "Upanishads"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Artha-shastra",
                  "explanation": "Kautilya’s Artha-shastra, a treatise on statecraft and governance, played a key role in shaping the administrative and political strategies of Chandragupta Maurya’s rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Chandragupta Maurya’s military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanding trade routes",
                    "Securing border regions",
                    "Suppressing internal revolts",
                    "Establishing diplomatic relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Securing border regions",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s military campaigns primarily focused on securing the empire's border regions to strengthen and protect the empire from external threats."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Chandragupta Maurya’s empire reach during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Modern-day Bangladesh",
                    "Modern-day Pakistan",
                    "Modern-day Nepal",
                    "Modern-day Sri Lanka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Modern-day Pakistan",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s empire extended into modern-day Pakistan, particularly after securing the Punjab region through military conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which advisor played a crucial role in Chandragupta Maurya’s rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chanakya (Kautilya)",
                    "Bharat",
                    "Aristotle",
                    "Kalidasa"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chanakya (Kautilya)",
                  "explanation": "Chanakya, also known as Kautilya, was a key advisor and strategist who played a crucial role in Chandragupta Maurya’s rise to power, helping to establish the Maurya Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical figure’s influence did Chandragupta Maurya encounter while he was in Taxila?",
                  "options": [
                    "Darius III",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alexander the Great",
                  "explanation": "While in Taxila, Chandragupta Maurya encountered the influence of Alexander the Great, whose campaign in the region shaped the political landscape."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason behind Chandragupta Maurya’s shift to Jainism later in life?",
                  "options": [
                    "To strengthen his political alliances",
                    "His desire for spiritual enlightenment",
                    "Influence of the famine and Bhadrabahu I",
                    "To appease his subjects"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Influence of the famine and Bhadrabahu I",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya adopted Jainism later in life under the influence of the Jain sage Bhadrabahu I and the impact of a severe famine in his empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who did Chandragupta Maurya defeat to end the rule of the Nanda Dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dhanananda",
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Bhadrabahu",
                    "Seleucus Nikator"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dhanananda",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya defeated Dhanananda, the last ruler of the Nanda Dynasty, to establish the Maurya Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta Maurya’s marriage with the daughter of which ruler was a part of a peace treaty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander",
                    "Seleucus Nikator",
                    "Cyrus the Great",
                    "Darius"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucus Nikator",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya married the daughter of Seleucus Nikator as part of a peace treaty between the Mauryan Empire and the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire was established as a result of Chandragupta Maurya’s conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Maurya Empire",
                    "Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Maurya Empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta's conquests led to the establishment of the Maurya Empire, one of the largest empires in ancient India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Greek historian wrote about Chandragupta Maurya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Herodotus",
                    "Megasthenes",
                    "Pliny the Elder",
                    "Thucydides"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Megasthenes",
                  "explanation": "Megasthenes, a Greek historian and ambassador, wrote extensively about Chandragupta Maurya in his work 'Indica'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major geographical boundary did Chandragupta’s empire reach in the north?",
                  "options": [
                    "Himalayas",
                    "Gobi Desert",
                    "Sahara Desert",
                    "Caspian Sea"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Himalayas",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's empire extended up to the Himalayan mountain range in the north."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What type of government did the Mauryas replace in ancient India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Monarchy",
                    "Republican and oligarchical governments",
                    "Democratic",
                    "Federal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Republican and oligarchical governments",
                  "explanation": "The Mauryas replaced the republican and oligarchical governments in India with a centralized monarchy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religion did Chandragupta Maurya adopt towards the end of his life?",
                  "options": ["Hinduism", "Buddhism", "Jainism", "Islam"],
                  "answer": "Jainism",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya adopted Jainism later in life and is believed to have abdicated the throne to become a monk."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the main source of historical evidence of Chandragupta Maurya found in the 2nd century CE?",
                  "options": [
                    "Junagarh inscription",
                    "Rosetta Stone",
                    "Sanchi Stupa",
                    "Delhi Iron Pillar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Junagarh inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Junagarh inscription provides important historical evidence of Chandragupta Maurya's reign and achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Mauryan king was Chandragupta Maurya’s grandson and is considered one of the greatest rulers in Indian history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Dhanananda",
                    "Harshavardhana"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka, Chandragupta's grandson, is considered one of the greatest rulers in Indian history due to his spread of Buddhism and welfare policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Greek ambassador visited Chandragupta Maurya’s court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aristophanes",
                    "Megasthenes",
                    "Strabo",
                    "Diodorus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Megasthenes",
                  "explanation": "The famous Greek ambassador who visited Chandragupta Maurya’s court was Megasthenes."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for Chandragupta Maurya's conflict with Seleucus I Nicator?",
                  "options": [
                    "Territorial expansion",
                    "Trade disagreements",
                    "Dynastic succession",
                    "Religious differences"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Territorial expansion",
                  "explanation": "The conflict with Seleucus I Nicator was primarily driven by territorial expansion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient text provides detailed accounts of Chandragupta Maurya's administration and governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Arthashastra",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Manusmriti"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Arthashastra",
                  "explanation": "The Arthashastra, authored by Chanakya, provides detailed accounts of Chandragupta Maurya's administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya's military strategies influence the political dynamics of ancient India?",
                  "options": [
                    "By creating alliances",
                    "By establishing a centralized bureaucracy",
                    "By encouraging regional rivalries",
                    "By focusing on economic reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By establishing a centralized bureaucracy",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's military strategies established a centralized bureaucracy that influenced political dynamics."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Chandragupta Maurya's alliances play in his rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Securing military support",
                    "Strengthening trade routes",
                    "Gaining religious endorsements",
                    "Encouraging cultural exchange"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Securing military support",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's alliances were crucial in securing military support to rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which foreign dignitary is known to have written about Chandragupta Maurya's empire from an external perspective?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diodorus",
                    "Pliny the Elder",
                    "Arrian",
                    "Strabo"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diodorus",
                  "explanation": "Diodorus, a Greek historian, provided an external perspective on Chandragupta Maurya's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Chandragupta Maurya's reforms in his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Taxation and legal codes",
                    "Cultural patronage",
                    "Religious reforms",
                    "Economic trade policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taxation and legal codes",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's reforms primarily focused on taxation and establishing legal codes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the historical significance of Chandragupta Maurya's interaction with Alexander the Great?",
                  "options": [
                    "Formation of alliances",
                    "Introduction of Greek culture",
                    "Negotiation of peace treaties",
                    "Expansion into Europe"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Negotiation of peace treaties",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's interaction with Alexander the Great led to the negotiation of peace treaties."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region was a major area of conflict between Chandragupta Maurya and the Seleucid Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Indus Valley",
                    "The Ganges Plain",
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "The Western Ghats"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Indus Valley",
                  "explanation": "The Indus Valley was a major area of conflict between Chandragupta Maurya and the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya's policies impact the development of trade in ancient India?",
                  "options": [
                    "By establishing trade routes",
                    "By focusing on isolationism",
                    "By promoting foreign invasions",
                    "By discouraging trade partnerships"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By establishing trade routes",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's policies included the establishment of trade routes that facilitated economic development."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Chandragupta Maurya's reign on subsequent Indian dynasties?",
                  "options": [
                    "Set precedents for centralized rule",
                    "Promoted regional fragmentation",
                    "Encouraged foreign dominance",
                    "Focused on religious reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Set precedents for centralized rule",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya's reign set important precedents for centralized rule that influenced subsequent Indian dynasties."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which administrative system did Chandragupta Maurya’s rule resemble in its structure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Roman Republic",
                    "Achaemenid Empire",
                    "Ottoman Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Achaemenid Empire",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s centralized administrative system was modeled on the Achaemenid Empire, which also had a highly organized bureaucracy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the nature of Chandragupta Maurya’s relationship with the Nanda dynasty before he established his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Supporter of the Nandas",
                    "Rival seeking to overthrow",
                    "Alliance with the Nandas",
                    "Neutral"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rival seeking to overthrow",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya, with the help of Kautilya, actively plotted to overthrow the Nanda dynasty, viewing them as a major obstacle to his ambition of establishing a new empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Chandragupta Maurya’s conquests on the power dynamics in the Indian subcontinent?",
                  "options": [
                    "Divided into smaller states",
                    "Unified under one rule",
                    "Established a feudal system",
                    "Promoted regional independence"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Unified under one rule",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s conquests brought most of the Indian subcontinent under his control, marking the beginning of a unified and centralized empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the significant military strategies used by Chandragupta Maurya to defeat the Nandas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Guerilla warfare",
                    "War elephants",
                    "Siege warfare",
                    "Naval blockade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "War elephants",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya employed war elephants as a key part of his military strategy, which played a crucial role in defeating the Nanda dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya manage to maintain control over such a vast empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alliances with foreign powers",
                    "Centralized bureaucracy and surveillance",
                    "Network of fortresses",
                    "Cultural integration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized bureaucracy and surveillance",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya maintained control over his vast empire by creating a centralized bureaucracy and implementing an extensive surveillance system to monitor officials and subjects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which specific policy was introduced under Chandragupta Maurya’s rule to ensure the security of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land reforms",
                    "Military conscription",
                    "Secret police",
                    "Trade regulation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Secret police",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya introduced the concept of a secret police to maintain law and order and to ensure loyalty among his subjects and officials."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Chandragupta Maurya’s interaction with Alexander the Great influence his political ambitions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Inspired to conquer Greece",
                    "Seek alliances with Greek states",
                    "Assert rule over Indian territories",
                    "Adopt Greek military tactics"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Assert rule over Indian territories",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s encounter with Alexander the Great inspired him to challenge the existing power structures in India and establish his own empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Greek historical figure’s departure from India allowed Chandragupta Maurya to consolidate power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Demetrius",
                    "Seleucus I Nicator",
                    "Ptolemy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alexander the Great",
                  "explanation": "After Alexander the Great’s departure from India, Chandragupta Maurya was able to consolidate power and expand his empire in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the long-term impact of Chandragupta Maurya’s establishment of the Mauryan dynasty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fragmentation into several states",
                    "Model of centralized governance",
                    "Decline of trade in India",
                    "Beginning of colonial rule"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Model of centralized governance",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta Maurya’s establishment of a centralized and well-structured governance system set a precedent for future Indian empires."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Chandragupta Maurya’s achievements was directly influenced by his mentor Kautilya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing trade routes",
                    "Developing military strategies",
                    "Creating a system of espionage",
                    "Initiating land reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Creating a system of espionage",
                  "explanation": "Kautilya, also known as Chanakya, influenced Chandragupta Maurya to establish an extensive espionage system, which was vital for maintaining control over his vast empire."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Ashoka",
          "description": [
            "Ashoka was one of the greatest emperors of the Maurya Empire, ruling from around 268 to 232 BCE.",
            "After the bloody Kalinga War, Ashoka embraced Buddhism and promoted peace and non-violence.",
            "Ashoka is known for spreading Buddhism across Asia through missionaries and his inscriptions on edicts.",
            "Ashoka's reign marked a significant era of social welfare, with the construction of hospitals, roads, and educational institutions.",
            "The Ashoka Chakra, featured on India's national flag, symbolizes his influence and legacy."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "An Indian Emperor",
                    "A Greek Philosopher",
                    "A Roman General",
                    "A Chinese Emperor"
                  ],
                  "answer": "An Indian Emperor",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was an Indian Emperor from the Mauryan dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Ashoka rule over?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mauryan Empire",
                    "The Gupta Empire",
                    "The Mughal Empire",
                    "The Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Mauryan Empire",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was a ruler of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major event influenced Ashoka's conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Kalinga War",
                    "The Battle of Plassey",
                    "The Battle of Thermopylae",
                    "The Fall of Constantinople"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Kalinga War",
                  "explanation": "The Kalinga War was a turning point for Ashoka, leading him to embrace Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which edict includes inscriptions by Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Major Rock Edict",
                    "The Ashoka Pillar",
                    "The Iron Pillar",
                    "The Aśoka Edict"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Major Rock Edict",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's Major Rock Edict contains inscriptions from his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the Ashoka Chakra?",
                  "options": [
                    "A symbol on the Indian Flag",
                    "A type of ancient coin",
                    "A famous Buddhist stupa",
                    "A historic battle"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A symbol on the Indian Flag",
                  "explanation": "The Ashoka Chakra is featured at the center of the Indian National Flag."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient text describes Ashoka's role in Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dipavamsa",
                    "Mahabharata",
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Puranas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dipavamsa",
                  "explanation": "The Dipavamsa is a text that highlights Ashoka's contributions to Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Ashoka support to spread Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Missionaries",
                    "Military Conquests",
                    "Economic Policies",
                    "Scientific Research"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Missionaries",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka supported Buddhist missionaries to spread Buddhism across Asia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where was Ashoka's capital?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Pataliputra was the capital of Ashoka's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these inscriptions is related to Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Sirkap Inscription",
                    "The Ashoka Edict",
                    "The Gupta Inscription",
                    "The Mauryan Pillar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Sirkap Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Sirkap Inscription is connected to Ashoka's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka's edicts focus mainly on which topic?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dhamma",
                    "Military Strategies",
                    "Trade Routes",
                    "Royal Lineage"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dhamma",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's edicts primarily discuss 'dhamma' or righteous conduct."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary religion Ashoka promoted during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hinduism",
                    "Buddhism",
                    "Jainism",
                    "Zoroastrianism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Buddhism",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka is known for promoting Buddhism and spreading its teachings during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Ashoka rule as the last major emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Empire",
                    "Nanda Empire",
                    "Mauryan Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mauryan Empire",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was the last major emperor of the Mauryan Empire, ruling from 268 to 232 BCE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the country Ashoka conquered that led to his conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": ["Kalinga", "Punjab", "Kashmir", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Kalinga",
                  "explanation": "The conquest of Kalinga, marked by immense bloodshed, led Ashoka to embrace Buddhism and promote non-violence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Ashoka call his policy of ruling by moral principles?",
                  "options": ["Dharma", "Karma", "Moksha", "Nirvana"],
                  "answer": "Dharma",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s policy of ruling by moral principles was known as Dharma, focusing on ethical governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the Lion Capital of Ashoka now a part of?",
                  "options": [
                    "A museum in Delhi",
                    "The Indian national emblem",
                    "A Buddhist stupa",
                    "A historic fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Indian national emblem",
                  "explanation": "The Lion Capital of Ashoka is part of the Indian national emblem, symbolizing strength and courage."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT one of Ashoka’s contributions to public welfare?",
                  "options": [
                    "Founding hospitals",
                    "Planting roadside trees",
                    "Constructing temples for Hindu gods",
                    "Digging wells"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Constructing temples for Hindu gods",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s public welfare contributions included founding hospitals, planting trees, and digging wells, but not constructing temples for Hindu gods."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which year is commonly associated with the end of Ashoka’s reign?",
                  "options": ["238 BCE", "273 BCE", "232 BCE", "250 BCE"],
                  "answer": "238 BCE",
                  "explanation": "The year 238 BCE is commonly associated with the end of Ashoka’s reign, following his death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Ashoka emphasize in his rock and pillar edicts?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Trade policies",
                    "Principles of dharma",
                    "Agricultural reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Principles of dharma",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s rock and pillar edicts emphasized the principles of dharma, including ethical conduct and public welfare."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which modern-day Indian state was historically known as Kalinga?",
                  "options": ["Odisha", "Bengal", "Assam", "Andhra Pradesh"],
                  "answer": "Odisha",
                  "explanation": "Kalinga is the historical region corresponding to present-day Odisha."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Ashoka’s 'dharma ministers' play?",
                  "options": [
                    "Collecting taxes",
                    "Maintaining military order",
                    "Promoting dharma and public welfare",
                    "Supervising trade routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoting dharma and public welfare",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s 'dharma ministers' were responsible for promoting dharma and ensuring public welfare across his empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s policy of 'conquest by dharma' was primarily aimed at:",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanding territories",
                    "Promoting economic growth",
                    "Serving his subjects and humanity",
                    "Establishing new trade routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Serving his subjects and humanity",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s policy of 'conquest by dharma' focused on the welfare and moral upliftment of his subjects rather than territorial expansion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Ashoka’s efforts to prevent cruelty to animals?",
                  "options": [
                    "Banning animal sacrifices",
                    "Setting up animal shelters",
                    "Prohibiting hunting",
                    "Creating wildlife reserves"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Banning animal sacrifices",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s efforts to prevent cruelty included banning animal sacrifices, reflecting his commitment to non-violence and compassion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s inscriptions can be found on:",
                  "options": [
                    "Temple walls",
                    "Ancient coins",
                    "Rocks and pillars",
                    "Buddhist manuscripts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rocks and pillars",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts are inscribed on rocks and pillars, which were placed across his empire to communicate his policies and moral principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka sent his own children to which country as missionaries?",
                  "options": ["Nepal", "Sri Lanka", "China", "Myanmar"],
                  "answer": "Sri Lanka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka sent his children to Sri Lanka to spread Buddhism and promote its teachings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which specific aspect of Ashoka’s rule did his inscriptions highlight?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military strategies",
                    "Agricultural advancements",
                    "Religious and moral principles",
                    "Trade policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious and moral principles",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s inscriptions primarily emphasized his commitment to religious and moral principles, especially his promotion of Buddhism and dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism was influenced by:",
                  "options": [
                    "A spiritual vision",
                    "The suffering caused by war",
                    "A royal decree",
                    "An alliance with Buddhist leaders"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The suffering caused by war",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism was deeply influenced by the suffering and destruction caused by the Kalinga War, leading him to embrace non-violence and compassion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Lion Capital of Ashoka originally topped a pillar in which location?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Sarnath", "Patna", "Ujjain"],
                  "answer": "Sarnath",
                  "explanation": "The Lion Capital of Ashoka was originally placed on a pillar in Sarnath, where the Buddha is said to have given his first sermon."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s edicts were written in which language?",
                  "options": ["Sanskrit", "Pali", "Prakrit", "Tamil"],
                  "answer": "Prakrit",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts were primarily written in Prakrit, a language used for administrative purposes during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s reforms was aimed at improving the quality of life for common people?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing universities",
                    "Building roads",
                    "Creating educational institutions",
                    "Founding hospitals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Founding hospitals",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s reforms included founding hospitals to improve healthcare and the quality of life for his subjects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s reign was characterized by his emphasis on:",
                  "options": [
                    "Conquest and military expansion",
                    "Trade and commerce",
                    "Peace and moral governance",
                    "Artistic and cultural achievements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Peace and moral governance",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s reign is noted for its emphasis on peace and moral governance, focusing on ethical conduct and the promotion of Buddhism."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical figure's edicts are considered an early example of imperial self-representation in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Akbar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's edicts are some of the earliest examples of imperial self-representation in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant role did Ashoka play in the spread of Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Patron and promoter",
                    "Military conqueror",
                    "Royal architect",
                    "Economic reformer"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patron and promoter",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was a key patron and promoter of Buddhism, supporting its spread throughout Asia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which tradition emphasizes Ashoka's dispatch of missionaries to Sri Lanka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Sri Lankan Tradition",
                    "North Indian Tradition",
                    "Chinese Tradition",
                    "Burmese Tradition"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sri Lankan Tradition",
                  "explanation": "The Sri Lankan Tradition highlights Ashoka's role in sending missionaries to Sri Lanka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text describes Ashoka’s efforts to collect a relic of Buddha from Ramagrama?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashokavadana",
                    "Mahavamsa",
                    "Dipavamsa",
                    "Jataka Tales"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashokavadana",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana describes Ashoka's efforts and challenges in collecting a relic of Buddha from Ramagrama."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription is debated to potentially include Ashoka's title 'Priyadarshi'?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Sirkap Inscription",
                    "The Junagadh Rock Inscription",
                    "The Sohgaura Copper Plate Inscription",
                    "The Mahasthan Inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Sirkap Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Sirkap Inscription is debated to possibly include the title 'Priyadarshi', attributed to Ashoka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In Ashoka's inscriptions, which major theme is emphasized?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dhamma",
                    "Military victories",
                    "Royal lineage",
                    "Economic prosperity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dhamma",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's inscriptions primarily emphasize 'dhamma' or righteous conduct."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following inscriptions is considered a significant source for understanding Ashoka’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Major Rock Edict",
                    "The Ashoka Pillar",
                    "The Aramaic Inscription",
                    "The Gupta Edict"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Major Rock Edict",
                  "explanation": "The Major Rock Edict is a significant source for understanding Ashoka’s reign and policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of Ashoka's edicts according to modern scholars?",
                  "options": [
                    "Political propaganda",
                    "Historical record",
                    "Religious instruction",
                    "Economic data"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Political propaganda",
                  "explanation": "Modern scholars view Ashoka’s edicts as political propaganda aimed at presenting a favorable image of his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text from the North Indian tradition does not mention Ashoka’s role in convening the Third Buddhist Council?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashokavadana",
                    "Mahavamsa",
                    "Divyavadana",
                    "A-yü wang chuan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashokavadana",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana, from the North Indian tradition, does not mention Ashoka’s role in the Third Buddhist Council."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical artifact's emblem is adapted into the modern Republic of India's national symbol?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Lion Capital of Ashoka",
                    "The Ashoka Chakra",
                    "The Pillar of Ashoka",
                    "The Stupa of Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Lion Capital of Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "The Lion Capital of Ashoka is adapted into the emblem of the modern Republic of India."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What major battle led to Ashoka's transformation and adoption of Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Kalinga",
                    "Battle of Pataliputra",
                    "Battle of Ujjain",
                    "Battle of Taxila"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kalinga",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Kalinga was pivotal for Ashoka’s transformation. The immense suffering and loss of life during this battle led him to embrace Buddhism and commit to non-violence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which edict is known for stating Ashoka’s remorse over the suffering caused by his conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rock Edict XIII",
                    "Pillar Edict IV",
                    "Rock Edict I",
                    "Pillar Edict VI"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rock Edict XIII",
                  "explanation": "Rock Edict XIII is famous for Ashoka’s expression of remorse and reflection on the suffering caused by his conquests, marking a significant turn in his rule towards Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s reign marked the spread of Buddhism to which region outside India?",
                  "options": ["Tibet", "Sri Lanka", "Thailand", "Central Asia"],
                  "answer": "Sri Lanka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka sent his emissaries, including his children, to Sri Lanka, significantly contributing to the spread of Buddhism beyond the Indian subcontinent."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s policies aimed to ensure the well-being of both people and animals?",
                  "options": [
                    "Public welfare",
                    "Social justice",
                    "Environmental protection",
                    "Religious tolerance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public welfare",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s public welfare policies included various measures to ensure the well-being of people and animals, reflecting his commitment to non-violence and compassion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of Ashoka’s rock and pillar edicts?",
                  "options": [
                    "To commemorate military victories",
                    "To propagate his moral and religious principles",
                    "To announce trade agreements",
                    "To record administrative changes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To propagate his moral and religious principles",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s rock and pillar edicts were primarily used to communicate his moral and religious principles, especially his commitment to Buddhism and dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who were the ‘dharma ministers’ appointed by Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Advisors for trade",
                    "Officials for religious and moral guidance",
                    "Military commanders",
                    "Tax collectors"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Officials for religious and moral guidance",
                  "explanation": "Dharma ministers were appointed by Ashoka to promote and oversee his policies of dharma, focusing on moral and ethical guidance for the administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Ashoka establish to support his policy of nonviolence?",
                  "options": [
                    "War memorials",
                    "Animal hospitals",
                    "Military forts",
                    "Trade centers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Animal hospitals",
                  "explanation": "To support his policy of nonviolence, Ashoka established animal hospitals to care for injured and sick animals, reflecting his commitment to compassion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Indian state’s population was directly impacted by Ashoka’s Kalinga campaign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tamil Nadu",
                    "Andhra Pradesh",
                    "Odisha",
                    "West Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Odisha",
                  "explanation": "The Kalinga campaign, which had a profound impact on Ashoka’s policies, affected the region of present-day Odisha, where the battle took place."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important feature of Ashoka’s governance was aimed at improving justice?",
                  "options": [
                    "Creation of new laws",
                    "Establishment of dharma ministers",
                    "Expansion of military forces",
                    "Promotion of arts and culture"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of dharma ministers",
                  "explanation": "The establishment of dharma ministers was aimed at promoting justice and ethical governance, ensuring that Ashoka’s policies of dharma were implemented effectively."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the main goals of Ashoka’s public works projects?",
                  "options": [
                    "Enhancing military infrastructure",
                    "Improving trade routes",
                    "Promoting public welfare and infrastructure",
                    "Supporting religious institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoting public welfare and infrastructure",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s public works projects focused on promoting public welfare and improving infrastructure, including the construction of roads, hospitals, and other facilities to support his subjects."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical text provides details on Ashoka’s role in spreading Buddhism?",
                  "options": ["Mahavamsa", "Arthashastra", "Ramayana", "Vedas"],
                  "answer": "Mahavamsa",
                  "explanation": "The Mahavamsa, an ancient Sri Lankan chronicle, details Ashoka’s role in the spread of Buddhism, including his missionary activities and support for the religion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s policies promoted which form of governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Militaristic",
                    "Feudal",
                    "Moral and ethical",
                    "Authoritarian"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Moral and ethical",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s governance was characterized by a focus on moral and ethical principles, emphasizing nonviolence, compassion, and dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s edicts are known for their:",
                  "options": [
                    "Political decrees",
                    "Economic strategies",
                    "Ethical and religious teachings",
                    "Military achievements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ethical and religious teachings",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts primarily convey ethical and religious teachings, reflecting his commitment to Buddhism and moral governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What kind of messages did Ashoka’s edicts commonly convey?",
                  "options": [
                    "Trade regulations",
                    "Military orders",
                    "Principles of dharma",
                    "Tax laws"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Principles of dharma",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts commonly conveyed principles of dharma, focusing on ethical conduct and religious teachings as part of his governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was NOT a focus of Ashoka’s reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promotion of Buddhist practices",
                    "Construction of stupas and monasteries",
                    "Expansion of the Mauryan Empire’s territories",
                    "Relief of human and animal suffering"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of the Mauryan Empire’s territories",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s reforms focused on promoting Buddhist practices, constructing stupas and monasteries, and relieving suffering, rather than expanding the empire's territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What action did Ashoka take to support Buddhism internally within his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Building military fortifications",
                    "Founding new Buddhist schools",
                    "Eradicating non-Buddhist practices",
                    "Suppressing internal schisms in the Buddhist community"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Suppressing internal schisms in the Buddhist community",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka worked to support Buddhism by addressing internal schisms within the Buddhist community to maintain unity and strengthen the religion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka ensure his message of dharma reached a wide audience?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through oral announcements and inscriptions",
                    "By writing books and scriptures",
                    "Through public debates",
                    "By establishing Buddhist universities"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Through oral announcements and inscriptions",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka used oral announcements and inscriptions on rocks and pillars to disseminate his message of dharma to a broad audience across his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s policy of nonviolence was reflected in his:",
                  "options": [
                    "Military strategies",
                    "Social policies",
                    "Environmental regulations",
                    "Trade practices"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Social policies",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s policy of nonviolence was reflected in his social policies, which included promoting peace, compassion, and the welfare of his subjects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s efforts to relieve suffering included:",
                  "options": [
                    "Creating trade alliances",
                    "Establishing educational institutions",
                    "Building rest houses and watering sheds",
                    "Developing new farming techniques"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building rest houses and watering sheds",
                  "explanation": "To relieve suffering, Ashoka undertook public works such as building rest houses and watering sheds to aid travelers and support those in need."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What aspect of Ashoka’s rule became a model for subsequent rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Economic prosperity",
                    "Ethical and moral governance",
                    "Artistic achievements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ethical and moral governance",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s emphasis on ethical and moral governance, characterized by his commitment to dharma and nonviolence, set a precedent for future rulers."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka’s role in the Mauryan Dynasty before becoming emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Minister",
                    "General",
                    "Crown Prince",
                    "Ambassador"
                  ],
                  "answer": "General",
                  "explanation": "Before becoming emperor, Ashoka served as a general in the Mauryan Dynasty, which gave him experience in military affairs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s sons was involved in spreading Buddhism to Ceylon?",
                  "options": ["Tivala", "Kunala", "Mahinda", "Dasharatha"],
                  "answer": "Mahinda",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's son Mahinda played a key role in spreading Buddhism to Ceylon (modern-day Sri Lanka)."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the reason behind Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "His interest in philosophy",
                    "His remorse over the Kalinga War",
                    "His desire for power",
                    "His quest for immortality"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His remorse over the Kalinga War",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism was motivated by his deep remorse for the suffering caused by the Kalinga War."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Ashoka after his death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Mahinda",
                    "Samprati",
                    "Dasharatha Maurya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dasharatha Maurya",
                  "explanation": "After Ashoka's death, his son Dasharatha Maurya succeeded him as emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of the Kalinga War on Ashoka’s policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military aggression",
                    "Focus on trade expansion",
                    "Emphasis on dharma and non-violence",
                    "Strengthening of fortifications"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Emphasis on dharma and non-violence",
                  "explanation": "The Kalinga War led Ashoka to emphasize dharma and non-violence in his governance, reflecting his shift towards Buddhist principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which modern-day country did Ashoka’s son Mahinda spread Buddhism?",
                  "options": ["Nepal", "Bangladesh", "Sri Lanka", "Pakistan"],
                  "answer": "Sri Lanka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s son Mahinda is known for spreading Buddhism to Sri Lanka, where it took root and flourished."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription system did Ashoka use to spread his messages?",
                  "options": [
                    "Manuscripts",
                    "Rock edicts",
                    "Scrolls",
                    "Tablets"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rock edicts",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka used rock edicts to spread his messages, which were inscribed on rocks and pillars throughout his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the term 'Devanampriya Priyadarshi' mean?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Compassionate King",
                    "The King of Kings",
                    "The Beloved of the Gods",
                    "The Conqueror"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Beloved of the Gods",
                  "explanation": "The term 'Devanampriya Priyadarshi' translates to 'The Beloved of the Gods,' which Ashoka used to describe himself in his edicts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka’s approach towards his subjects after the Kalinga War?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased taxation",
                    "Expansion of the military",
                    "Welfare and social reforms",
                    "Isolation from other kingdoms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Welfare and social reforms",
                  "explanation": "Following the Kalinga War, Ashoka focused on welfare and social reforms, including efforts to improve the lives of his subjects and promote ethical governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka’s new name after his conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandashoka",
                    "Priyadasi",
                    "Dharmashoka",
                    "Asokavardhana"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Priyadasi",
                  "explanation": "After converting to Buddhism, Ashoka took the name 'Priyadasi,' which means 'one who is dear to the gods.'"
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription found at Sirkap is debated to potentially reference Ashoka's title?",
                  "options": [
                    "Priyadarshi Inscription",
                    "Junagadh Rock Edict",
                    "Sirkap Inscription",
                    "Mahasthan Inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sirkap Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Sirkap Inscription is debated to possibly reference Ashoka's title 'Priyadarshi'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How do the Ashokavadana and the Mahavamsa differ in their accounts of the Bodhi Tree’s destruction?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashokavadana: healed, Mahavamsa: destroyed",
                    "Mahavamsa: healed, Ashokavadana: destroyed",
                    "Both: destroyed then healed",
                    "Both: transplanted"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashokavadana: healed, Mahavamsa: destroyed",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana describes the Bodhi Tree being healed after destruction, while the Mahavamsa describes its permanent destruction."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What discrepancy exists between the North Indian and Sri Lankan traditions concerning Ashoka's descendants?",
                  "options": [
                    "North Indian: Kunala mentioned",
                    "Sri Lankan: Kunala mentioned",
                    "Both agree on descendants",
                    "Neither mentions descendants"
                  ],
                  "answer": "North Indian: Kunala mentioned",
                  "explanation": "The North Indian tradition includes Ashoka's son Kunala, while the Sri Lankan tradition does not mention him."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of these inscriptions includes edicts by both Ashoka and other rulers like Rudradaman I and Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Major Rock Edict at Junagadh",
                    "The Ashoka Pillar",
                    "The Sohgaura Copper Plate Inscription",
                    "The Sirkap Inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Major Rock Edict at Junagadh",
                  "explanation": "The Major Rock Edict at Junagadh contains inscriptions by Ashoka and other rulers like Rudradaman I and Skandagupta."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text narrates Ashoka's unsuccessful attempt to collect a relic from Ramagrama?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashokavadana",
                    "Mahavamsa",
                    "Dipavamsa",
                    "Vamsatthapakasini"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashokavadana",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana narrates Ashoka’s unsuccessful attempt to collect a relic from Ramagrama."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which foreign dignitary’s inscriptions are considered a contemporary reference to Ashoka's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diodorus",
                    "Pliny the Elder",
                    "Arrian",
                    "Strabo"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diodorus",
                  "explanation": "Diodorus, a Greek historian, provides contemporary references to Ashoka’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is one major difference between the Ashokavadana and the Dipavamsa regarding Ashoka's achievements?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashokavadana: relics, Dipavamsa: Third Council",
                    "Dipavamsa: military conquests, Ashokavadana: religious policies",
                    "Both describe similar achievements",
                    "Ashokavadana: diplomacy, Dipavamsa: economic reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashokavadana: relics, Dipavamsa: Third Council",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana focuses on Ashoka’s attempts to collect relics, whereas the Dipavamsa emphasizes his role in the Third Buddhist Council."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Ashoka play in the Third Buddhist Council according to the Sri Lankan tradition?",
                  "options": [
                    "Patron and convenor",
                    "Primary critic",
                    "Local mediator",
                    "Relic collector"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patron and convenor",
                  "explanation": "According to the Sri Lankan tradition, Ashoka played the role of a patron and convenor of the Third Buddhist Council."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following inscriptions includes texts in Aramaic, thought to possibly reference Ashoka’s title?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Sirkap Inscription",
                    "The Junagadh Rock Edict",
                    "The Sohgaura Copper Plate Inscription",
                    "The Mahasthan Inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Sirkap Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Sirkap Inscription includes texts in Aramaic that are thought to reference Ashoka’s title."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city founded by Seleucus Nicator became a significant cultural and economic center in the East?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                    "Antioch",
                    "Alexandria",
                    "Pergamum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                  "explanation": "Seleucia on the Tigris became a major cultural and economic center in the East, playing a pivotal role in the Seleucid Empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary motivation behind Ashoka’s transition to Buddhism after the Kalinga War?",
                  "options": [
                    "Witnessing the suffering from his conquest",
                    "A vision from a Buddhist monk",
                    "Pressure from his advisors",
                    "Unifying his empire under Buddhism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Witnessing the suffering from his conquest",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's shift to Buddhism was profoundly influenced by the suffering and devastation he observed following his conquest of Kalinga. This experience led him to embrace Buddhism and promote nonviolence and moral governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year of his reign did Ashoka reportedly conquer Kalinga?",
                  "options": [
                    "The 6th year",
                    "The 8th year",
                    "The 10th year",
                    "The 12th year"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The 8th year",
                  "explanation": "Historical records indicate that Ashoka's conquest of Kalinga occurred in the 8th year of his reign, a pivotal event that influenced his subsequent embrace of Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical source provides an account of Ashoka sending his own children as missionaries to Sri Lanka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahavamsa",
                    "Rajatarangini",
                    "Bhagavad Gita",
                    "Puranas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mahavamsa",
                  "explanation": "The Mahavamsa, an ancient chronicle of Sri Lanka, provides details about Ashoka sending his children as missionaries to Sri Lanka to propagate Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Ashoka’s edicts were primarily inscribed in which type of locations?",
                  "options": [
                    "Temples",
                    "Fortresses",
                    "Rocks and pillars",
                    "Palaces"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rocks and pillars",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts were inscribed on rocks and pillars across his empire, serving as a means to communicate his policies and principles to a wide audience."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka’s approach to governance change after the Kalinga War?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military campaigns",
                    "Focused on economic development",
                    "Adopted nonviolence and moral leadership",
                    "Centralized administrative control"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adopted nonviolence and moral leadership",
                  "explanation": "After the Kalinga War, Ashoka’s governance shifted to emphasize nonviolence and moral leadership. He prioritized compassion, ethical conduct, and dharma, moving away from military conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant shift in Buddhist practice did Ashoka influence through his support?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of new rituals",
                    "Establishment of monastic orders in India",
                    "Spread of Buddhism beyond India",
                    "Reformation of Buddhist texts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spread of Buddhism beyond India",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was instrumental in spreading Buddhism beyond India by supporting missionary activities and fostering connections with other regions, thus expanding its influence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What specific aspect of Ashoka’s edicts reflects his approach to inter-religious respect?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promotion of Buddhism",
                    "Encouragement of religious tolerance",
                    "Restriction to Buddhism only",
                    "Establishment of Buddhist temples"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Encouragement of religious tolerance",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts promoted religious tolerance and respect for all sects, reflecting his commitment to inter-religious harmony rather than exclusively promoting Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Buddhist practice did Ashoka not explicitly endorse in his edicts?",
                  "options": [
                    "Meditation",
                    "Monastic life",
                    "Ritualistic practices",
                    "Scriptural studies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ritualistic practices",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts focus on ethical conduct, meditation, monastic life, and scriptural studies, but do not explicitly endorse ritualistic practices."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka’s administration address the needs of women and marginalized communities?",
                  "options": [
                    "Special welfare programs",
                    "Appointment of dharma ministers",
                    "Educational institutions",
                    "Social reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Appointment of dharma ministers",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka addressed the needs of women and marginalized communities by appointing dharma ministers to promote welfare and provide moral guidance, ensuring their needs were met."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major consequence of Ashoka’s policy of nonviolence on his empire’s military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military expansion",
                    "Reduction of military expenditures",
                    "Strengthening of fortifications",
                    "Integration of military and dharma policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reduction of military expenditures",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s policy of nonviolence led to a reduction in military expenditures as he focused on promoting peace and dharma rather than continuing military conquests."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical source describes Ashoka's transformation after the Kalinga War?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Ashokavadana",
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Arthashastra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Ashokavadana",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana describes Ashoka's transformation and his subsequent embrace of Buddhism following the Kalinga War."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many years did Ashoka rule the Mauryan Empire?",
                  "options": ["25 years", "37 years", "45 years", "50 years"],
                  "answer": "37 years",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka ruled the Mauryan Empire for approximately 37 years, from around 268 to 232 BCE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka's sons was blinded and thus not considered a successor?",
                  "options": ["Mahinda", "Tivala", "Kunala", "Samprati"],
                  "answer": "Kunala",
                  "explanation": "Kunala, one of Ashoka's sons, was blinded and therefore not considered a viable successor to the throne."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major impact of the Kalinga War on Ashoka's policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expand empire further",
                    "Adopt non-violence and dharma",
                    "Seek alliances with neighbors",
                    "Increase taxation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Adopt non-violence and dharma",
                  "explanation": "The Kalinga War had a profound impact on Ashoka, leading him to abandon further military conquests and embrace a policy of non-violence. This shift was characterized by his dedication to spreading Buddhism and promoting moral and ethical governance through dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Ashoka's policy of non-violence on his military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "More frequent campaigns",
                    "Ceased conquests, spread Buddhism",
                    "Increased army size",
                    "New military alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ceased conquests, spread Buddhism",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's adoption of non-violence led him to cease military campaigns entirely. Instead of pursuing further conquests, he focused on spreading Buddhism and promoting peace throughout his empire, reflecting his commitment to ethical and non-violent principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary content of Ashoka's rock edicts?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military strategies",
                    "Religious teachings and moral instructions",
                    "Administrative orders",
                    "Personal biographies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious teachings and moral instructions",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's rock edicts primarily contain religious teachings and moral instructions aimed at promoting dharma and ethical behavior."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Ashoka belong to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Dynasty",
                    "Mauryan Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Mughal Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mauryan Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was a ruler of the Mauryan Dynasty, one of the major dynasties of ancient India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the Dharma Chakra in Ashoka's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "It represented his military conquests.",
                    "It symbolized his commitment to Buddhism and dharma.",
                    "It was used as a royal seal.",
                    "It was an emblem of his administrative reforms."
                  ],
                  "answer": "It symbolized his commitment to Buddhism and dharma.",
                  "explanation": "The Dharma Chakra, or Wheel of Dharma, symbolized Ashoka's commitment to Buddhism and his promotion of dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following actions was NOT part of Ashoka’s post-conversion reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishing hospitals",
                    "Promoting animal welfare",
                    "Enhancing military training",
                    "Encouraging the planting of trees"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Enhancing military training",
                  "explanation": "Enhancing military training was not part of Ashoka’s reforms after his conversion to Buddhism; instead, he focused on welfare, non-violence, and moral teachings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who were Ashoka's main advisors during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "His sons and military generals",
                    "His younger brother and trusted ministers",
                    "Foreign diplomats and scholars",
                    "Religious leaders and monks"
                  ],
                  "answer": "His younger brother and trusted ministers",
                  "explanation": "During his reign, Ashoka relied on his younger brother and trusted ministers as his main advisors."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Bindusara",
          "description": [
            "Bindusara was the second Mauryan emperor and the father of Ashoka.",
            "Bindusara was the second emperor of the Maurya Empire, ruling from around 297 to 273 BCE.",
            "Bindusara expanded the Maurya Empire to the southern parts of India, continuing the legacy of his father, Chandragupta Maurya.",
            "Bindusara maintained diplomatic relations with the Hellenistic world, particularly with the Seleucid Empire.",
            "During his reign, Bindusara consolidated the empire's control over central and southern India, except for the Tamil kingdoms.",
            "Bindusara was the father of Ashoka, who succeeded him as the Maurya emperor."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the second emperor of the Mauryan Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Chandragupta",
                    "Alexander"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bindusara",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was the second emperor of the Mauryan Empire, ascending the throne around 297 BCE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Greek name is used for Bindusara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Amitrochates",
                    "Megasthenes",
                    "Selucus",
                    "Pliny"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Amitrochates",
                  "explanation": "Greek sources referred to Bindusara as Amitrochates, meaning 'destroyer of foes'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Bindusara's father?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Alexander",
                    "Seleucus Nicator"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was the son of Chandragupta Maurya, the founder of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "When did Bindusara ascend the throne?",
                  "options": ["297 BCE", "321 BCE", "232 BCE", "305 BCE"],
                  "answer": "297 BCE",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara ascended the throne around 297 BCE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Bindusara belong to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mauryan Empire",
                    "Gupta Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mauryan Empire",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was a ruler of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Bindusara's campaign extended to which region in the south?",
                  "options": ["Karnataka", "Kerala", "Tamil Nadu", "Goa"],
                  "answer": "Karnataka",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara's military campaign extended to the region near modern-day Karnataka."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which southern kingdoms avoided Bindusara’s conquest?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cholas, Pandyas, Cheras",
                    "Satavahanas, Chalukyas",
                    "Guptas, Kalabhras",
                    "Pallavas, Kadambas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cholas, Pandyas, Cheras",
                  "explanation": "The southern kingdoms of Cholas, Pandyas, and Cheras had good relations with the Mauryas and were not conquered."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Bindusara known for in Greek sources?",
                  "options": [
                    "Destroyer of Foes",
                    "Protector of Allies",
                    "Conqueror of the West",
                    "Great Trader"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Destroyer of Foes",
                  "explanation": "Greek sources referred to Bindusara as Amitrochates, meaning 'destroyer of foes'."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for Bindusara stopping his campaign in the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Friendly relations with southern kingdoms",
                    "Lack of resources",
                    "Invading armies",
                    "Geographical challenges"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Friendly relations with southern kingdoms",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara stopped his campaign in the Deccan because the southern kingdoms like the Cholas had good relations with the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous emperor succeeded Bindusara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Chandragupta",
                    "Alexander",
                    "Seleucus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "After Bindusara’s death, his son Ashoka succeeded him as emperor."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the father of Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Kanishka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bindusara",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was the father of Ashoka and the second Mauryan emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Ashoka rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Empire",
                    "Mauryan Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mauryan Empire",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was a ruler of the Mauryan Empire, which was one of the largest empires in ancient India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major event led to Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ujjain",
                    "Battle of Kalinga",
                    "Battle of Magadha",
                    "Battle of Takshashila"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kalinga",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Kalinga, with its immense bloodshed, led Ashoka to embrace Buddhism and adopt a policy of non-violence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the Lion Capital of Ashoka?",
                  "options": ["A statue", "A pillar", "A coin", "A fort"],
                  "answer": "A pillar",
                  "explanation": "The Lion Capital is the capital of an Ashokan pillar and is a symbol of the Indian Republic."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What language were Ashoka's edicts primarily written in?",
                  "options": ["Greek", "Sanskrit", "Pali", "Tamil"],
                  "answer": "Pali",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's edicts were primarily written in Pali, which was used to communicate his policies and teachings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Ashoka as emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahinda",
                    "Sushima",
                    "Dasharatha Maurya",
                    "Samprati"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dasharatha Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Dasharatha Maurya, Ashoka's grandson, succeeded him as the emperor of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka's attitude towards animal sacrifice?",
                  "options": [
                    "He promoted it",
                    "He banned it",
                    "He ignored it",
                    "He used it for rituals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He banned it",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka banned animal sacrifice as part of his commitment to non-violence and his Buddhist principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title did Ashoka adopt after his conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka the Great",
                    "Ashoka the Benevolent",
                    "Ashoka the Just",
                    "Priyadasi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Priyadasi",
                  "explanation": "After his conversion to Buddhism, Ashoka adopted the title 'Priyadasi,' meaning 'one who regards others with affection.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which king sent an envoy to Ashoka's court during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Ptolemy Philadelphus",
                    "Antiochos I",
                    "Chandragupta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ptolemy Philadelphus",
                  "explanation": "Ptolemy Philadelphus, the Greek ruler of Egypt, sent an envoy to Ashoka's court to establish diplomatic relations."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka's primary method of promoting Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquest",
                    "Rock edicts and pillars",
                    "Construction of temples",
                    "Writing books"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rock edicts and pillars",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka primarily used rock edicts and pillars to promote Buddhism and spread his moral and religious teachings."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the father of Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Kanishka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bindusara",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was the father of Ashoka and the second Mauryan emperor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Ashoka rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gupta Empire",
                    "Mauryan Empire",
                    "Mughal Empire",
                    "Chola Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mauryan Empire",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was a ruler of the Mauryan Empire, which was one of the largest empires in ancient India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major event led to Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ujjain",
                    "Battle of Kalinga",
                    "Battle of Magadha",
                    "Battle of Takshashila"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kalinga",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Kalinga, with its immense bloodshed, led Ashoka to embrace Buddhism and adopt a policy of non-violence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the Lion Capital of Ashoka?",
                  "options": ["A statue", "A pillar", "A coin", "A fort"],
                  "answer": "A pillar",
                  "explanation": "The Lion Capital is the capital of an Ashokan pillar and is a symbol of the Indian Republic."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What language were Ashoka's edicts primarily written in?",
                  "options": ["Greek", "Sanskrit", "Pali", "Tamil"],
                  "answer": "Pali",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's edicts were primarily written in Pali, which was used to communicate his policies and teachings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Ashoka as emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahinda",
                    "Sushima",
                    "Dasharatha Maurya",
                    "Samprati"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dasharatha Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Dasharatha Maurya, Ashoka's grandson, succeeded him as the emperor of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka's attitude towards animal sacrifice?",
                  "options": [
                    "He promoted it",
                    "He banned it",
                    "He ignored it",
                    "He used it for rituals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He banned it",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka banned animal sacrifice as part of his commitment to non-violence and his Buddhist principles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title did Ashoka adopt after his conversion to Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka the Great",
                    "Ashoka the Benevolent",
                    "Ashoka the Just",
                    "Priyadasi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Priyadasi",
                  "explanation": "After his conversion to Buddhism, Ashoka adopted the title 'Priyadasi,' meaning 'one who regards others with affection.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which king sent an envoy to Ashoka's court during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Ptolemy Philadelphus",
                    "Antiochos I",
                    "Chandragupta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ptolemy Philadelphus",
                  "explanation": "Ptolemy Philadelphus, the Greek ruler of Egypt, sent an envoy to Ashoka's court to establish diplomatic relations."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka's primary method of promoting Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military conquest",
                    "Rock edicts and pillars",
                    "Construction of temples",
                    "Writing books"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rock edicts and pillars",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka primarily used rock edicts and pillars to promote Buddhism and spread his moral and religious teachings."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Seleucus Nicator a successor to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Julius Caesar",
                    "Augustus",
                    "Cyrus the Great"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alexander the Great",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator was a successor to Alexander the Great, ruling over the territories that were part of Alexander's vast empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire did Seleucus Nicator found?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ptolemaic Empire",
                    "Seleucid Empire",
                    "Roman Empire",
                    "Mauryan Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucid Empire",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator founded the Seleucid Empire, which was one of the Hellenistic states that emerged after Alexander the Great's empire was divided."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator was one of the successors of Alexander the Great, known as:",
                  "options": ["Satraps", "Diadochi", "Sultans", "Emperors"],
                  "answer": "Diadochi",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator was one of the Diadochi, the successors to Alexander the Great who fought for control of his empire after his death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s position in Alexander’s army during the campaign in Asia?",
                  "options": ["General", "Infantry Officer", "Page", "Admiral"],
                  "answer": "Infantry Officer",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator served as an Infantry Officer in Alexander the Great's army during the campaign in Asia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which battle did Seleucus play a significant role against King Porus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Granicus",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela",
                    "Battle of Hydaspes",
                    "Battle of Issus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Hydaspes",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator played a significant role in the Battle of Hydaspes, where Alexander the Great defeated King Porus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who did Seleucus Nicator marry after the marriage ceremony at Susa?",
                  "options": [
                    "A Persian princess",
                    "A Macedonian noblewoman",
                    "A Greek aristocrat",
                    "A Roman senator's daughter"
                  ],
                  "answer": "A Persian princess",
                  "explanation": "After the marriage ceremony at Susa, Seleucus Nicator married a Persian princess, part of the wider Macedonian and Persian integration strategy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus was initially appointed as the governor of which region?",
                  "options": ["Persia", "Babylon", "Egypt", "Greece"],
                  "answer": "Babylon",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator was initially appointed as the governor of Babylon, a key region in the eastern part of Alexander's former empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator fled to which country to escape Antigonus?",
                  "options": ["Egypt", "Rome", "Persia", "India"],
                  "answer": "Egypt",
                  "explanation": "To escape Antigonus, Seleucus Nicator fled to Egypt, seeking refuge under the protection of Ptolemy I Soter."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s return to Babylon marked the beginning of which empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Macedonian Empire",
                    "Seleucid Empire",
                    "Ptolemaic Empire",
                    "Roman Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucid Empire",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator’s return to Babylon marked the beginning of the Seleucid Empire, which he established and expanded."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle saw Seleucus and his allies defeat Antigonus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Granicus",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela",
                    "Battle of Corupedium"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ipsus",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Ipsus was a decisive confrontation in which Seleucus Nicator and his allies defeated Antigonus, solidifying Seleucus's control over his territories."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s capital city founded around 305-307 BCE was called:",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucia",
                    "Alexandria",
                    "Babylon",
                    "Persepolis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator founded the city of Seleucia around 305-307 BCE as his new capital, which became a major center of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s relationship with Chandragupta Maurya after their treaty?",
                  "options": ["Rivals", "Allies", "Enemies", "Neutral"],
                  "answer": "Allies",
                  "explanation": "After their treaty, Seleucus Nicator and Chandragupta Maurya became allies, establishing a diplomatic and political relationship."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the end of Antigonus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Corupedium",
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Hydaspes",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ipsus",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Ipsus, fought in 301 BCE, marked the end of Antigonus, with Seleucus Nicator playing a significant role in the coalition that defeated him."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator was assassinated near which location?",
                  "options": [
                    "Babylon",
                    "Lysimachia",
                    "Persepolis",
                    "Alexandria"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Lysimachia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator was assassinated near Lysimachia in 281 BCE, ending his reign and his role in the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s wife, Apama, was the daughter of which historical figure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alexander the Great",
                    "Darius III",
                    "Spitamenes",
                    "Antigonus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spitamenes",
                  "explanation": "Apama, Seleucus Nicator’s wife, was the daughter of Spitamenes, a notable Persian leader and contemporary of Alexander the Great."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Diadochi coalition did Seleucus join to fight against Antigonus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cassander, Ptolemy, and Lysimachus",
                    "Cassander, Ptolemy, and Demetrius",
                    "Lysimachus, Antigonus, and Ptolemy",
                    "Demetrius, Ptolemy, and Eumenes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cassander, Ptolemy, and Lysimachus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator joined the coalition of Cassander, Ptolemy, and Lysimachus to fight against Antigonus, leading to the crucial Battle of Ipsus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator's daughter Helena was married to which Indian ruler?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Alexander"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Helena, the daughter of Seleucus Nicator, was married to Chandragupta Maurya, linking the Seleucid and Mauryan empires through marriage."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Seleucus Nicator die?",
                  "options": ["305 BCE", "306 BCE", "281 BCE", "323 BCE"],
                  "answer": "281 BCE",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator died in 281 BCE, marking the end of his significant contributions to the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator was known for his role in which famous battle during his campaign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Hydaspes",
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Corupedium",
                    "Battle of Granicus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ipsus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator was notably involved in the Battle of Ipsus, which was a decisive battle that led to the downfall of Antigonus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Seleucus Nicator establish as his new capital?",
                  "options": ["Babylon", "Seleucia", "Susa", "Alexandria"],
                  "answer": "Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator established Seleucia as his new capital, which became an important center of his empire and administration."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Bindusara fail to conquer?",
                  "options": [
                    "Karnataka",
                    "Tamil Nadu",
                    "Kerala",
                    "Maharashtra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tamil Nadu",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara's campaign stopped short of Tamil Nadu, due to good relations with the southern kingdoms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the relationship between Bindusara and Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Father and Son",
                    "Brothers",
                    "Cousins",
                    "Uncle and Nephew"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Father and Son",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was Bindusara’s son."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which foreign empire did Bindusara maintain relations with?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Greeks",
                    "The Chinese",
                    "The Romans",
                    "The Persians"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Greeks",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara and the Mauryan Empire maintained relations with the Greeks."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title did Bindusara hold in Greek records?",
                  "options": ["Amitrochates", "Soter", "Megas", "Basileus"],
                  "answer": "Amitrochates",
                  "explanation": "The Greek records referred to Bindusara as Amitrochates."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Bindusara's rule extended across which parts of India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Northern and parts of Southern India",
                    "Eastern India",
                    "Western India",
                    "Entire Indian subcontinent"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northern and parts of Southern India",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara extended the Mauryan Empire across northern and parts of southern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Mauryan text was composed during Bindusara's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Arthashastra",
                    "Vedas",
                    "Ramayana",
                    "Mahabharata"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Arthashastra",
                  "explanation": "The Arthashastra, a text on political economy, was composed during the Mauryan period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous traveler visited the Mauryan court during Bindusara's time?",
                  "options": [
                    "Megasthenes",
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Xuanzang",
                    "Ibn Battuta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Megasthenes",
                  "explanation": "Megasthenes, a Greek traveler, visited the Mauryan court during Bindusara's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Bindusara's campaigns primarily focused on which region?",
                  "options": ["Deccan", "Northwest", "Bengal", "Indus Valley"],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara focused on extending his campaigns into the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How long did Bindusara rule the Mauryan Empire?",
                  "options": ["25 years", "40 years", "50 years", "30 years"],
                  "answer": "25 years",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara ruled the Mauryan Empire for about 25 years."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Bindusara's sons succeeded him after a war of succession?",
                  "options": ["Ashoka", "Sumana", "Kunala", "Vitashoka"],
                  "answer": "Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka emerged victorious in the war of succession and succeeded Bindusara."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s actions was aimed at spreading Buddhism across the empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Building new forts",
                    "Sending missionaries and building stupas",
                    "Engaging in more conquests",
                    "Establishing a new capital"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sending missionaries and building stupas",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka sent missionaries and built stupas to spread Buddhism and its teachings across his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did the Greek ambassador Deimachus do during Bindusara’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "He established trade routes",
                    "He reported on the Mauryan Empire to Greece",
                    "He negotiated a peace treaty",
                    "He set up a Greek colony in India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He reported on the Mauryan Empire to Greece",
                  "explanation": "Deimachus reported on the Mauryan Empire, providing valuable insights into its structure and culture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main goal of the Buddhist missions sent by Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "To conquer new territories",
                    "To spread Buddhism and dharma",
                    "To establish diplomatic relations",
                    "To trade with neighboring states"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To spread Buddhism and dharma",
                  "explanation": "The primary goal of the Buddhist missions was to spread the teachings of Buddhism and dharma across different regions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Ashoka’s significant contributions to public welfare?",
                  "options": [
                    "Building a network of roads",
                    "Establishing hospitals and medicinal plants",
                    "Expanding military infrastructure",
                    "Founding educational institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishing hospitals and medicinal plants",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka established hospitals and promoted the use of medicinal plants as part of his commitment to public welfare."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of Khallataka during Ashoka’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military commander",
                    "Royal advisor and supporter of Ashoka’s claim to the throne",
                    "Foreign diplomat",
                    "Chief architect"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Royal advisor and supporter of Ashoka’s claim to the throne",
                  "explanation": "Khallataka was a key royal advisor who supported Ashoka's claim to the throne."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text describes the story of Ashoka’s rise to power after his father’s death?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Ashokavadana",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Arthashastra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Ashokavadana",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana is a text that describes Ashoka's rise to power and his conversion to Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka manage to secure the throne despite his father’s wish for Sushima?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through military force",
                    "Winning royal councillors' support",
                    "Negotiating with kingdoms",
                    "Becoming a religious leader"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Winning royal councillors' support",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka was able to secure the throne by gaining the support of the royal councillors, which allowed him to ascend to power despite his father’s preference for his brother Sushima."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Ashoka’s edicts on Indian society?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military conquests",
                    "Promoted religious tolerance and moral conduct",
                    "Expanded trade routes",
                    "Established new administrative policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoted religious tolerance and moral conduct",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s edicts had a significant impact on Indian society by promoting religious tolerance and moral conduct. These edicts reflected his commitment to Buddhism and dharma, fostering a more inclusive and ethical society."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which empire was known to have had diplomatic relations with Ashoka’s Mauryan Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Roman Empire",
                    "Achaemenid Empire",
                    "Ptolemaic Egypt",
                    "Byzantine Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ptolemaic Egypt",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s Mauryan Empire established diplomatic relations with Ptolemaic Egypt. This relationship is evidenced by the exchange of envoys and correspondence between the two empires."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka’s policy towards the Brahmins and other non-Buddhist sects?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expelled them",
                    "Persecuted them",
                    "Respected and engaged while promoting Buddhism",
                    "Replaced them with Buddhist monks"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Respected and engaged while promoting Buddhism",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka adopted a policy of respect and engagement towards Brahmins and other non-Buddhist sects, while promoting Buddhism. He did not seek to exclude or replace them but rather integrated them into his broader vision of ethical governance."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which region was NOT part of the Mauryan Empire during Bindusara’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "The Mysore region",
                    "Northern India",
                    "The Himalayan region"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Himalayan region",
                  "explanation": "The Himalayan region was not part of the Mauryan Empire during Bindusara’s reign, which primarily covered regions like the Deccan Plateau, Mysore, and Northern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Ashoka’s approach to governance after the Kalinga War?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aggressive expansion",
                    "Consolidation and administrative reform",
                    "Increased taxation",
                    "Isolationism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidation and administrative reform",
                  "explanation": "After the Kalinga War, Ashoka focused on consolidating his empire and implementing administrative reforms, reflecting his commitment to non-violence and dharma."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant battle marked a turning point in Ashoka’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Takshashila",
                    "Battle of Kalinga",
                    "Battle of Ujjain",
                    "Battle of Patliputra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Kalinga",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Kalinga was a significant turning point in Ashoka’s reign, leading to his conversion to Buddhism and a focus on non-violence."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of the Ajivika astrologer in Ashoka’s succession?",
                  "options": [
                    "He predicted Ashoka’s future greatness",
                    "He opposed Ashoka’s rise",
                    "He advised Sushima against Ashoka",
                    "He conducted rituals for Sushima"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He predicted Ashoka’s future greatness",
                  "explanation": "The Ajivika astrologer predicted Ashoka’s future greatness, which was a significant factor in his eventual rise to power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Greek ambassador succeeded Megasthenes at Bindusara’s court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Dionysis",
                    "Deimachus",
                    "Jambulus",
                    "Polycleitus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deimachus",
                  "explanation": "Deimachus succeeded Megasthenes as the Greek ambassador at Bindusara’s court, providing further insights into the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the reasons for the decline in historical records about Bindusara?",
                  "options": [
                    "Limited historical interest",
                    "Destruction of records",
                    "Loss of primary sources",
                    "Invasion of the Mauryan Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Limited historical interest",
                  "explanation": "The decline in historical records about Bindusara is mainly due to limited historical interest and the focus of historical accounts on more prominent rulers, such as Ashoka, who had a more significant impact on history."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major achievement of Ashoka’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of new trade routes",
                    "Conversion to Buddhism and promotion of dharma",
                    "Conquest of new territories",
                    "Creation of new administrative divisions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Conversion to Buddhism and promotion of dharma",
                  "explanation": "A major achievement of Ashoka’s reign was his conversion to Buddhism and his subsequent promotion of dharma. This shift in policy had a profound effect on his governance and the cultural landscape of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s sons was sent to spread Buddhism to Sri Lanka?",
                  "options": ["Kunala", "Vijaya", "Mahinda", "Tivala"],
                  "answer": "Mahinda",
                  "explanation": "Mahinda, one of Ashoka’s sons, was sent to Sri Lanka to spread Buddhism, helping to establish Buddhism in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Ashoka do to improve the welfare of his subjects?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military spending",
                    "Built hospitals and rest houses",
                    "Expanded the empire’s borders",
                    "Reduced taxes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Built hospitals and rest houses",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka focused on improving the welfare of his subjects by building hospitals and rest houses, reflecting his commitment to public welfare."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka address conflicts and issues within his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through military force",
                    "By employing diplomatic and administrative measures",
                    "By isolating rebellious regions",
                    "By appointing new governors"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By employing diplomatic and administrative measures",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka addressed conflicts and issues within his empire through diplomatic and administrative measures, rather than relying solely on military force."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s role in the Battle of Hydaspes?",
                  "options": [
                    "He led the Macedonian cavalry",
                    "He commanded the Macedonian infantry",
                    "He directed the siege operations",
                    "He was an observer"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He led the Macedonian cavalry",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator played a crucial role in the Battle of Hydaspes by leading the Macedonian cavalry under Alexander the Great's command."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant event occurred in 323 BCE involving Seleucus Nicator?",
                  "options": [
                    "He was appointed as the governor of Babylon",
                    "Alexander the Great died",
                    "He married Apama",
                    "He fought against Demetrius"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alexander the Great died",
                  "explanation": "In 323 BCE, the significant event involving Seleucus Nicator was the death of Alexander the Great, which led to the subsequent power struggles among his successors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which province was Seleucus assigned after the Partition of Babylon?",
                  "options": ["Egypt", "Asia Minor", "Babylon", "Persia"],
                  "answer": "Babylon",
                  "explanation": "After the Partition of Babylon, Seleucus Nicator was assigned the province of Babylon, which was a key region in his future empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Seleucus Nicator’s main rival during the Babylonian War?",
                  "options": ["Antigonus", "Demetrius", "Ptolemy", "Cassander"],
                  "answer": "Antigonus",
                  "explanation": "During the Babylonian War, Seleucus Nicator's main rival was Antigonus, who was one of the major Diadochi and posed a significant challenge to Seleucus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant battle did Seleucus Nicator participate in, which led to the downfall of Antigonus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela",
                    "Battle of Corupedium",
                    "Battle of Hydaspes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ipsus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator participated in the Battle of Ipsus, which was decisive in the downfall of Antigonus and reshaped the power dynamics among the Diadochi."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What was the nature of the treaty between Seleucus Nicator and Chandragupta Maurya?",
                  "options": [
                    "Trade agreement",
                    "Military alliance",
                    "Matrimonial alliance",
                    "Territorial division"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Matrimonial alliance",
                  "explanation": "The treaty between Seleucus Nicator and Chandragupta Maurya was a matrimonial alliance, which also included other terms like territorial concessions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Seleucus Nicator transfer the mint to, making it a significant administrative center?",
                  "options": [
                    "Babylon",
                    "Seleucia",
                    "Alexandria",
                    "Persepolis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator transferred the mint to Seleucia, which he established as a major administrative center in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the political situation in the Macedonian empire after Alexander’s death that affected Seleucus Nicator?",
                  "options": [
                    "Stable and unified",
                    "Fragmented and in conflict",
                    "Completely annexed by the Romans",
                    "Peaceful with no major disputes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fragmented and in conflict",
                  "explanation": "After Alexander the Great’s death, the Macedonian empire was fragmented and embroiled in conflicts among his successors, which significantly affected Seleucus Nicator's political maneuvers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main outcome of the Seleucid-Mauryan war?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucus lost control of eastern territories",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya retained the Indus Valley",
                    "Seleucus fled back to Macedonia",
                    "Chandragupta was overthrown"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya retained the Indus Valley",
                  "explanation": "The main outcome of the Seleucid-Mauryan war was that Chandragupta Maurya retained control of the Indus Valley. The war resulted in Seleucus Nicator securing a treaty with Chandragupta, which included territorial concessions but allowed Chandragupta to maintain control of the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Seleucus Nicator manage to return to Babylon in 311 BCE?",
                  "options": [
                    "With a large army from Macedonia",
                    "With support from Ptolemy and 50 loyal friends",
                    "By negotiating peace with Antigonus",
                    "By diplomatic means only"
                  ],
                  "answer": "With support from Ptolemy and 50 loyal friends",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator managed to return to Babylon in 311 BCE with the crucial support of Ptolemy and a small group of 50 loyal friends. This support was instrumental in his efforts to reclaim his position after a period of exile and conflict."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which city was Seleucus Nicator's capital before he founded Seleucia?",
                  "options": ["Persepolis", "Susa", "Babylon", "Damascus"],
                  "answer": "Babylon",
                  "explanation": "Before founding Seleucia, Seleucus Nicator's capital was Babylon, which was a significant city in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major impact of Seleucus Nicator's reign on the region of Mesopotamia?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decline in trade",
                    "Economic prosperity and urban development",
                    "Increased military conflicts",
                    "Decreased cultural influence"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Economic prosperity and urban development",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's reign brought economic prosperity and significant urban development to the region of Mesopotamia."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator established which strategic city along the Tigris River?",
                  "options": ["Seleucia", "Antioch", "Alexandria", "Babylon"],
                  "answer": "Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator established Seleucia along the Tigris River, making it a key strategic and administrative city."
                },

                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s governance saw the establishment of which important trade route?",
                  "options": [
                    "Silk Road",
                    "Incense Route",
                    "Royal Road",
                    "Via Egnatia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Incense Route",
                  "explanation": "Under Seleucus Nicator, the Incense Route became an important trade route that facilitated commerce and cultural exchange."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator's diplomatic relations with which Indian ruler were notably significant?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Bindusara",
                    "Alexander"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's diplomatic relations with Chandragupta Maurya were significant, including a treaty that involved a matrimonial alliance and territorial concessions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major battle did Seleucus Nicator lose before gaining control over Babylon?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela",
                    "Battle of Corupedium",
                    "Battle of Hydaspes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Corupedium",
                  "explanation": "Before gaining control over Babylon, Seleucus Nicator lost the Battle of Corupedium against Lysimachus, which was a significant setback in his early career."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s role in the formation of the Hellenistic world?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanded Greek culture in the East",
                    "Isolated himself from Greek culture",
                    "Focused solely on military conquests",
                    "Supported Roman expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expanded Greek culture in the East",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator significantly contributed to the formation of the Hellenistic world by spreading Greek culture and influence throughout the Eastern territories. His empire facilitated the exchange of ideas and traditions between Greek and local cultures, shaping the Hellenistic period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s ultimate legacy in the context of Hellenistic history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Unification of Greek states",
                    "Establishment of a vast empire that spread Greek culture",
                    "Collapse of Greek influence in Asia",
                    "A brief and unstable reign"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of a vast empire that spread Greek culture",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's ultimate legacy was the establishment of a vast empire that significantly contributed to the spread of Greek culture throughout Asia. His rule helped to consolidate Hellenistic influences across a large and diverse region, impacting the cultural and political landscape of the time."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s efforts in which field significantly shaped his empire's success?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military strategy",
                    "Diplomacy and alliances",
                    "Religious reforms",
                    "Naval power"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diplomacy and alliances",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's success was significantly shaped by his efforts in diplomacy and forming strategic alliances, which helped stabilize and expand his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant city did Seleucus Nicator found as a center of Hellenistic culture in the East?",
                  "options": ["Antioch", "Seleucia", "Pergamum", "Alexandria"],
                  "answer": "Seleucia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucia was founded by Seleucus Nicator as a major center of Hellenistic culture and administration in the East."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 11,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of these southern dynasties did Bindusara have good relations with?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cholas, Pandyas, Cheras",
                    "Satavahanas, Chalukyas",
                    "Guptas, Kalabhras",
                    "Rashtrakutas, Hoysalas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cholas, Pandyas, Cheras",
                  "explanation": "The Cholas, Pandyas, and Cheras had good relations with the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the cause of the war of succession after Bindusara’s death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Disputes among his sons",
                    "External invasion",
                    "Rebellion in southern provinces",
                    "Economic collapse"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Disputes among his sons",
                  "explanation": "After Bindusara’s death, a war of succession broke out among his sons."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Bindusara’s policy towards the southern kingdoms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diplomatic relations",
                    "Military conquest",
                    "Economic blockade",
                    "Naval warfare"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diplomatic relations",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara maintained diplomatic relations with southern kingdoms like the Cholas, Pandyas, and Cheras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major focus of Bindusara's foreign policy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanding into Southeast Asia",
                    "Maintaining diplomatic relations with the Greek states",
                    "Consolidating the empire’s territories",
                    "Establishing trade routes with China"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Maintaining diplomatic relations with the Greek states",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara focused on maintaining diplomatic relations with Greek states and other foreign entities, aiming to secure alliances and trade connections."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What role did Greek ambassadors play during Bindusara's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maintained diplomatic ties",
                    "Led military campaigns",
                    "Established trade routes",
                    "Conquered new territories"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Maintained diplomatic ties",
                  "explanation": "Greek ambassadors like Megasthenes maintained diplomatic ties with the Mauryan Empire during Bindusara's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Bindusara's sons became famous for his rule?",
                  "options": ["Ashoka", "Kunala", "Vitashoka", "Sushima"],
                  "answer": "Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka, Bindusara's son, became famous for his rule and the spread of Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Bindusara's reign contribute to the spread of Buddhism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Indirectly through Ashoka",
                    "He was a Buddhist",
                    "He funded Buddhist monasteries",
                    "He sent emissaries abroad"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Indirectly through Ashoka",
                  "explanation": "Although Bindusara was not a Buddhist, his reign set the stage for Ashoka, who later spread Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region remained autonomous during Bindusara's rule?",
                  "options": ["Tamil Nadu", "Kashmir", "Punjab", "Bihar"],
                  "answer": "Tamil Nadu",
                  "explanation": "Tamil Nadu remained largely autonomous during Bindusara's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which philosophy influenced Bindusara's rule?",
                  "options": ["Ajivika", "Buddhism", "Hinduism", "Jainism"],
                  "answer": "Ajivika",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara was influenced by the Ajivika philosophy, a sect that predated Buddhism."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Bindusara maintain control over the vast Mauryan Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Appointing governors",
                    "Centralized rule",
                    "Constant military campaigns",
                    "Spies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Appointing governors",
                  "explanation": "Bindusara, like his father, maintained control by appointing governors in different regions of the empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 12,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of the Edicts of Ashoka?",
                  "options": [
                    "Document royal decrees",
                    "Promote Buddhism and moral governance",
                    "Record military achievements",
                    "Establish trade regulations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promote Buddhism and moral governance",
                  "explanation": "The Edicts of Ashoka primarily aimed to promote Buddhism and moral governance. They were used to communicate his commitment to these ideals and to guide his subjects in ethical conduct."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient Greek historian wrote about Ashoka’s empire and its administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Herodotus",
                    "Diodorus Siculus",
                    "Arrian",
                    "Strabo"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Diodorus Siculus",
                  "explanation": "Diodorus Siculus, an ancient Greek historian, documented Ashoka’s empire and its administration, providing historical insights into the Mauryan Empire's organization and governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Ashoka’s conversion on his foreign policy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military aggression",
                    "Shift towards diplomacy and peaceful relations",
                    "Isolation from international affairs",
                    "Aggressive expansion into neighboring territories"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shift towards diplomacy and peaceful relations",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s conversion to Buddhism significantly impacted his foreign policy by leading to a shift towards diplomacy and peaceful relations, as opposed to previous aggressive military tactics."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following is NOT true about Ashoka’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maintained a network of spies",
                    "Reduced military commanders' roles",
                    "Focused on welfare",
                    "Centralized administration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reduced military commanders' roles",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s administration did not reduce the role of military commanders. Instead, he maintained a network of spies for surveillance and intelligence, focused on improving welfare and moral instruction, and centralized control to streamline governance. Military commanders continued to play a role in his administration, which was crucial for managing the vast Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the significance of the Edicts of Ashoka in the context of Indian history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Early diplomacy",
                    "Use of Sanskrit",
                    "Social justice and tolerance",
                    "Trade regulations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Social justice and tolerance",
                  "explanation": "The Edicts of Ashoka are significant as they provide a window into Ashoka’s principles of social justice and religious tolerance. They reflect his commitment to spreading Buddhism and promoting ethical governance. These edicts highlight his efforts to create a more humane and inclusive society, showing a shift from military conquest to moral and spiritual leadership."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did the Ashokavadana describe Ashoka’s rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military campaigns",
                    "Support of key ministers",
                    "Diplomatic efforts",
                    "Political conspiracy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Support of key ministers",
                  "explanation": "The Ashokavadana describes Ashoka’s rise to power as largely a result of gaining the support of influential ministers and royal councillors. This political maneuvering was crucial for establishing his rule over the Mauryan Empire, rather than relying solely on military conquests or political intrigue. This support helped him consolidate power and implement his policies effectively."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Chanakya play during Bindusara’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chief military strategist",
                    "Diplomatic envoy",
                    "Prime Minister and advisor",
                    "Religious leader"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Prime Minister and advisor",
                  "explanation": "Chanakya served as Prime Minister and advisor during Bindusara’s reign, playing a crucial role in the administration and strategic governance of the Mauryan Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of the Ajivika sect in the Mauryan court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Opponents of Ashoka",
                    "Providers of prophecies",
                    "Military advisors",
                    "Diplomatic negotiators"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Providers of prophecies",
                  "explanation": "The Ajivika sect was known for providing prophecies and astrological advice at the Mauryan court. Their role was significant in influencing decision-making and governance, as they were consulted for their interpretations of omens and predictions, rather than being involved in military or diplomatic matters."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a primary focus of Ashoka’s edicts in South India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Trade agreements",
                    "Buddhism and moral behavior",
                    "Military victories",
                    "Architectural projects"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Buddhism and moral behavior",
                  "explanation": "In South India, Ashoka’s edicts were primarily focused on promoting Buddhism and encouraging moral behavior. These edicts were designed to spread Buddhist teachings and foster ethical conduct among his subjects, emphasizing his commitment to these principles over other aspects such as trade or military achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical text provides a detailed account of Ashoka’s efforts to spread Buddhism beyond India?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mahabharata",
                    "The Dipavamsa",
                    "The Ramayana",
                    "The Arthashastra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Dipavamsa",
                  "explanation": "The Dipavamsa offers a detailed account of Ashoka’s efforts to spread Buddhism beyond India, documenting his extensive missionary activities and influence on the Buddhist expansion."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 13,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What evidence suggests Ashoka’s interest in diplomatic relations with the Hellenistic world?",
                  "options": [
                    "Correspondence with Greek philosophers",
                    "Greek ambassadors at his court",
                    "Establishment of Greek-style cities",
                    "Military alliances with Greek states"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Greek ambassadors at his court",
                  "explanation": "The presence of Greek ambassadors at Ashoka’s court is evidence of his interest in establishing diplomatic relations with the Hellenistic world. These interactions indicate a mutual interest in fostering diplomatic and cultural exchanges between the Mauryan Empire and Hellenistic states."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were some of the reforms introduced by Ashoka to promote welfare and justice in his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of bureaucracy",
                    "Establishment of rest houses, hospitals, and schools",
                    "Introduction of a new currency",
                    "Development of trade networks"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of rest houses, hospitals, and schools",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s reforms aimed at promoting welfare and justice included the establishment of rest houses for travelers, hospitals for the sick, and educational institutions. These measures were part of his broader efforts to enhance the quality of life and support moral and ethical values within his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka’s policies affect the Indian subcontinent’s cultural landscape?",
                  "options": [
                    "Spread of Buddhism and non-violence",
                    "Enforcement of a single religious practice",
                    "Revival of Vedic traditions",
                    "Isolation from foreign influences"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spread of Buddhism and non-violence",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s policies had a profound impact on the cultural landscape of the Indian subcontinent by promoting Buddhism and fostering a culture of non-violence. His support for Buddhism led to its widespread acceptance and influenced cultural and ethical practices throughout the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the Edicts of Ashoka in terms of administrative transparency?",
                  "options": [
                    "Detailed military records",
                    "Public outline of policies and morals",
                    "Trade regulations",
                    "Genealogies of rulers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public outline of policies and morals",
                  "explanation": "The Edicts of Ashoka are significant for their role in administrative transparency. They publicly outlined Ashoka’s policies and moral principles, making them accessible to the general populace and promoting an understanding of his governance and ethical standards."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Ashoka’s reign on the Indian subcontinent’s foreign relations?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased military conflicts",
                    "Fostered diplomatic relations and peaceful coexistence",
                    "Isolation from diplomacy",
                    "Prompted foreign invasions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fostered diplomatic relations and peaceful coexistence",
                  "explanation": "During Ashoka’s reign, the Indian subcontinent experienced improved foreign relations, characterized by diplomatic engagements and peaceful coexistence with other kingdoms. Ashoka’s commitment to non-violence and diplomacy helped to stabilize and enhance interactions with neighboring regions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Ashoka’s edicts is considered the most famous for its detailed account of his policy and beliefs?",
                  "options": [
                    "Major Rock Edict",
                    "Minor Pillar Edict",
                    "Kalinga Edict",
                    "Girnar Edict"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Major Rock Edict",
                  "explanation": "The Major Rock Edict is renowned for its comprehensive account of Ashoka’s policies and beliefs. It provides detailed insights into his administrative principles, moral values, and the promotion of Buddhism, making it a key source for understanding his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the nature of the relationship between Ashoka and his predecessors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expanded on their policies",
                    "Rejected their policies",
                    "Focused on military expansion",
                    "Isolated from the political structure"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expanded on their policies",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s relationship with his predecessors involved continuing and expanding upon their policies, particularly in the areas of administrative reforms and welfare initiatives. He built on the foundations laid by his predecessors to enhance governance and societal well-being."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did the royal counsellors play in Ashoka’s rise to power according to the Ashokavadana?",
                  "options": [
                    "Supported Sushima",
                    "Supported Ashoka’s claim",
                    "Opposed Ashoka",
                    "Played no significant role"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Supported Ashoka’s claim",
                  "explanation": "According to the Ashokavadana, the royal counsellors played a crucial role in supporting Ashoka’s claim to the throne. Their support was instrumental in securing Ashoka’s position as ruler, highlighting the importance of political backing in his ascension."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the story of Bindusara’s birth reveal about historical methods and reliability of sources?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mythological nature of ancient texts",
                    "Concrete historical evidence",
                    "Accuracy of Jain and Buddhist texts",
                    "Consistency in ancient records"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mythological nature of ancient texts",
                  "explanation": "The story of Bindusara’s birth illustrates the mythological nature of ancient texts and their influence on historical narratives. It demonstrates how historical accounts can be shaped by myth and legend, impacting our understanding of past events."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Ashoka’s rule influence the development of Buddhism in Asia?",
                  "options": [
                    "Spread through diplomatic and missionary efforts",
                    "Enforced Buddhism as state religion",
                    "Limited to India",
                    "Focused on monasticism only"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spread through diplomatic and missionary efforts",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka’s rule had a significant impact on the development of Buddhism in Asia by actively promoting its spread through diplomatic missions and missionary work. His efforts helped extend Buddhism beyond India, contributing to its growth across the Asian continent."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 14,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s defeat in which battle led to the temporary loss of Babylon?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Corupedium",
                    "Battle of Gaugamela",
                    "Battle of Granicus"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Corupedium",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator temporarily lost Babylon due to his defeat in the Battle of Corupedium against Lysimachus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which region did Seleucus Nicator establish a major stronghold as a counterweight to Antigonus?",
                  "options": ["Anatolia", "Persia", "Egypt", "India"],
                  "answer": "Persia",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator established a major stronghold in Persia to balance the power dynamics with Antigonus."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Seleucus Nicator manage to reestablish control over Babylon in 311 BCE?",
                  "options": [
                    "Direct military conquest",
                    "Negotiating with Ptolemy and gaining support",
                    "Strategic alliance with Antigonus",
                    "Diplomatic channels alone"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Negotiating with Ptolemy and gaining support",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator reestablished control over Babylon by negotiating with Ptolemy and securing his support. This diplomatic approach helped him regain his position and stabilize his control over the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significant outcome of the Battle of Ipsus for Seleucus Nicator?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control over Egypt",
                    "Dominance in the Eastern Macedonian Empire",
                    "Loss of Anatolia",
                    "Treaty with the Ptolemies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dominance in the Eastern Macedonian Empire",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Ipsus was a turning point for Seleucus Nicator, as it enabled him to establish dominance over the eastern portion of the former Macedonian Empire. This victory solidified his position and expanded his influence in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Seleucus Nicator play in the political instability that followed Alexander’s death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Stabilized the west",
                    "Key player in division",
                    "Fled and left chaos",
                    "Formed alliances with Rome"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Key player in division",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator played a crucial role in the division of Alexander the Great’s vast empire following his death. After Alexander’s empire fragmented, Seleucus emerged as a prominent figure among the Diadochi (successor generals). He initially controlled Babylon and later expanded his influence across a significant portion of the former Macedonian Empire. His actions were pivotal in shaping the boundaries and political structure of the Hellenistic world. Seleucus’ strategic negotiations, battles, and alliances were instrumental in establishing the Seleucid Empire, which became a major power in the Hellenistic period. His role in dividing Alexander's empire significantly impacted the political dynamics and territorial configurations of the successor states."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important battle did Seleucus Nicator win against Demetrius, strengthening his position in the East?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Gaza",
                    "Battle of Babylon",
                    "Battle of Persepolis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Gaza",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's victory in the Battle of Gaza against Demetrius was crucial in strengthening his position in the East."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s political and military strategies were pivotal in shaping the course of which historical period?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Roman Empire",
                    "The Hellenistic period",
                    "The Byzantine Empire",
                    "The Middle Ages"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Hellenistic period",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's strategies were critical in shaping the Hellenistic period, particularly through his establishment of the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What specific administrative change did Seleucus Nicator implement to consolidate his power in Mesopotamia?",
                  "options": [
                    "Redistributed land",
                    "Established new cities",
                    "Reformed the tax system",
                    "Created a new military hierarchy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Established new cities",
                  "explanation": "To consolidate his power in Mesopotamia, Seleucus Nicator implemented a significant administrative change by establishing new cities as administrative centers. One of his most notable projects was the founding of Seleucia on the Tigris River, which became a major hub for administration and commerce in the region. This strategy helped him strengthen his control over the vast and culturally diverse territory of Mesopotamia. The establishment of these cities not only facilitated better governance and resource management but also promoted economic development and stability in the area. By centralizing administrative functions and creating urban centers, Seleucus effectively solidified his authority and laid the groundwork for the enduring influence of the Seleucid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s alliance with which ruler resulted in the cession of territories in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta Maurya",
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Darius III",
                    "Bindusara"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator’s alliance with Chandragupta Maurya led to the cession of territories in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s relationship with which other Diadochi was critical in securing his empire’s northern frontier?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lysimachus",
                    "Ptolemy",
                    "Cassander",
                    "Demetrius"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Lysimachus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's relationship with Lysimachus was crucial in securing his northern frontier and maintaining stability in his empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 15,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator's strategic marriages were aimed at:",
                  "options": [
                    "Gaining military support",
                    "Strengthening alliances with other Diadochi",
                    "Expanding his territory",
                    "Building a cultural heritage"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strengthening alliances with other Diadochi",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator used strategic marriages primarily to strengthen alliances with other Diadochi, solidifying his political and military position."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Seleucid ruler’s reign marked the beginning of a period of decline for the Seleucid Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucus IV Philopator",
                    "Antiochus III",
                    "Antiochus IV Epiphanes",
                    "Seleucus V Philometor"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucus IV Philopator",
                  "explanation": "The reign of Seleucus IV Philopator marked the beginning of a period of decline for the Seleucid Empire, as it faced increasing internal and external pressures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator's approach to integrating Greek and Persian cultures within his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Separate cultural regions",
                    "Syncretic blend of cultures",
                    "Complete isolation of Persian culture",
                    "Only Greek practices"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Syncretic blend of cultures",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator adopted a policy of promoting a syncretic blend of Greek and Persian cultures to effectively integrate his diverse empire. By combining elements of both cultures, he aimed to create a cohesive and stable administrative and social framework. This approach involved adopting Persian administrative practices and integrating Greek cultural and architectural styles, which helped bridge cultural gaps and foster a sense of unity among the empire's varied populations. This blending of cultures not only facilitated smoother governance and better relations between different ethnic groups but also ensured the preservation and continuation of both Greek and Persian traditions within the empire. Seleucus's strategy was instrumental in establishing and maintaining the Seleucid Empire's influence across a vast and culturally rich territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for Seleucus Nicator’s alliance with Ptolemy I Soter?",
                  "options": [
                    "To secure trade routes",
                    "To gain military assistance against Antigonus",
                    "To establish a cultural exchange program",
                    "To divide Alexander’s empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To gain military assistance against Antigonus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator allied with Ptolemy I Soter primarily to gain military support against Antigonus Monophthalmus, a key rival."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The establishment of which city by Seleucus Nicator was a major milestone in his campaign to secure trade routes?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                    "Antioch",
                    "Persepolis",
                    "Alexandria"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                  "explanation": "Seleucia on the Tigris was a major city founded by Seleucus Nicator to secure and control important trade routes in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Seleucus Nicator's assassination impact the Seleucid Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Immediate peace",
                    "Internal conflicts and instability",
                    "Stronger external alliances",
                    "End of the empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Internal conflicts and instability",
                  "explanation": "The assassination of Seleucus Nicator had profound consequences for the Seleucid Empire. Following his death, the empire experienced a period of significant internal turmoil and instability. The power vacuum left by his assassination led to a struggle for succession among his generals and family members, resulting in factionalism and frequent changes in leadership. This internal discord weakened the central authority and made the empire more vulnerable to external threats. The subsequent instability eroded the empire's ability to maintain control over its vast territories and manage its complex administrative structure effectively. As a result, the Seleucid Empire faced increased challenges in preserving its unity and influence, leading to gradual decline over time."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Seleucus Nicator’s military campaigns extended into which region, impacting the political landscape significantly?",
                  "options": [
                    "Anatolia",
                    "India",
                    "North Africa",
                    "Central Asia"
                  ],
                  "answer": "India",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator's military campaigns extended into India, which significantly influenced the political landscape of the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major conflict did Seleucus Nicator engage in against the forces of Antigonus Monophthalmus?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Ipsus",
                    "Battle of Gaza",
                    "Battle of Babylon",
                    "Battle of Persepolis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ipsus",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator participated in the Battle of Ipsus against Antigonus Monophthalmus, which was a decisive conflict in the struggle for control of Alexander's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Seleucus Nicator’s most significant diplomatic achievement in his relations with the Indian subcontinent?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of trade agreements",
                    "Treaty of mutual defense",
                    "Marriage alliances",
                    "Military support in Indian conflicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of trade agreements",
                  "explanation": "Seleucus Nicator’s most significant diplomatic achievement with the Indian subcontinent was the establishment of trade agreements, facilitating economic and cultural exchanges."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city founded by Seleucus Nicator became a significant cultural and economic center in the East?",
                  "options": [
                    "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                    "Antioch",
                    "Alexandria",
                    "Pergamum"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Seleucia on the Tigris",
                  "explanation": "Seleucia on the Tigris became a major cultural and economic center in the East, playing a pivotal role in the Seleucid Empire."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },

    {
      "topicName": "Gupta Empire",
      "subtopics": [
        {
          "subtopicName": "Samudragupta",
          "description": [
            "Samudragupta was a great military ruler of the Gupta Empire, often called the Napoleon of India.",
            "Samudragupta was a powerful ruler of the Gupta Empire, reigning from around 335 to 375 CE.",
            "Samudragupta is known for his military conquests, which greatly expanded the Gupta Empire across northern and central India.",
            "Samudragupta was a patron of the arts and culture, and he was also an accomplished poet and musician.",
            "His reign is often referred to as the 'Golden Age' of India due to the prosperity, cultural development, and advancements in science and literature.",
            "The Allahabad Pillar inscription highlights Samudragupta’s extensive military campaigns and his policy of 'Digvijaya' (world conquest)."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the second emperor of the Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Samudragupta",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was the second emperor of the Gupta Empire, succeeding his father Chandragupta I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription details Samudragupta's military conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Prayag Pillar",
                    "Eran Stone",
                    "Allahabad Pillar",
                    "Mathura Stone"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Allahabad Pillar",
                  "explanation": "The Allahabad Pillar inscription provides a detailed account of Samudragupta's military conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Samudragupta's father?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Harsha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta I",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was the son of Chandragupta I, the founder of the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major focus of Samudragupta's military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Northwestern India",
                    "Southern India",
                    "Eastern India",
                    "Central India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northwestern India",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta focused on expanding his empire in northwestern India, defeating several kings and annexing their territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What type of sacrifice did Samudragupta perform?",
                  "options": ["Ashvamedha", "Rajasuya", "Vajapeya", "Chaula"],
                  "answer": "Ashvamedha",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta performed the Ashvamedha sacrifice to assert his sovereignty over his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which river marked the western boundary of Samudragupta's empire?",
                  "options": ["Indus", "Ganges", "Ravi", "Yamuna"],
                  "answer": "Ravi",
                  "explanation": "The Ravi River marked the western boundary of Samudragupta's empire at its height."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Samudragupta's title mentioned in the Allahabad Pillar inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Prakrama",
                    "Vijayadhvaja",
                    "Mahasena",
                    "Chakravartin"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Prakrama",
                  "explanation": "The title Prakrama, meaning 'valorous', was attributed to Samudragupta in the Allahabad Pillar inscription."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which neighboring rulers tried to please Samudragupta according to the Allahabad Pillar inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Southern rulers",
                    "Western rulers",
                    "Eastern rulers",
                    "Northern rulers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Southern rulers",
                  "explanation": "The inscription mentions that many rulers from the south tried to please Samudragupta."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for the issuance of Samudragupta's coins and inscriptions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military victories",
                    "Religious ceremonies",
                    "Economic transactions",
                    "Royal propaganda"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Royal propaganda",
                  "explanation": "The coins and inscriptions were used for royal propaganda, highlighting Samudragupta's achievements and status."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Samudragupta as the Gupta Emperor?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Kumaragupta",
                    "Skandagupta",
                    "Harsha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta II",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was succeeded by his son Chandragupta II, who continued the expansionist policies."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Samudragupta belong to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maurya Dynasty",
                    "Gupta Dynasty",
                    "Kushan Dynasty",
                    "Satavahana Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gupta Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was a prominent ruler of the Gupta Dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What is the name of the famous inscription that provides details about Samudragupta's conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Allahabad Pillar Inscription",
                    "Ashokan Edicts",
                    "Hathigumpha Inscription",
                    "Rudradaman Inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Allahabad Pillar Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Allahabad Pillar Inscription, composed by Harisena, details Samudragupta's military achievements and conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title was given to Samudragupta due to his military prowess?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lion of the North",
                    "King of Kings",
                    "Second Ashoka",
                    "Great Conqueror"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Great Conqueror",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was often referred to as the 'Great Conqueror' due to his extensive military campaigns and conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who composed the Prayaga Prasasti?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Harisena",
                    "Bana Bhatta",
                    "Aryabhatta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Harisena",
                  "explanation": "The Prayaga Prasasti, also known as the Allahabad Pillar Inscription, was composed by the court poet Harisena."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta expand the Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through peaceful negotiations",
                    "By forming alliances with neighboring kingdoms",
                    "Through military conquests",
                    "By trading with foreign powers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Through military conquests",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta expanded the Gupta Empire primarily through a series of military conquests and campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title was Samudragupta known for after his conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mahapadma",
                    "Paramabhattaraka",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Chakravartin"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was known as Vikramaditya, a title that reflected his legendary status as a great king and warrior."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which northern territories did Samudragupta's campaigns notably include?",
                  "options": [
                    "Punjab and Kashmir",
                    "Bengal and Assam",
                    "Rajasthan and Gujarat",
                    "Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Punjab and Kashmir",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's military campaigns notably included the northern territories of Punjab and Kashmir, helping to secure Gupta control over these regions."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What were the major southern kingdoms that Samudragupta defeated?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cholas, Cheras, and Pandyas",
                    "Vakatakas, Pallavas, and Kadambas",
                    "Satavahanas, Ikshvakus, and Abhiras",
                    "Mauryas, Shungas, and Kanvas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cholas, Cheras, and Pandyas",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta defeated the major southern kingdoms of Cholas, Cheras, and Pandyas during his southern campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta's conquests impact the Gupta Empire's economy and culture?",
                  "options": [
                    "They led to economic decline and cultural stagnation",
                    "They promoted trade and cultural exchange",
                    "They had no significant impact on the empire",
                    "They resulted in a decline of Indian civilization"
                  ],
                  "answer": "They promoted trade and cultural exchange",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's conquests promoted trade and cultural exchange, contributing to the prosperity and cultural development of the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of Samudragupta's victory over the Nagas?",
                  "options": [
                    "It marked the beginning of his southern conquests",
                    "It established his control over the central Indian region",
                    "It led to the decline of the Naga Empire",
                    "It was a minor victory with no lasting impact"
                  ],
                  "answer": "It established his control over the central Indian region",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's victory over the Nagas was significant as it established his control over the central Indian region and solidified his power."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What were the major regions conquered by Samudragupta in his campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Northwestern and Central India",
                    "Southern and Eastern India",
                    "Western and Northern India",
                    "Southern and Northwestern India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northwestern and Central India",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta conquered major regions in northwestern and central India during his campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How many battles did Samudragupta reportedly fight according to the Allahabad Pillar inscription?",
                  "options": ["50", "100", "150", "200"],
                  "answer": "100",
                  "explanation": "The Allahabad Pillar inscription states that Samudragupta fought a hundred battles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Samudragupta defeat in his southern campaigns?",
                  "options": ["Chalukya", "Pallava", "Maurya", "Kushan"],
                  "answer": "Pallava",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta advanced into the Pallava kingdom in southern India during his campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription records Samudragupta's accomplishments in defeating various kings?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mathura Stone",
                    "Eran Stone",
                    "Prayag Pillar",
                    "Allahabad Pillar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Allahabad Pillar",
                  "explanation": "The Allahabad Pillar inscription records Samudragupta's achievements and military conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Samudragupta's primary method for documenting his achievements?",
                  "options": [
                    "Temple inscriptions",
                    "Coins",
                    "Public monuments",
                    "Royal edicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Coins",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta used coins to document and propagate his achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title did Samudragupta hold that indicated his role in expanding the empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chakravartin",
                    "Mahakshatrapa",
                    "Samrat",
                    "Rajadhiraja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Samrat",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta held the title Samrat, indicating his role as an emperor and expansionist."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was not a characteristic of Samudragupta's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Art patronage",
                    "Military expansion",
                    "Religious tolerance",
                    "Isolationist policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Isolationist policies",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta was known for military expansion and art patronage, not isolationist policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region was considered the southeastern boundary of Samudragupta's empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kanchipuram",
                    "Pataliputra",
                    "Ayodhya",
                    "Varanasi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kanchipuram",
                  "explanation": "Kanchipuram in the Pallava kingdom marked the southeastern boundary of Samudragupta's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of the Ashvamedha sacrifice performed by Samudragupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "To assert his sovereignty",
                    "To promote trade",
                    "To establish diplomatic relations",
                    "To celebrate a victory"
                  ],
                  "answer": "To assert his sovereignty",
                  "explanation": "The Ashvamedha sacrifice was performed to assert Samudragupta's imperial sovereignty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the contemporary ruler of Samudragupta in Anuradhapura?",
                  "options": [
                    "King Meghavarna",
                    "King Kanishka",
                    "King Ashoka",
                    "King Chandragupta I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "King Meghavarna",
                  "explanation": "King Meghavarna was a contemporary ruler in Anuradhapura during Samudragupta's reign."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta expand the Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Peaceful negotiations",
                    "Forming alliances",
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Trading"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military conquests",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta expanded the Gupta Empire primarily through military conquests, which helped in establishing and consolidating control over a vast region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of Samudragupta's military campaigns in the north?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control over north",
                    "Defeated the Huns",
                    "Conquered Persia",
                    "Invaded China"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control over north",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's campaigns in the north were significant for establishing and securing Gupta control over the northern regions of India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the major southern kingdoms that Samudragupta defeated?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cholas, Cheras, Pandyas",
                    "Vakatakas, Pallavas, Kadambas",
                    "Satavahanas, Ikshvakus, Abhiras",
                    "Mauryas, Shungas, Kanvas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vakatakas, Pallavas, Kadambas",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta defeated several southern kingdoms, including the Vakatakas, Pallavas, and Kadambas, as part of his expansion campaign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta's conquests impact the Gupta Empire's economy and culture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Economic decline",
                    "Promoted trade",
                    "No impact",
                    "Decline of civilization"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promoted trade",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's conquests helped in promoting trade and cultural exchange, contributing to the economic prosperity and cultural development during the Gupta Empire's Golden Age."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significance of Samudragupta's victory over the Nagas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Beginning of southern conquests",
                    "Control over central India",
                    "Decline of Naga Empire",
                    "Minor victory"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control over central India",
                  "explanation": "The victory over the Nagas was significant as it helped Samudragupta establish control over central India, paving the way for further conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the nature of Samudragupta's relationship with the Vakatakas?",
                  "options": ["Hostile", "Friendly", "Neutral", "Unknown"],
                  "answer": "Friendly",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta had a generally friendly relationship with the Vakatakas, often engaging in diplomacy and mutual respect."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta's policies contribute to the Golden Age of India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Religious intolerance",
                    "Neglected culture",
                    "Peace and prosperity",
                    "Limited trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Peace and prosperity",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's policies promoted a climate of peace and prosperity, which contributed significantly to the Golden Age of India during the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the key features of Samudragupta's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized rule",
                    "Decentralized rule",
                    "Military dictatorship",
                    "Democratic rule"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized rule",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's administration was marked by centralized rule, an efficient bureaucracy, and a policy of religious tolerance, which contributed to the stability and growth of the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta's military strategies differ from those of his predecessors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Used cavalry",
                    "Land and sea forces",
                    "Defensive tactics",
                    "Elephants"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Elephants",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's military strategies often involved the use of elephants, which were a significant factor in his successful campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the challenges faced by Samudragupta during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Foreign invasions",
                    "Religious conflicts",
                    "Administrative issues",
                    "None"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Foreign invasions",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta faced challenges such as foreign invasions, internal rebellions, and economic issues, which he successfully managed during his reign."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "When is the start of Samudragupta's reign generally dated to?",
                  "options": ["319 CE", "320 CE", "350 CE", "319-350 CE"],
                  "answer": "319-350 CE",
                  "explanation": "Modern scholars variously assign the start of Samudragupta's reign from c. 319 CE to c. 350 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Gupta king is generally debated to have founded the Gupta calendar era?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Skandagupta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta I or Samudragupta",
                  "explanation": "The identity of the era's founder is debated and is attributed to either Chandragupta I or Samudragupta."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Why is the beginning of Samudragupta's reign uncertain?",
                  "options": [
                    "Unclear inscriptions",
                    "Uncertain period of Chandragupta I's reign",
                    "Debated era's epoch",
                    "No inscriptions available"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Uncertain period of Chandragupta I's reign",
                  "explanation": "The beginning of Samudragupta's reign is uncertain primarily due to the lack of clear historical records regarding the exact period of Chandragupta I's reign. Since Samudragupta was the successor to Chandragupta I, the uncertainties about the latter's reign create ambiguity in determining the exact starting point of Samudragupta’s rule. This lack of precise chronological data impacts the historical timeline and makes it challenging to establish a definitive date for the beginning of Samudragupta's reign. Additionally, discrepancies in inscriptions and other sources further complicate the historical reconstruction of this period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "If Samudragupta is regarded as the founder of the Gupta era, what date is his ascension likely to be?",
                  "options": ["319-320 CE", "320-330 CE", "350 CE", "330 CE"],
                  "answer": "319-320 CE",
                  "explanation": "If Samudragupta is considered the founder of the Gupta era, his ascension is dated to c. 319–320 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "If Chandragupta I is regarded as the founder of the Gupta era, when must Samudragupta's ascension be dated?",
                  "options": [
                    "Earlier than 319 CE",
                    "Later than 319 CE",
                    "350 CE",
                    "Exactly 319 CE"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Later than 319 CE",
                  "explanation": "If Chandragupta I is considered the founder, Samudragupta's ascension must be dated to a later date than 319 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which contemporary king's regnal period is also uncertain?",
                  "options": [
                    "King Meghavarna of Anuradhapura",
                    "King Ashoka of the Maurya Dynasty",
                    "King Harsha of Kanauj",
                    "King Kanishka of the Kushan Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "King Meghavarna of Anuradhapura",
                  "explanation": "King Meghavarna of Anuradhapura's regnal period is also uncertain, making comparisons with Samudragupta's period difficult."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the Prayag Pillar inscription suggest about Chandragupta I?",
                  "options": [
                    "He was a contemporary of Samudragupta",
                    "He appointed his son as his successor",
                    "He founded the Gupta calendar era",
                    "His reign lasted less than a decade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "He appointed his son as his successor",
                  "explanation": "The Prayag Pillar inscription suggests that Chandragupta I appointed his son as his successor, implying a long reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What aspect of Samudragupta's reign is debated by scholars?",
                  "options": [
                    "The exact length of his reign",
                    "The exact start date of his reign",
                    "The number of military campaigns he led",
                    "The geographic extent of his empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The exact start date of his reign",
                  "explanation": "Scholars debate the exact start date of Samudragupta's reign due to uncertainties related to his father's reign and inscriptions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the debate over Samudragupta's succession reveal about historical records?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ambiguity",
                    "Accuracy",
                    "Completeness",
                    "Consistency"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ambiguity",
                  "explanation": "The debate reveals that historical records can be ambiguous and open to interpretation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the uncertainty about Samudragupta's reign show about ancient history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Document reliability",
                    "Dating challenges",
                    "Archaeological evidence",
                    "Clear inscriptions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dating challenges",
                  "explanation": "The uncertainty highlights the challenges in accurately dating historical events."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Samudragupta's military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of territory",
                    "Religious conversion",
                    "Diplomatic alliances",
                    "Trade control"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of territory",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's military campaigns were primarily focused on expanding the Gupta Empire's territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient historian provided a detailed account of Samudragupta's reign?",
                  "options": ["Aryabhata", "Kalidasa", "Harisena", "Bana"],
                  "answer": "Harisena",
                  "explanation": "Harisena, a contemporary of Samudragupta, provided detailed accounts of his reign in inscriptions and literary works."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Samudragupta’s victory over the Huns on the Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Consolidated control",
                    "Weakened influence",
                    "Dominance in the west",
                    "No impact"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidated control",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta's victory over the Huns helped to consolidate Gupta control over northern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Samudragupta handle the political fragmentation in southern India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through military conquests",
                    "By forming alliances",
                    "By diplomatic negotiations",
                    "By ignoring it"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Through military conquests",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta addressed the political fragmentation in southern India through a series of military conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which text offers a comprehensive record of Samudragupta’s achievements and conquests?",
                  "options": [
                    "Prayaga Prasasti",
                    "Allahabad Pillar Inscription",
                    "Meghaduta",
                    "Vikramorvashiya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Allahabad Pillar Inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Allahabad Pillar Inscription provides a comprehensive record of Samudragupta's achievements and conquests."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which neighboring kingdom was notably influenced by Samudragupta's policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kushan Empire",
                    "Vakatakas",
                    "Chalukyas",
                    "Pallavas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vakatakas",
                  "explanation": "The Vakatakas were notably influenced by Samudragupta’s policies due to his interactions and conquests in the region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the result of Samudragupta’s military campaigns in the western regions of India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of trade routes",
                    "Expansion of Gupta territory",
                    "Diplomatic ties with Persian Empire",
                    "Cultural assimilation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Gupta territory",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta’s military campaigns in the western regions led to the expansion of Gupta territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key feature of Samudragupta’s reign contributed to the Gupta Empire's Golden Age?",
                  "options": [
                    "Religious tolerance",
                    "Technological innovation",
                    "Increased taxation",
                    "Military expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious tolerance",
                  "explanation": "Religious tolerance during Samudragupta's reign contributed significantly to the cultural and intellectual flourishing of the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Samudragupta's policy towards the local rulers he conquered?",
                  "options": [
                    "Complete annexation",
                    "Autonomy with tribute",
                    "Reinstatement of previous rulers",
                    "Complete destruction of local power"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Autonomy with tribute",
                  "explanation": "Samudragupta often allowed local rulers to retain their positions under the condition of paying tribute to the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major dynasty was a contemporary rival to Samudragupta’s Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": ["Chalukyas", "Mauryas", "Shungas", "Nandas"],
                  "answer": "Chalukyas",
                  "explanation": "The Chalukyas were a major contemporary rival to the Gupta Empire during Samudragupta’s reign."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Chandragupta II",
          "description": [
            "Chandragupta II was a ruler of the Gupta Empire known for expanding its territory and cultural achievements.",
            "Chandragupta II was one of the most celebrated rulers of the Gupta Empire, reigning from around 380 to 415 CE.",
            "Under Chandragupta II's rule, the Gupta Empire reached its zenith, with a vast territory and flourishing trade and culture.",
            "Chandragupta II is known for defeating the Shakas (Western Kshatrapas) and annexing their territories, expanding the Gupta Empire to western India.",
            "His reign is marked by immense cultural achievements, particularly in art, literature, and science, making it a 'Golden Age' of India.",
            "The court of Chandragupta II was home to the legendary 'Navaratnas' (Nine Gems), including the famous poet Kalidasa."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital city of Chandragupta II's empire?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ayodhya", "Ujjain", "Varanasi"],
                  "answer": "Ayodhya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II made Ayodhya his capital city."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous poet and dramatist was a scholar at Chandragupta II's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Bhartrihari",
                    "Vatsyayana"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kalidasa",
                  "explanation": "Kalidasa was one of the famous scholars at Chandragupta II's court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta II was known for his patronage of which type of arts?",
                  "options": [
                    "Art and sculpture",
                    "Music and dance",
                    "Literature and philosophy",
                    "Architecture and science"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Art and sculpture",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's reign is noted for flourishing art, architecture, and sculpture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title appeared on some of Chandragupta II's silver coins?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Chakravartin",
                    "Raja",
                    "Maharaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Some of Chandragupta II's silver coins bore the title Vikramaditya."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region was not subjugated by Chandragupta II?",
                  "options": ["Gujarat", "Saurashtra", "Malwa", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II subjugated Gujarat, Saurashtra, and Malwa, but not Bengal."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Chandragupta II's daughter married to?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rudrasena II",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Harsha",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rudrasena II",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's daughter Prabhavati was married to Rudrasena II, king of the Vakatakas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "During which years did Faxian visit India?",
                  "options": [
                    "405–411 CE",
                    "380–405 CE",
                    "410–420 CE",
                    "390–400 CE"
                  ],
                  "answer": "405–411 CE",
                  "explanation": "Faxian visited India from 405 to 411 CE during Chandragupta II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city besides Ayodhya achieved prosperity under Chandragupta II?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ujjain", "Varanasi", "Delhi"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Pataliputra also achieved prosperity and grandeur under Chandragupta II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the charitable actions of Chandragupta II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Maintained free rest houses and hospitals",
                    "Established new temples",
                    "Supported international trade",
                    "Organized grand festivals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Maintained free rest houses and hospitals",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II maintained free rest houses and hospitals as part of his charitable actions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous scholar was associated with the court of Chandragupta II?",
                  "options": [
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Varahamihira",
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Bhartrihari"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kalidasa",
                  "explanation": "Kalidasa was a renowned scholar at Chandragupta II's court, known for his contributions to literature and drama."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary religion supported during Chandragupta II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hinduism",
                    "Buddhism",
                    "Jainism",
                    "Zoroastrianism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hinduism",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II is known for his patronage of Hinduism, including the support of Hindu temples and scholars."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant alliance did Chandragupta II form through marriage?",
                  "options": ["Vakatakas", "Chalukyas", "Pallavas", "Kushanas"],
                  "answer": "Vakatakas",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II formed a strategic alliance with the Vakatakas through the marriage of his daughter to Rudrasena II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous astronomical work was created during Chandragupta II's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Surya Siddhanta",
                    "Aryabhatiya",
                    "Brahmasphutasiddhanta",
                    "Padaratnamala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aryabhatiya",
                  "explanation": "Aryabhatiya, an important astronomical and mathematical work, was composed by Aryabhata during Chandragupta II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city was the center of trade and culture under Chandragupta II?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ujjain", "Taxila", "Kannauj"],
                  "answer": "Ujjain",
                  "explanation": "Ujjain was a major center of trade and cultural activities during Chandragupta II's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Chandragupta II's primary military strategy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defensive warfare",
                    "Naval dominance",
                    "Diplomatic alliances",
                    "Aggressive expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Aggressive expansion",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II is known for his aggressive military campaigns to expand the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which prominent scholar and commentator was part of Chandragupta II's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kumarajiva",
                    "Bhartrihari",
                    "Madhava",
                    "Kautilya"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bhartrihari",
                  "explanation": "Bhartrihari, known for his contributions to Sanskrit literature and philosophy, was a notable scholar in Chandragupta II's court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the key feature of the coins issued during Chandragupta II's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Religious symbols",
                    "Animal motifs",
                    "Portraits of rulers",
                    "Geometric patterns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Portraits of rulers",
                  "explanation": "Coins issued during Chandragupta II's rule often featured portraits of the king, emphasizing his royal status."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Sanskrit play was written during Chandragupta II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shakuntala",
                    "Mrichchhakatika",
                    "Mudrarakshasa",
                    "Vikramorvasiyam"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramorvasiyam",
                  "explanation": "Vikramorvasiyam, a celebrated Sanskrit play by Kalidasa, was written during the reign of Chandragupta II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region was a significant part of Chandragupta II's empire for trade purposes?",
                  "options": [
                    "Deccan Plateau",
                    "Indus Valley",
                    "Gangetic Plains",
                    "Narmada Valley"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gangetic Plains",
                  "explanation": "The Gangetic Plains were crucial for trade and agriculture, contributing to the prosperity of Chandragupta II's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major cultural contribution of Chandragupta II’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Development of classical Sanskrit drama",
                    "Advancements in metallurgy",
                    "Expansion of Buddhist monasteries",
                    "Establishment of new trading routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Development of classical Sanskrit drama",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s reign is noted for significant advancements in classical Sanskrit drama and literature."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "When did Chandragupta II reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "c. 380–c. 415 CE",
                    "c. 350–c. 400 CE",
                    "c. 390–c. 425 CE",
                    "c. 370–c. 410 CE"
                  ],
                  "answer": "c. 380–c. 415 CE",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II reigned from approximately 380 to 415 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Chandragupta II's father?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Rudrasena II",
                    "Ashoka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Samudragupta",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II was the son of Samudragupta."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which territories did Chandragupta II subjugate between 388 and 409 CE?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra",
                    "Gujarat, Bengal, and Malwa",
                    "Gujarat, Rajasthan, and Kashmir",
                    "Gujarat, Punjab, and Karnataka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II subjugated Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra during this period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "To strengthen his southern flank, Chandragupta II arranged a marriage between his daughter and which king?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rudrasena II",
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Harsha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rudrasena II",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II arranged a marriage between his daughter Prabhavati and Rudrasena II, king of the Vakatakas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Chandragupta II make his capital?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ayodhya", "Ujjain", "Varanasi"],
                  "answer": "Ayodhya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II made Ayodhya his capital city."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title did some of Chandragupta II's silver coins bear?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Chakravartin",
                    "Raja",
                    "Maharaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Some of Chandragupta II's silver coins bore the title Vikramaditya, meaning 'Sun of Valour.'"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous scholars were patrons of Chandragupta II's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Varahamihira and Kalidasa",
                    "Aryabhata and Patanjali",
                    "Bhartrihari and Kalidasa",
                    "Vatsyayana and Aryabhata"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Varahamihira and Kalidasa",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's court was patronized by the astronomer Varahamihira and the Sanskrit poet and dramatist Kalidasa."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did the Chinese Buddhist pilgrim Faxian praise about Chandragupta II's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "The military conquests",
                    "The system of government and charity",
                    "The size of the empire",
                    "The architectural achievements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The system of government and charity",
                  "explanation": "Faxian praised the system of government, charity, and medicine maintained during Chandragupta II’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city, besides Ayodhya, achieved prosperity and grandeur under Chandragupta II?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ujjain", "Varanasi", "Gujarat"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Besides Ayodhya, the city of Pataliputra also achieved prosperity and grandeur under Chandragupta II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta II was a devout follower of which religion, while also tolerating Buddhism and Jainism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hinduism",
                    "Buddhism",
                    "Jainism",
                    "Zoroastrianism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hinduism",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II was a devout Hindu but also tolerated Buddhism and Jainism."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical text provides details about Chandragupta II's court and administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Vishnu Purana",
                    "The Bhagavata Purana",
                    "The Jaina Agamas",
                    "The Harshacharita"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Harshacharita",
                  "explanation": "The Harshacharita, written by Banabhatta, provides details about Chandragupta II's court and administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which specific title was used by Chandragupta II to denote his military prowess and status?",
                  "options": [
                    "Parameshvara",
                    "Mahashveta",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Mahabali"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II used the title Vikramaditya to denote his military prowess and status."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Chandragupta II’s diplomatic relations with neighboring states?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military alliances",
                    "Cultural exchanges",
                    "Trade agreements",
                    "Marital alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marital alliances",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s diplomatic focus was on marital alliances, notably with the Vakatakas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major literary work, completed during Chandragupta II’s reign, is considered a key source of classical Sanskrit drama?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mrichchhakatika",
                    "The Kumārasambhava",
                    "The Raghuvamsa",
                    "The Malavikagnimitra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Malavikagnimitra",
                  "explanation": "The Malavikagnimitra, a classical Sanskrit drama by Kalidasa, was completed during Chandragupta II’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant cultural and religious practice was promoted by Chandragupta II during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hindu rituals",
                    "Buddhist meditation",
                    "Jain asceticism",
                    "Zoroastrian fire worship"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hindu rituals",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II promoted Hindu rituals and practices while also being tolerant of other religions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of Chandragupta II’s court in the development of Sanskrit literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Patronage and encouragement",
                    "Restriction and control",
                    "Neglect and oversight",
                    "Complete indifference"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patronage and encouragement",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s court played a significant role in the development of Sanskrit literature through patronage and encouragement."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Chandragupta II’s administration establish as a key center for astronomical studies?",
                  "options": ["Ujjain", "Pataliputra", "Mathura", "Taxila"],
                  "answer": "Ujjain",
                  "explanation": "Ujjain became a key center for astronomical studies during Chandragupta II’s administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which artifact from Chandragupta II’s reign provides insights into the economic prosperity of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gold coins",
                    "Stone inscriptions",
                    "Bronze statues",
                    "Silk manuscripts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gold coins",
                  "explanation": "Gold coins from Chandragupta II’s reign provide insights into the economic prosperity and wealth of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significant architectural achievement during Chandragupta II’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of grand temples",
                    "Development of urban infrastructure",
                    "Creation of large water reservoirs",
                    "Establishment of educational institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Construction of grand temples",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s reign saw the construction of grand temples and other significant architectural achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which notable figure’s writings provide a description of the wealth and grandeur of Chandragupta II’s court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Banabhatta",
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Varahamihira"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Banabhatta",
                  "explanation": "Banabhatta’s writings, particularly the Harshacharita, describe the wealth and grandeur of Chandragupta II’s court."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What is the traditional account of how Chandragupta II achieved power?",
                  "options": [
                    "By assassinating a weak elder brother",
                    "By winning a major battle",
                    "Through diplomatic alliances",
                    "By inheriting the throne directly"
                  ],
                  "answer": "By assassinating a weak elder brother",
                  "explanation": "Tradition states that Chandragupta II achieved power by assassinating a weak elder brother."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which regions did Chandragupta II subjugate from 388 to 409 CE?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra",
                    "Gujarat, Bengal, and Malwa",
                    "Gujarat, Rajasthan, and Kashmir",
                    "Gujarat, Punjab, and Karnataka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II subjugated Gujarat, Malwa, and Saurashtra during this period."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which king did Chandragupta II arrange a marriage between his daughter and?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rudrasena II",
                    "Ashoka",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Harsha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rudrasena II",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II arranged a marriage between his daughter Prabhavati and Rudrasena II, king of the Vakatakas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Chinese Buddhist pilgrim visited India during Chandragupta II's reign and praised the system of government and charity?",
                  "options": ["Faxian", "Xuanzang", "Yijing", "Buddhabhadra"],
                  "answer": "Faxian",
                  "explanation": "Faxian visited India during Chandragupta II's reign and praised the system of government and charity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant matrimonial alliance did Chandragupta II make to strengthen his influence in the south?",
                  "options": [
                    "Marriage with a Mysore dynasty",
                    "Marriage with a Tamil king",
                    "Marriage with a king of the Chalukyas",
                    "Marriage with a dynasty in Sri Lanka"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marriage with a Mysore dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II may have made a matrimonial alliance with a dynasty in Mysore to strengthen his influence in the south."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title is Chandragupta II associated with in later Hindu tradition?",
                  "options": [
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Chakravartin",
                    "Rajadhiraja",
                    "Maharaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II is associated with the title Vikramaditya, meaning 'Sun of Valour', in later Hindu tradition."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Chandragupta II's patronage during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Art, literature, and science",
                    "Military conquests",
                    "Agricultural advancements",
                    "Religious reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Art, literature, and science",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's reign is noted for his patronage of art, literature, and science."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city was considered a prominent center of culture during Chandragupta II's rule?",
                  "options": ["Pataliputra", "Ayodhya", "Ujjain", "Mathura"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Pataliputra was a prominent center of culture during Chandragupta II's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region was ruled by Shaka chiefs before Chandragupta II's conquest?",
                  "options": ["Gujarat", "Bengal", "Mysore", "Punjab"],
                  "answer": "Gujarat",
                  "explanation": "Gujarat was ruled by Shaka chiefs before being subjugated by Chandragupta II."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Chandragupta II's daughter play after her husband's death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Acted as regent for her sons",
                    "Governed the entire empire",
                    "Supported her sons' education",
                    "Maintained diplomatic relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Acted as regent for her sons",
                  "explanation": "After her husband's death, Prabhavati acted as regent for her sons, increasing Gupta influence in the south."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical text provides details about Chandragupta II's court and administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Vishnu Purana",
                    "The Bhagavata Purana",
                    "The Jaina Agamas",
                    "The Harshacharita"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Harshacharita",
                  "explanation": "The Harshacharita, written by Banabhatta, provides details about Chandragupta II's court and administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which specific title was used by Chandragupta II to denote his military prowess and status?",
                  "options": [
                    "Parameshvara",
                    "Mahashveta",
                    "Vikramaditya",
                    "Mahabali"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Vikramaditya",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II used the title Vikramaditya to denote his military prowess and status."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Chandragupta II’s diplomatic relations with neighboring states?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military alliances",
                    "Cultural exchanges",
                    "Trade agreements",
                    "Marital alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marital alliances",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s diplomatic focus was on marital alliances, notably with the Vakatakas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major literary work, completed during Chandragupta II’s reign, is considered a key source of classical Sanskrit drama?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mrichchhakatika",
                    "The Kumārasambhava",
                    "The Raghuvamsa",
                    "The Malavikagnimitra"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Malavikagnimitra",
                  "explanation": "The Malavikagnimitra, a classical Sanskrit drama by Kalidasa, was completed during Chandragupta II’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant cultural and religious practice was promoted by Chandragupta II during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hindu rituals",
                    "Buddhist meditation",
                    "Jain asceticism",
                    "Zoroastrian fire worship"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hindu rituals",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II promoted Hindu rituals and practices while also being tolerant of other religions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the role of Chandragupta II’s court in the development of Sanskrit literature?",
                  "options": [
                    "Patronage and encouragement",
                    "Restriction and control",
                    "Neglect and oversight",
                    "Complete indifference"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patronage and encouragement",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s court played a significant role in the development of Sanskrit literature through patronage and encouragement."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Chandragupta II’s court was known for its patronage of which literary form?",
                  "options": [
                    "Epic poetry",
                    "Dramatic plays",
                    "Lyric poetry",
                    "Philosophical essays"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Dramatic plays",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's court was renowned for its support of dramatic plays, with Kalidasa being a prominent figure."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which contemporary historian provides accounts of Chandragupta II’s administration and policies?",
                  "options": ["Fa-Hien", "Hiuen Tsang", "I-Tsing", "Al-Biruni"],
                  "answer": "Fa-Hien",
                  "explanation": "Fa-Hien’s accounts provide valuable information about Chandragupta II’s administration and policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the significant architectural achievement during Chandragupta II’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of grand temples",
                    "Development of urban infrastructure",
                    "Creation of large water reservoirs",
                    "Establishment of educational institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Construction of grand temples",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s reign saw the construction of grand temples and other significant architectural achievements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which notable figure’s writings provide a description of the wealth and grandeur of Chandragupta II’s court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Banabhatta",
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Aryabhata",
                    "Varahamihira"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Banabhatta",
                  "explanation": "Banabhatta’s writings, particularly the Harshacharita, describe the wealth and grandeur of Chandragupta II’s court."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Skandagupta",
          "description": [
            "Skandagupta was known for defending the Gupta Empire from invasions by the Huns.",
            "Skandagupta was a Gupta emperor who ruled from around 455 to 467 CE.",
            "Skandagupta is known for successfully defending the Gupta Empire against the invasions of the Huns (Hephthalites).",
            "His military victories, especially against the Huns, helped delay the fall of the Gupta Empire for several more decades.",
            "Skandagupta's reign saw internal economic challenges, reflected in the debasement of coinage and increased military expenditures.",
            "Skandagupta is often regarded as the last great ruler of the Gupta dynasty, after which the empire gradually declined."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Skandagupta's father?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Kumaragupta I",
                    "Chandragupta II"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Kumaragupta I",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta was the son of Kumaragupta I."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription suggests that Skandagupta restored Gupta power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Junagadh inscription",
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Allahabad pillar inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription suggests that Skandagupta restored Gupta power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which group did Skandagupta repel during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Indo-Hephthalites (Hunas)",
                    "Shakas",
                    "Kushanas",
                    "Mughals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Indo-Hephthalites (Hunas)",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta repelled an invasion by the Indo-Hephthalites (Hunas) during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the likely successor of Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Purugupta",
                    "Kumaragupta II",
                    "Samudragupta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Purugupta",
                  "explanation": "Purugupta, who was probably Skandagupta's younger half-brother, succeeded him."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant feature is mentioned in the Bhitari pillar inscription about Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeated Pushyamitras",
                    "Defeated Yudhyamitras",
                    "Married to Rudrasena II's daughter",
                    "Conquered Gujarat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeated Yudhyamitras",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription mentions that Skandagupta defeated enemies referred to as Yudhyamitras or Pushyamitras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where did Skandagupta spend a night before defeating his enemies?",
                  "options": [
                    "On the bare earth",
                    "In a palace",
                    "In a temple",
                    "In a battlefield camp"
                  ],
                  "answer": "On the bare earth",
                  "explanation": "According to the Bhitari pillar inscription, Skandagupta spent a night on the bare earth before defeating his enemies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city contains the Junagadh rock inscription of Skandagupta?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Ujjain", "Girnar", "Pataliputra"],
                  "answer": "Girnar",
                  "explanation": "The Junagadh rock inscription of Skandagupta is located in Girnar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which title did Skandagupta hold as one of the last great Gupta emperors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Great Emperor",
                    "Maharaja",
                    "Rajadhiraja",
                    "Chakravartin"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chakravartin",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta is generally considered one of the last great Gupta emperors, holding the title Chakravartin."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Skandagupta do after defeating his enemies according to the Bhitari inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Visited his mother",
                    "Built new fortresses",
                    "Initiated trade agreements",
                    "Expanded his territory"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Visited his mother",
                  "explanation": "After defeating his enemies, Skandagupta visited his widowed mother, whose eyes were full of tears from joy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following inscriptions does NOT mention Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription",
                    "Allahabad pillar inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sarnath inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Sarnath inscription does not mention Skandagupta."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary challenge Skandagupta faced during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Invasions by the Huns",
                    "Economic instability",
                    "Internal rebellions",
                    "Religious conflicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Invasions by the Huns",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta's primary challenge was repelling invasions by the Indo-Hephthalites (Huns)."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Gupta emperor’s reign is considered a golden age for the Gupta Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Kumaragupta I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta II",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II's reign is often considered a golden age for the Gupta Empire due to its cultural and economic prosperity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which artifact provides evidence of Skandagupta’s military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gold coins",
                    "Silver plate",
                    "Bronze statue",
                    "Stone inscriptions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Stone inscriptions",
                  "explanation": "Stone inscriptions, such as the Bhitari pillar inscription, provide evidence of Skandagupta's military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the capital city of the Gupta Empire during Skandagupta’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Pataliputra", "Ujjain", "Kanauj"],
                  "answer": "Pataliputra",
                  "explanation": "Pataliputra was the capital city of the Gupta Empire during Skandagupta’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Gupta ruler is known for having significant military success against the Hunas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Kumaragupta I",
                    "Skandagupta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Skandagupta",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta is known for his significant military success against the Hunas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What type of governance did Skandagupta's administration primarily focus on?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized monarchy",
                    "Feudal system",
                    "Republicanism",
                    "Decentralized governance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized monarchy",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta’s administration focused on a centralized monarchy to maintain control over his vast empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major event marked the end of Skandagupta’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Invasion by the Mughals",
                    "Internal revolt",
                    "Succession crisis",
                    "Decline of Gupta power"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decline of Gupta power",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta’s reign saw the beginning of the decline of Gupta power due to external pressures and internal issues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Skandagupta’s notable achievement in terms of architecture or infrastructure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of new temples",
                    "Expansion of road networks",
                    "Building of fortresses",
                    "Development of irrigation systems"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building of fortresses",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta is noted for building fortresses as part of his defense strategy against invasions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Gupta emperor is known for extensive patronage of learning and culture, influencing Skandagupta’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Chandragupta I",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Kumaragupta I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Chandragupta II",
                  "explanation": "Chandragupta II’s extensive patronage of learning and culture influenced the intellectual environment during Skandagupta’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a common feature of Gupta coins during Skandagupta’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Depiction of deities",
                    "Commemorative inscriptions",
                    "Images of military conquests",
                    "Portrayals of daily life"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Depiction of deities",
                  "explanation": "Gupta coins from Skandagupta’s rule often featured depictions of deities, reflecting the religious aspects of his reign."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What significant military achievement is associated with Skandagupta according to the Bhitari pillar inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Restoration of Gupta power",
                    "Establishment of new trade routes",
                    "Expansion into southern India",
                    "Defeat of the Huns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Restoration of Gupta power",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription suggests that Skandagupta restored Gupta power by defeating his enemies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Skandagupta focus on securing through military campaigns during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gujarat and Malwa",
                    "Southern India",
                    "Eastern Bengal",
                    "Deccan Plateau"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Gujarat and Malwa",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta focused on securing Gujarat and Malwa during his reign to stabilize his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Skandagupta's reign as suggested by his inscriptions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defeating foreign invasions",
                    "Cultural development",
                    "Religious reforms",
                    "Administrative restructuring"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeating foreign invasions",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta's inscriptions primarily highlight his efforts in defeating foreign invasions and restoring Gupta power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "According to the Bhitari pillar inscription, what did Skandagupta do to prepare for his campaign against his enemies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Held a grand assembly",
                    "Performed a religious ritual",
                    "Spent a night on the bare earth",
                    "Built new fortifications"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spent a night on the bare earth",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta prepared for his campaign by spending a night on the bare earth, as mentioned in the Bhitari pillar inscription."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What type of enemy might Skandagupta have faced according to some interpretations of the Bhitari inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Pushyamitras",
                    "Yudhyamitras",
                    "Kushanas",
                    "Shakas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Pushyamitras",
                  "explanation": "Some interpretations of the Bhitari inscription suggest that Skandagupta faced enemies referred to as Pushyamitras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following inscriptions does not mention Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription",
                    "Ashoka's Edicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashoka's Edicts",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's Edicts do not mention Skandagupta. The Junagadh rock and Bhitari pillar inscriptions do."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What alternative interpretation is provided by some scholars for the enemies mentioned in the Bhitari inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Yudhyamitras",
                    "Pushyamitras",
                    "Kidarites",
                    "Shakas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Yudhyamitras",
                  "explanation": "Some scholars interpret the enemies mentioned in the Bhitari inscription as Yudhyamitras instead of Pushyamitras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following statements is supported by the Junagadh rock inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Skandagupta’s military campaigns",
                    "Skandagupta's genealogy",
                    "Skandagupta’s cultural contributions",
                    "Skandagupta’s religious reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Skandagupta’s genealogy",
                  "explanation": "The Junagadh rock inscription provides information about Skandagupta's genealogy, alongside earlier kings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the possible theories regarding Skandagupta's mother's background?",
                  "options": [
                    "She was a concubine of Kumaragupta",
                    "She was a foreign princess",
                    "She was from a noble Aryan family",
                    "She was from a low-caste background"
                  ],
                  "answer": "She was from a low-caste background",
                  "explanation": "Some theories suggest that Skandagupta's mother was from a low-caste background, though this is debated."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Skandagupta’s mother reportedly react to his restoration of Gupta power?",
                  "options": [
                    "With joy and tears",
                    "With indifference",
                    "With anger",
                    "With skepticism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "With joy and tears",
                  "explanation": "According to the Bhitari pillar inscription, Skandagupta's mother reacted with joy and tears after he restored Gupta power."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary military achievement of Skandagupta as mentioned in the Bhitari pillar inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Consolidation of Gupta territories",
                    "Defeat of the Huns",
                    "Reformation of administration",
                    "Expansion into new regions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeat of the Huns",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription highlights Skandagupta's achievement in defeating the Huns, which was a significant military accomplishment."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Skandagupta focus on to secure his empire from external threats?",
                  "options": [
                    "Western India",
                    "Eastern India",
                    "Southern India",
                    "Northern India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Western India",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta focused on securing Western India, including Gujarat and Malwa, to protect his empire from external threats."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical inscription details Skandagupta’s victory over the Huns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription",
                    "Allahabad pillar inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription is known for detailing Skandagupta’s victory over the Huns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What did Skandagupta reportedly do to demonstrate his dedication before his military campaign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Organized a grand feast",
                    "Performed an elaborate ritual",
                    "Spent a night on the bare earth",
                    "Commissioned new military equipment"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Spent a night on the bare earth",
                  "explanation": "According to the Bhitari pillar inscription, Skandagupta spent a night on the bare earth as a sign of his dedication before launching his military campaign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription provides information about Skandagupta's victories and royal achievements?",
                  "options": [
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription",
                    "Ashoka's Edicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Junagadh rock inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Junagadh rock inscription provides information about Skandagupta’s victories and his achievements as a ruler."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which term is used in the inscriptions to describe the enemies defeated by Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Pushyamitras",
                    "Yudhyamitras",
                    "Shakas",
                    "Kushanas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Yudhyamitras",
                  "explanation": "In some interpretations of the Bhitari pillar inscription, the defeated enemies are referred to as Yudhyamitras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What aspect of Skandagupta’s administration is highlighted in the Bhitari pillar inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military strategy",
                    "Cultural patronage",
                    "Economic reforms",
                    "Religious policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military strategy",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription highlights Skandagupta’s military strategy and his efforts in restoring Gupta power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "According to historical interpretations, what was the background of Skandagupta's mother?",
                  "options": [
                    "Noble family",
                    "Foreign princess",
                    "Low-caste background",
                    "Merchant family"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Low-caste background",
                  "explanation": "Historical interpretations suggest that Skandagupta's mother might have come from a low-caste background, though this remains debated."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription is not related to Skandagupta’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ashoka's Edicts",
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ashoka's Edicts",
                  "explanation": "Ashoka's Edicts do not mention Skandagupta. The Bhitari pillar and Junagadh rock inscriptions are related to his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Skandagupta's mother reportedly respond to his achievements as per the inscriptions?",
                  "options": [
                    "With tears of joy",
                    "With indifference",
                    "With anger",
                    "With skepticism"
                  ],
                  "answer": "With tears of joy",
                  "explanation": "The inscriptions describe Skandagupta's mother reacting with tears of joy upon hearing of his achievements."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which battle is often associated with Skandagupta’s efforts to restore Gupta power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of the Narmada",
                    "Battle of the Jhelum",
                    "Battle of the Kalinga",
                    "Battle of the Ganges"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of the Narmada",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of the Narmada is often associated with Skandagupta’s efforts to restore Gupta power, as suggested by some inscriptions and historical records."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the specific name used in some interpretations of the Bhitari inscription to describe Skandagupta's enemies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Pushyamitras",
                    "Yudhyamitras",
                    "Kidarites",
                    "Shakas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Pushyamitras",
                  "explanation": "Some interpretations of the Bhitari inscription read the enemies as Pushyamitras, although others suggest Yudhyamitras."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What theory is supported by Dasharatha Sharma regarding Skandagupta's mother?",
                  "options": [
                    "She held a very exalted status",
                    "She was a low-caste Shudra",
                    "She was not mentioned deliberately",
                    "She was a foreigner"
                  ],
                  "answer": "She held a very exalted status",
                  "explanation": "Dasharatha Sharma argued that the Bhitari inscription suggests Skandagupta's mother held a very exalted status."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What alternative reading did Jagannath Agrawal provide for the Bhitari inscription's description of Skandagupta?",
                  "options": [
                    "Eulogies causing nobility to blush",
                    "Defeating enemies in a specific battle",
                    "Conquering specific regions",
                    "Honoring ancestors' legacy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Eulogies causing nobility to blush",
                  "explanation": "Jagannath Agrawal provided an alternative reading suggesting that the Bhitari inscription describes eulogies causing nobility to blush."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which inscription might suggest that Skandagupta's enemies were from the banks of the Narmada River?",
                  "options": [
                    "Junagadh rock inscription",
                    "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                    "Allahabad pillar inscription",
                    "Sarnath inscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Bhitari pillar inscription",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription may suggest that Skandagupta's enemies were from the banks of the Narmada River."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the date of Skandagupta's ascension to the throne according to the Gupta era?",
                  "options": ["Year 136", "Year 145", "Year 160", "Year 175"],
                  "answer": "Year 136",
                  "explanation": "Skandagupta ascended the throne in year 136 of the Gupta era, which corresponds to approximately 455-456 CE."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which emperor's inscription mentions Skandagupta alongside earlier kings like Ashoka and Rudradaman I?",
                  "options": [
                    "Skandagupta",
                    "Samudragupta",
                    "Kumaragupta I",
                    "Chandragupta I"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Skandagupta",
                  "explanation": "The Junagadh rock inscription, which includes inscriptions of Ashoka and Rudradaman I, also mentions Skandagupta."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which theory is supported regarding the enemies Skandagupta faced according to the Bhitari inscription?",
                  "options": [
                    "Invasion by Pushyamitras",
                    "Invasion by Indo-Hephthalites",
                    "Disputed succession",
                    "Internal rebellion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Invasion by Indo-Hephthalites",
                  "explanation": "One theory suggests that Skandagupta faced an invasion by the Indo-Hephthalites (Hunas) as mentioned in the Bhitari inscription."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the Bhitari pillar inscription suggest Skandagupta did after restoring his family's fortunes?",
                  "options": [
                    "Visited his mother",
                    "Built new temples",
                    "Established trade relations",
                    "Wrote epics"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Visited his mother",
                  "explanation": "The Bhitari pillar inscription describes Skandagupta visiting his widowed mother after restoring his family's fortunes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was likely Skandagupta's successor according to historical records?",
                  "options": [
                    "Purugupta",
                    "Chandragupta II",
                    "Kumaragupta II",
                    "Harsha"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Purugupta",
                  "explanation": "Historical records suggest that Purugupta, who was probably Skandagupta's younger half-brother, succeeded him."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "How does the Junagarh Rock Inscription challenge the traditional view of Skandagupta's defeat by the Hunas?",
                  "options": [
                    "Skandagupta may not have been defeated.",
                    "Confirms a defeat.",
                    "Shows a victory.",
                    "Indicates an alliance."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Skandagupta may not have been defeated.",
                  "explanation": "The Junagarh Rock Inscription suggests Skandagupta might have resisted the Hunas more successfully than previously thought, challenging the idea of his defeat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What are the limitations of using literary sources alone for understanding the Huna invasions and Skandagupta's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Can be biased.",
                    "Only sources available.",
                    "Provides complete view.",
                    "Less reliable than numismatics."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Can be biased.",
                  "explanation": "Literary sources may be biased or exaggerated, potentially skewing the historical understanding of the invasions and reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How does the Naga-Huna alliance theory challenge the Skandagupta narrative?",
                  "options": [
                    "Implies a coalition.",
                    "Hunas as only foes.",
                    "Excludes Nagas.",
                    "Indicates quick defeat."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Imples a coalition.",
                  "explanation": "It suggests Skandagupta faced a broader coalition, not just the Hunas."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What are the strengths and weaknesses of identifying Prakasaditya as Skandagupta's rival?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strength: Clear rival; Weakness: No direct proof.",
                    "Strength: Numismatic; Weakness: Literary issues.",
                    "Strength: Inscriptions; Weakness: No archaeology.",
                    "Strength: Evidence; Weakness: Debated."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strength: Clear rival; Weakness: No direct proof.",
                  "explanation": "Prakasaditya is a likely rival but lacks direct proof."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How do Ghato coins impact the Skandagupta rival debate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Supports Huna rival.",
                    "No evidence.",
                    "No new insights.",
                    "Confirms rival."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Supports Huna rival.",
                  "explanation": "Ghato coins support the idea of a Huna rival through coin changes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What are the implications of identifying Skandagupta's rival for Gupta politics?",
                  "options": [
                    "Insights on strategies.",
                    "Resolves internal politics.",
                    "Clarifies economics.",
                    "Shows stability."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Insights on strategies.",
                  "explanation": "Helps understand Gupta strategies and external threats."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How does studying the Huna invasions and Skandagupta's reign aid in understanding the Gupta Empire's history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Reveals military challenges.",
                    "Shows cultural achievements.",
                    "Confirms prosperity.",
                    "Indicates stability."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reveals military challenges.",
                  "explanation": "Offers insights into military challenges faced by the Gupta Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How does numismatic evidence relate to the theory of multiple Huna invasions during Skandagupta's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Supports multiple invasions.",
                    "Shows no invasions.",
                    "Contradicts theory.",
                    "Indicates pattern changes."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Supports multiple invasions.",
                  "explanation": "Changes in coinage patterns support the theory of multiple Huna invasions by showing distinct issues related to these events."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What does the debate on the 'serpent kings' reveal about Gupta politics?",
                  "options": [
                    "Highlights complex diplomacy.",
                    "Clarifies enemies.",
                    "Resolves all uncertainties.",
                    "Shows internal strife."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Highlights complex diplomacy.",
                  "explanation": "The debate over the 'serpent kings' illustrates the intricate political dynamics and difficulties in identifying adversaries during Gupta rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How does Skandagupta's coinage analysis help us understand the economic impact of the Huna invasions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Shows economic decline.",
                    "Indicates increased trade.",
                    "No impact shown.",
                    "Suggests economic growth."
                  ],
                  "answer": "Shows economic decline.",
                  "explanation": "Analysis of Skandagupta's coinage indicates economic decline, reflecting instability linked to the Huna invasions."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },

    {
      "topicName": "Delhi Sultanate",
      "subtopics": [
        {
          "subtopicName": "Qutb al-Din Aibak",
          "description": [
            "Qutb al-Din Aibak was the founder of the Mamluk Dynasty and the first Sultan of the Delhi Sultanate.",
            "Originally a slave, he rose to power under Muhammad of Ghor and declared independence after his death in 1206.",
            "Aibak began the construction of the iconic Qutb Minar in Delhi, symbolizing the rise of Islamic rule in India.",
            "Known for his generosity, he earned the title Lakh Baksh (giver of lakhs).",
            "His reign was short, ending abruptly in 1210 due to a horse-riding accident. Despite his brief rule, he laid the foundation for centuries of Muslim rule in India."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was the founder of the Mamluk (Slave) Dynasty in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alauddin Khilji",
                    "Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
                    "Qutub-ud-din Aibak",
                    "Iltutmish"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak was the founder of the Mamluk (Slave) Dynasty in India, establishing rule in 1206."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What title was given to Qutub-ud-din Aibak for his generosity?",
                  "options": ["Sultan", "Malik", "Lakh Baksh", "Shahenshah"],
                  "answer": "Lakh Baksh",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak was known as 'Lakh Baksh' for his generosity, as he was said to have given away lakhs of coins in charity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which monument's construction did Qutub-ud-din Aibak initiate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Humayun’s Tomb",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Taj Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutub Minar",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak started the construction of the Qutub Minar, one of the most famous historical monuments in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak declared himself the Sultan after the death of:",
                  "options": [
                    "Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
                    "Babur",
                    "Muhammad of Ghor",
                    "Alauddin Khilji"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Muhammad of Ghor",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak declared himself Sultan after the death of Muhammad of Ghor, his master."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following is not true about Qutub-ud-din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "He made Delhi his capital.",
                    "He completed the Qutub Minar.",
                    "He was known as Lakh Baksh.",
                    "He died in a horse-riding accident."
                  ],
                  "answer": "He completed the Qutub Minar.",
                  "explanation": "While Qutub-ud-din Aibak initiated the construction of the Qutub Minar, it was completed by his successor, Iltutmish."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutub-ud-din Aibak die?",
                  "options": [
                    "Assassinated by rivals",
                    "Died in battle",
                    "Natural causes",
                    "Died in a horse-riding accident"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Died in a horse-riding accident",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak died in a horse-riding accident while playing polo in 1210."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the original capital of Qutub-ud-din Aibak’s empire?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore", "Multan"],
                  "answer": "Lahore",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak initially ruled from Lahore, which was his original capital before Delhi became prominent."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak is regarded as the first:",
                  "options": [
                    "Mughal Emperor",
                    "Sultan of Delhi",
                    "King of Bengal",
                    "Governor of Gujarat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Sultan of Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak is regarded as the first Sultan of Delhi and established the Mamluk (Slave) Dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Qutub-ud-din Aibak become the ruler of Delhi?",
                  "options": ["1192", "1206", "1236", "1250"],
                  "answer": "1206",
                  "explanation": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak became the ruler of Delhi in 1206 after declaring independence from the Ghurid Empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Qutub-ud-din Aibak started the construction of Qutub Minar to commemorate which Sufi saint?",
                  "options": [
                    "Khwaja Qutbuddin Bakhtiyar Kaki",
                    "Moinuddin Chishti",
                    "Nizamuddin Auliya",
                    "Shah Jalal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Khwaja Qutbuddin Bakhtiyar Kaki",
                  "explanation": "The Qutub Minar was constructed in honor of the Sufi saint Khwaja Qutbuddin Bakhtiyar Kaki."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak's role in Indian history?",
                  "options": [
                    "Founder of the Delhi Sultanate",
                    "Mughal Emperor",
                    "Persian Scholar",
                    "Military General of the Mamluk Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Founder of the Delhi Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak was a prominent figure as the founder of the Delhi Sultanate in Indian history."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the original role of Qutb al-Din Aibak before becoming a ruler?",
                  "options": [
                    "Slave",
                    "Merchant",
                    "Scholar",
                    "Military General"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Slave",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak was originally a slave who rose to power and eventually became the Sultan of Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Qutb al-Din Aibak found?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ghurid Dynasty",
                    "Mamluk Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Gupta Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mamluk Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak founded the Mamluk Dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Qutb al-Din Aibak briefly capture before establishing his rule in Delhi?",
                  "options": ["Lahore", "Multan", "Agra", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Lahore",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak captured Lahore before establishing his rule in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Qutb al-Din Aibak as the ruler of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Iltutmish",
                    "Raziya Sultana",
                    "Alauddin Khilji",
                    "Ghyasuddin Tughlaq"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Iltutmish",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak was succeeded by his son-in-law, Iltutmish, who continued to build on his legacy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "In which year did Qutb al-Din Aibak start his rule in Delhi?",
                  "options": ["1206", "1210", "1225", "1230"],
                  "answer": "1206",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak began his rule in Delhi in the year 1206."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary architectural style of Qutb al-Din Aibak's constructions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Gothic",
                    "Indo-Islamic",
                    "Renaissance",
                    "Baroque"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Indo-Islamic",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak's constructions, including the Qutub Minar, are noted for their Indo-Islamic architectural style."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s notable contribution to architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of Forts",
                    "Building of Canals",
                    "Development of Universities",
                    "Establishment of Libraries"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Construction of Forts",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak made significant contributions to architecture, including the construction of forts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak die?",
                  "options": [
                    "Assassination",
                    "Accident",
                    "Natural Causes",
                    "War Injuries"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Accident",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak died from an accident while playing polo."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which military leader did Qutb al-Din Aibak serve before becoming a ruler?",
                  "options": ["Muhammad Ghori", "Babur", "Akbar", "Shivaji"],
                  "answer": "Muhammad Ghori",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak served under Muhammad Ghori before establishing his own rule."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Qutb al-Din Aibak establish?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mamluk Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Mughal Dynasty",
                    "Gupta Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mamluk Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak founded the Mamluk Dynasty, also known as the Slave Dynasty, in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical figure did Qutb al-Din Aibak defeat to establish his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Prithviraj Chauhan",
                    "Raja Jai Chand",
                    "Shivaji",
                    "Raja Karan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Prithviraj Chauhan",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak defeated Prithviraj Chauhan in the Second Battle of Tarain."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s role before he became Sultan?",
                  "options": ["Commander", "Advisor", "Treasurer", "General"],
                  "answer": "General",
                  "explanation": "Before becoming Sultan, Qutb al-Din Aibak was a general in the army of Muhammad Ghori."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which structure in Delhi is named after Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Humayun's Tomb",
                    "Red Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutb Minar",
                  "explanation": "The Qutb Minar in Delhi is named after Qutb al-Din Aibak, though its construction was completed by his successor."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s policies during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land Reforms",
                    "Tax Reductions",
                    "Expansion of Territory",
                    "Cultural Patronage"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Territory",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak focused on expanding the territory of the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a notable achievement of Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of New Currency",
                    "Building of Qutub Minar",
                    "Establishment of Universities",
                    "Development of Trade Routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building of Qutub Minar",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak is credited with beginning the construction of the Qutub Minar in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Where was Qutb al-Din Aibak originally from?",
                  "options": ["Turkey", "Iran", "India", "Egypt"],
                  "answer": "Turkey",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak was originally from Turkey, where he was born as a slave."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which religious community did Qutb al-Din Aibak primarily engage with during his rule?",
                  "options": ["Hinduism", "Buddhism", "Islam", "Jainism"],
                  "answer": "Islam",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak engaged primarily with the Islamic community during his rule as a Muslim Sultan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the challenges Qutb al-Din Aibak faced during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebellions",
                    "Foreign Invasions",
                    "Economic Decline",
                    "Natural Disasters"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rebellions",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak faced several rebellions and challenges during his reign in establishing control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak's primary contribution to Delhi’s architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fort Construction",
                    "Palace Building",
                    "Religious Structures",
                    "Urban Planning"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious Structures",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s primary architectural contributions in Delhi were religious structures like the Qutb Mosque."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak's relationship with the Ghurid Empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Governor",
                    "Rebel Leader",
                    "Military General",
                    "Trade Partner"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military General",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak served as a military general under the Ghurid Empire before establishing his rule in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural feature is associated with Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign?",
                  "options": ["Dome", "Arch", "Pillar", "Minaret"],
                  "answer": "Minaret",
                  "explanation": "The Qutub Minar, a prominent minaret, is associated with Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the key factors in Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Political Alliances",
                    "Military Conquests",
                    "Economic Policies",
                    "Diplomatic Relations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Conquests",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rise to power was significantly aided by his military conquests and victories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Qutb al-Din Aibak as the ruler of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Iltutmish",
                    "Razia Sultana",
                    "Balban",
                    "Muhammad bin Tughlaq"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Iltutmish",
                  "explanation": "Iltutmish succeeded Qutb al-Din Aibak as the ruler of Delhi after his death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which aspect of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign was criticized by later historians?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military Overreach",
                    "Economic Instability",
                    "Religious Intolerance",
                    "Administrative Inefficiency"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Inefficiency",
                  "explanation": "Later historians often criticized Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign for administrative inefficiencies and lack of proper governance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s policies on the Delhi Sultanate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Consolidation of Power",
                    "Fragmentation",
                    "Economic Prosperity",
                    "Cultural Flourishing"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidation of Power",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s policies contributed to the consolidation of power in the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main purpose of constructing the Qutub Minar?",
                  "options": [
                    "Victory Monument",
                    "Religious Symbol",
                    "Watchtower",
                    "Cultural Center"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Victory Monument",
                  "explanation": "The Qutub Minar was originally constructed as a victory monument to commemorate the victory of Qutb al-Din Aibak."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the beginning of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s dominance in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Tarain",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Khanwa",
                    "Battle of Plassey"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Tarain",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Tarain marked the beginning of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s dominance in India after his victory over Prithviraj Chauhan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major administrative change implemented by Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land Reforms",
                    "Revenue System",
                    "Judicial Reforms",
                    "Taxation System"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Revenue System",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak introduced changes to the revenue system as part of his administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign influence future Delhi Sultans?",
                  "options": [
                    "Set Precedents",
                    "Created Conflict",
                    "Weakened Authority",
                    "Promoted Innovation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Set Precedents",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign set several precedents for future Delhi Sultans in terms of governance and administration."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant challenge faced by Qutb al-Din Aibak during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebellions",
                    "Famine",
                    "Diplomatic Isolation",
                    "Foreign Invasions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rebellions",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak faced significant challenges from internal rebellions during his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a major contribution of Qutb al-Din Aibak to Islamic architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Development of Courtyards",
                    "Expansion of Mosques",
                    "Building of Minarets",
                    "Construction of Palaces"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building of Minarets",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak is known for his contribution to the construction of minarets, particularly the Qutub Minar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the strategic significance of the Qutub Minar in Qutb al-Din Aibak’s era?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military Defense",
                    "Religious Symbolism",
                    "Cultural Landmark",
                    "Administrative Center"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious Symbolism",
                  "explanation": "The Qutub Minar served as a symbol of Islamic dominance and religious significance during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s era."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s approach to integrating diverse cultures in his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Forced Assimilation",
                    "Cultural Tolerance",
                    "Segregation",
                    "Selective Patronage"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cultural Tolerance",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak adopted a policy of cultural tolerance to manage the diverse population of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical figure was a contemporary rival of Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Raja Jai Chand",
                    "Khilji Dynasty",
                    "Muhammad Ghori",
                    "Rajput Kings"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rajput Kings",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak faced rivalries from Rajput kings who resisted his expansion into their territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s primary focus in his administrative reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military Organization",
                    "Revenue Collection",
                    "Land Distribution",
                    "Judicial Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Revenue Collection",
                  "explanation": "One of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s primary focuses in his administrative reforms was the improvement of revenue collection."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What led to the eventual downfall of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Assassination",
                    "Military Defeat",
                    "Internal Strife",
                    "Economic Collapse"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Internal Strife",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule faced internal strife and conflicts that eventually led to his downfall."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Qutb al-Din Aibak establish?",
                  "options": [
                    "Mamluk Dynasty",
                    "Chola Dynasty",
                    "Mughal Dynasty",
                    "Gupta Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Mamluk Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak founded the Mamluk Dynasty, also known as the Slave Dynasty, in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Qutb al-Din Aibak play in the consolidation of Islamic rule in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Founder of the Sultanate",
                    "Religious Reformer",
                    "Military Leader",
                    "Diplomat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Founder of the Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak played a crucial role as the founder of the Delhi Sultanate, consolidating Islamic rule in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the cultural impacts of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promotion of Persian Art",
                    "Spread of Hindu Temples",
                    "Construction of Fortresses",
                    "Establishment of Islamic Schools"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Islamic Schools",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak contributed to the cultural development by establishing Islamic schools and educational institutions."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which historical source provides detailed accounts of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta's Travels",
                    "The Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
                    "Ain-i-Akbari",
                    "The Rajatarangini"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
                  "explanation": "The Tabaqat-i-Nasiri provides detailed historical accounts of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule influence the development of Indo-Islamic architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of Persian Styles",
                    "Fusion of Hindu and Islamic Elements",
                    "Focus on Defensive Structures",
                    "Expansion of Trade Routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fusion of Hindu and Islamic Elements",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule influenced the development of Indo-Islamic architecture by blending Hindu and Islamic architectural elements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What strategic move did Qutb al-Din Aibak make to strengthen his control over northern India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alliances with Rajput Kings",
                    "Military Campaigns in the Deccan",
                    "Establishment of Fortified Cities",
                    "Expansion into Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Fortified Cities",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak strengthened his control by establishing fortified cities and military outposts in northern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule on the regional politics of South Asia?",
                  "options": [
                    "Stabilization of Power Dynamics",
                    "Fragmentation into Smaller States",
                    "Increased Trade and Diplomacy",
                    "Cultural Renaissance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Stabilization of Power Dynamics",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule contributed to the stabilization of power dynamics in South Asia by consolidating the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural feature in the Qutub Minar reflects the influence of Persian design?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decorative Inscriptions",
                    "Columnar Structure",
                    "Calligraphic Carvings",
                    "Dome Design"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decorative Inscriptions",
                  "explanation": "The decorative inscriptions in the Qutub Minar reflect Persian design influences in its architecture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What were the main reasons behind the internal conflicts during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Succession Disputes",
                    "Economic Disparities",
                    "Religious Differences",
                    "Military Defeats"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Succession Disputes",
                  "explanation": "Internal conflicts during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule were primarily due to succession disputes and challenges to his authority."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Persian historian’s work provides insights into Qutb al-Din Aibak’s administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Juzjani",
                    "Ibn Khaldun",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Firdawsi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Juzjani",
                  "explanation": "The Persian historian Juzjani’s work provides valuable insights into Qutb al-Din Aibak’s administration and rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak handle the administrative challenges of ruling a diverse empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized Bureaucracy",
                    "Delegation to Local Rulers",
                    "Imposition of Uniform Laws",
                    "Promotion of Local Leaders"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Delegation to Local Rulers",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak managed administrative challenges by delegating authority to local rulers and regional governors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major architectural innovation introduced during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Use of Red Stone",
                    "Intricate Tile Work",
                    "Supportive Arches",
                    "Ornamental Domes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Supportive Arches",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign saw the introduction of supportive arches in architecture, particularly in the Qutub Minar."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Qutb al-Din Aibak play in the military campaigns of his time?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strategist",
                    "Field Commander",
                    "Diplomat",
                    "Logistician"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strategist",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak played a key role as a strategist in the military campaigns that expanded and consolidated the Delhi Sultanate."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s role in the administration of the Ghurid Empire before his ascension?",
                  "options": [
                    "Governor",
                    "Military General",
                    "Diplomatic Envoy",
                    "Chief Treasurer"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Governor",
                  "explanation": "Before his ascension, Qutb al-Din Aibak served as a governor in the Ghurid Empire, managing territories on behalf of his masters."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historical account describes the architectural contributions of Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Delhi Chronicle",
                    "Tarikh-i-Firoz Shahi",
                    "Ain-i-Akbari",
                    "Khazain-ul-Futuh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Khazain-ul-Futuh",
                  "explanation": "Khazain-ul-Futuh provides historical accounts of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural contributions and rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant military achievement of Qutb al-Din Aibak that helped establish his power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Victory at the Battle of Panipat",
                    "Conquest of Kanauj",
                    "Defeat of Rajput Forces",
                    "Annexation of Bengal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defeat of Rajput Forces",
                  "explanation": "The defeat of Rajput forces, particularly during the Second Battle of Tarain, was a significant military achievement that helped Qutb al-Din Aibak establish his power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the strategic significance of Delhi for Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Economic Hub",
                    "Military Base",
                    "Cultural Center",
                    "Religious Sanctuary"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Base",
                  "explanation": "Delhi was strategically significant as a military base for Qutb al-Din Aibak, allowing him to control northern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural projects was completed by his successors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Humayun’s Tomb",
                    "Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutub Minar",
                  "explanation": "The Qutub Minar, initiated by Qutb al-Din Aibak, was completed by his successors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major factor in the consolidation of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s power in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Religious Reforms",
                    "Military Alliances",
                    "Economic Policies",
                    "Administrative Reorganization"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Reorganization",
                  "explanation": "Administrative reorganization played a crucial role in consolidating Qutb al-Din Aibak’s power in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak’s approach to governance influence subsequent rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized Authority",
                    "Decentralized Administration",
                    "Economic Autonomy",
                    "Military Expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Authority",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s approach to governance set a precedent for centralized authority that influenced subsequent rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s death on the Delhi Sultanate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Power Struggles",
                    "Immediate Collapse",
                    "Continued Stability",
                    "Cultural Flourishing"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Power Struggles",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s death led to power struggles and instability within the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Qutb al-Din Aibak focus on expanding during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Central India",
                    "South India",
                    "Eastern India",
                    "Northern India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northern India",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak focused on expanding his control over northern India during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary architectural style used in the construction of Qutb Minar?",
                  "options": ["Gothic", "Persian", "Romanesque", "Mughal"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "The architectural style of the Qutb Minar is primarily influenced by Persian designs and aesthetics."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was a major political challenge faced by Qutb al-Din Aibak during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Regional Rebellions",
                    "Economic Collapse",
                    "Foreign Invasions",
                    "Religious Uprisings"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Regional Rebellions",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak faced regional rebellions as a major political challenge during his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Qutb al-Din Aibak play in the development of Islamic culture in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Patron of Arts",
                    "Religious Reformer",
                    "Educational Leader",
                    "Military Strategist"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Patron of Arts",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak was a patron of the arts, contributing to the development of Islamic culture in India through architectural projects."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What architectural feature is characteristic of the Qutb Minar’s design?",
                  "options": [
                    "Islamic Calligraphy",
                    "Intricate Carvings",
                    "Large Dome",
                    "Mosaic Patterns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Islamic Calligraphy",
                  "explanation": "The Qutb Minar is characterized by its Islamic calligraphy and intricate carvings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important mosque did Qutb al-Din Aibak commission during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Jama Masjid",
                    "Qutb Mosque",
                    "Badshahi Mosque",
                    "Hawa Mahal"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutb Mosque",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak commissioned the Qutb Mosque, which is an important religious site in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak influence the military structure of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Formation of Elite Guard",
                    "Use of Gunpowder Artillery",
                    "Introduction of Cavalry Units",
                    "Establishment of Standing Army"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Standing Army",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak established a standing army to strengthen the military structure of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Qutb al-Din Aibak's foreign policy?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion into Southern India",
                    "Diplomatic Relations with Central Asia",
                    "Control of Trade Routes",
                    "Consolidation of Northern Territories"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Consolidation of Northern Territories",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak's foreign policy primarily focused on consolidating control over northern territories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was a major architectural innovation during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Multi-Storied Towers",
                    "Elaborate Courtyards",
                    "Columned Arches",
                    "Domed Vaults"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Columned Arches",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak's reign saw the introduction of columned arches in architectural structures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant economic measure implemented by Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tax Reforms",
                    "Land Redistribution",
                    "Currency Standardization",
                    "Trade Enhancements"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tax Reforms",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak implemented tax reforms to improve the economic stability of his administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s contribution to the Islamic scholarly community?",
                  "options": [
                    "Founding of Libraries",
                    "Sponsoring Scholars",
                    "Establishing Islamic Schools",
                    "Promoting Translations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishing Islamic Schools",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak contributed to the Islamic scholarly community by establishing Islamic schools."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Qutb al-Din Aibak prioritize for military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Deccan Plateau",
                    "Western India",
                    "Northern India",
                    "Southern India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Northern India",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak prioritized northern India for military campaigns to consolidate his rule."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural style on later Islamic architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of Minarets",
                    "Use of Brickwork",
                    "Incorporation of Persian Elements",
                    "Development of Vaulted Structures"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Incorporation of Persian Elements",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural style influenced later Islamic architecture through the incorporation of Persian elements."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian’s work provides a detailed account of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s military campaigns?",
                  "options": ["Ibn Battuta", "Barani", "Juzjani", "Firdawsi"],
                  "answer": "Barani",
                  "explanation": "The historian Barani provides detailed accounts of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant challenge faced by Qutb al-Din Aibak in consolidating his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Resistance from Local Rulers",
                    "Economic Decline",
                    "Religious Discord",
                    "External Invasions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Resistance from Local Rulers",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak faced significant resistance from local rulers while consolidating his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Qutb al-Din Aibak’s primary strategy for maintaining control over newly acquired territories?",
                  "options": [
                    "Garrisoning Troops",
                    "Economic Incentives",
                    "Marital Alliances",
                    "Religious Conversions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Garrisoning Troops",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak maintained control over newly acquired territories primarily by garrisoning troops."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign affect the socio-economic conditions in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Economic Growth",
                    "Social Unrest",
                    "Cultural Decline",
                    "Administrative Efficiency"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Efficiency",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign contributed to improved administrative efficiency in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which military campaign was pivotal in establishing Qutb al-Din Aibak’s dominance in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Campaign in Bengal",
                    "Conquest of Kanauj",
                    "Battle of Tarain",
                    "Invasion of Gujarat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Tarain",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Tarain was pivotal in establishing Qutb al-Din Aibak’s dominance in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important historical text details the architectural innovations during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Tarikh-i-Firoz Shahi",
                    "The Ain-i-Akbari",
                    "The Khazain-ul-Futuh",
                    "The Delhi Chronicle"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Khazain-ul-Futuh",
                  "explanation": "The Khazain-ul-Futuh details the architectural innovations during Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a key feature of the Qutb Minar that influenced subsequent Islamic architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Decorative Calligraphy",
                    "Red Sandstone Construction",
                    "Large Dome",
                    "Multiple Stories"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decorative Calligraphy",
                  "explanation": "The decorative calligraphy of the Qutb Minar influenced subsequent Islamic architecture."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Qutb al-Din Aibak play in the development of Islamic jurisprudence in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Formation of Legal Institutions",
                    "Promotion of Religious Law",
                    "Codification of Islamic Law",
                    "Establishment of Courts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Formation of Legal Institutions",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak contributed to the development of Islamic jurisprudence by forming legal institutions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which aspect of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s military strategy was crucial for his success?",
                  "options": [
                    "Surprise Attacks",
                    "Siege Warfare",
                    "Naval Power",
                    "Alliances with Local Rulers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Siege Warfare",
                  "explanation": "Siege warfare was a crucial aspect of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s military strategy for his success."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 10,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak secure the support of the local population during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Through Patronage",
                    "By Economic Incentives",
                    "Religious Reforms",
                    "Cultural Integration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Through Patronage",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak secured local support through patronage of local leaders and scholars."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important battle did Qutb al-Din Aibak win to consolidate his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Chandawar",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Tarain",
                    "Battle of Kanauj"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Chandawar",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Chandawar was crucial for consolidating Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule in India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major feature of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural contributions in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Use of Red Sandstone",
                    "Innovative Minarets",
                    "Large Dome Structures",
                    "Intricate Mosaic Work"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Use of Red Sandstone",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s architectural contributions in Delhi prominently featured the use of red sandstone."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Qutb al-Din Aibak establish the foundation for?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Mamluk Dynasty",
                    "The Khilji Dynasty",
                    "The Tughlaq Dynasty",
                    "The Lodi Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Mamluk Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak established the foundation for the Mamluk Dynasty, also known as the Slave Dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a significant challenge in managing the diverse population of Delhi under Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Religious Diversity",
                    "Economic Disparities",
                    "Language Barriers",
                    "Political Factions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Religious Diversity",
                  "explanation": "Managing religious diversity was a significant challenge for Qutb al-Din Aibak in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key administrative reform was introduced by Qutb al-Din Aibak?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of New Taxation System",
                    "Reorganization of Military Units",
                    "Reform of Judicial System",
                    "Standardization of Currency"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reorganization of Military Units",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak introduced significant reforms in the organization of military units."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the architectural legacies of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s reign that influenced later periods?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of Large Minarets",
                    "Development of Persian Gardens",
                    "Adoption of Dome Structures",
                    "Expansion of Fortifications"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Construction of Large Minarets",
                  "explanation": "The construction of large minarets, such as the Qutb Minar, influenced architectural styles in later periods."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Qutb al-Din Aibak contribute to the cultural landscape of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Promotion of Persian Culture",
                    "Support for Local Festivals",
                    "Sponsorship of Scholars",
                    "Development of Trade Routes"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Promotion of Persian Culture",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak promoted Persian culture, which significantly influenced the cultural landscape of Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a strategic advantage of Qutb al-Din Aibak’s rule over Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control of Major Trade Routes",
                    "Alliance with Mongol Tribes",
                    "Access to Maritime Trade",
                    "Strategic Location in North India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strategic Location in North India",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak’s strategic location in North India provided a significant advantage for his rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Qutb al-Din Aibak play in the establishment of Islamic governance in India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of Administrative Structures",
                    "Introduction of Islamic Law",
                    "Formation of a Centralized Bureaucracy",
                    "Development of Religious Institutions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Administrative Structures",
                  "explanation": "Qutb al-Din Aibak played a key role in establishing administrative structures for Islamic governance in India."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Alauddin Khilji",
          "description": [
            "Alauddin Khilji was the most powerful ruler of the Khilji Dynasty and reigned over the Delhi Sultanate from 1296 to 1316.",
            "He is known for his military conquests and significant administrative reforms.",
            " Alauddin expanded the Sultanate's territory by defeating the Rajput kingdoms and conquering parts of southern India.",
            " He is also credited with defending India from repeated Mongol invasions, making the Delhi Sultanate a powerful and secure state."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who was Alauddin Khilji's predecessor as the Sultan of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutb-ud-din Aibak",
                    "Iltutmish",
                    "Raziya Sultana",
                    "Jalal-ud-din Khilji"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Jalal-ud-din Khilji",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji succeeded his uncle Jalal-ud-din Khilji as the Sultan of Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous market reform was introduced by Alauddin Khilji?",
                  "options": [
                    "Hamaam",
                    "Sarai",
                    "Market Control Measures",
                    "Tax Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Market Control Measures",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented market control measures to regulate prices and prevent hoarding."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's approach to military expansion?",
                  "options": [
                    "Diplomatic Alliances",
                    "Military Campaigns",
                    "Marriages",
                    "Peace Treaties"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Campaigns",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji focused on military campaigns to expand his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Alauddin Khilji successfully conquer during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Bengal",
                    "Deccan Plateau",
                    "South India",
                    "North-West Frontier"
                  ],
                  "answer": "South India",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's empire extended into South India through successful military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Persian poet wrote about Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": ["Rumi", "Omar Khayyam", "Firdawsi", "Saadi"],
                  "answer": "Firdawsi",
                  "explanation": "Firdawsi, a Persian poet, wrote about the events during Alauddin Khilji's reign in his epic, Shahnameh."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of the 'Hamaam' system introduced by Alauddin Khilji?",
                  "options": [
                    "Public Baths",
                    "Military Barracks",
                    "Trade Centers",
                    "Administrative Offices"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public Baths",
                  "explanation": "The 'Hamaam' system introduced by Alauddin Khilji was aimed at providing public baths."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city was the capital of Alauddin Khilji's empire?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Delhi",
                  "explanation": "Delhi was the capital of Alauddin Khilji's empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major architectural project is attributed to Alauddin Khilji?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Alai Darwaza",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "The Alai Darwaza is a major architectural project attributed to Alauddin Khilji."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous battle did Alauddin Khilji win against the Rajput kings?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Chandawar",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Tarain",
                    "Battle of Plassey"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Chandawar",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji won the Battle of Chandawar against the Rajput kings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was Alauddin Khilji's chief minister known for administrative reforms?",
                  "options": ["Khilji", "Iltutmish", "Junaid", "Bairam Khan"],
                  "answer": "Junaid",
                  "explanation": "Junaid was Alauddin Khilji's chief minister and known for his administrative reforms."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's real name before he became Sultan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Khusrau Malik",
                    "Alauddin Firuz",
                    "Khilji Malik",
                    "Sultan Shihabuddin"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alauddin Firuz",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's real name was Alauddin Firuz before he became Sultan Alauddin Khilji."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Alauddin Khilji belong to?",
                  "options": ["Mughal", "Khilji", "Lodi", "Tughlaq"],
                  "answer": "Khilji",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji belonged to the Khilji dynasty, which ruled the Delhi Sultanate."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which event marked Alauddin Khilji's rise to power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Assassination of his uncle",
                    "Defeat of the Mongols",
                    "Marriage Alliance",
                    "Victory in the Battle of Panipat"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Assassination of his uncle",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji rose to power after the assassination of his uncle, Jalaluddin Khilji, the founder of the Khilji dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Alauddin Khilji's major administrative reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of the Iqta System",
                    "Centralized Market Regulation",
                    "Land Tax Reforms",
                    "Military Conscription"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Market Regulation",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented centralized market regulation to control prices and prevent hoarding."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Indian poet and scholar lived during Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Ameer Khusro",
                    "Aryabhata"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ameer Khusro",
                  "explanation": "Ameer Khusro, a renowned poet and scholar, lived during Alauddin Khilji's reign and contributed significantly to Persian and Hindi literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's approach towards the regional rulers?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alliance Building",
                    "Diplomatic Negotiations",
                    "Military Conquests",
                    "Autonomous Administration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Conquests",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji preferred military conquests to bring regional rulers under his control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which structure in Delhi was known for its intricate design and was built by Alauddin Khilji?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alai Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Minar",
                  "explanation": "The Alai Minar, built by Alauddin Khilji, is known for its intricate architectural design."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's policy regarding the collection of land revenue?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fixed Tax Rate",
                    "Percentage-Based Tax",
                    "Land Reforms",
                    "Revenue Redistribution"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fixed Tax Rate",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented a fixed tax rate system for land revenue to increase state revenue."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Alauddin Khilji as the Sultan of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutbuddin Mubarak Shah",
                    "Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
                    "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
                    "Iltutmish"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutbuddin Mubarak Shah",
                  "explanation": "Qutbuddin Mubarak Shah, Alauddin Khilji's nephew, succeeded him as the Sultan of Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Alauddin Khilji's achievements in architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Construction of the Qutb Minar",
                    "Expansion of the Red Fort",
                    "Completion of the Alai Darwaza",
                    "Restoration of Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Completion of the Alai Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji completed the Alai Darwaza, an architectural achievement of his reign."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following reforms was implemented by Alauddin Khilji to control the prices of goods?",
                  "options": [
                    "Price Control Measures",
                    "Agricultural Reforms",
                    "Currency Reforms",
                    "Land Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Control Measures",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented price control measures to regulate and stabilize the market."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the strategic importance of Alauddin Khilji's conquest of the Deccan region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control of Trade Routes",
                    "Expansion into China",
                    "Establishment of Trade with Europe",
                    "Cultural Exchange"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control of Trade Routes",
                  "explanation": "The conquest of the Deccan region was strategically important for controlling trade routes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Alauddin Khilji defeat to establish his rule over northern India?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Chola Dynasty",
                    "The Rajput Dynasty",
                    "The Ghurid Dynasty",
                    "The Mamluk Dynasty"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Rajput Dynasty",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji defeated the Rajput Dynasty to establish his dominance over northern India."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which system did Alauddin Khilji implement to ensure the efficiency of his army?",
                  "options": [
                    "Barid-i-Mamalik",
                    "Iqta System",
                    "Tughlaq System",
                    "Salar-i-Mamlik"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Barid-i-Mamalik",
                  "explanation": "The Barid-i-Mamalik system was implemented by Alauddin Khilji to ensure the efficiency of his army."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's major military campaign against the Mongols known for?",
                  "options": [
                    "Defensive Strategy",
                    "Treaty of Peace",
                    "Alliance Formation",
                    "Cultural Assimilation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Defensive Strategy",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji is known for his defensive strategy against the Mongol invasions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural structure did Alauddin Khilji build to commemorate his victory?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alai Minar",
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Tomb of Iltutmish"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Minar",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji built the Alai Minar to commemorate his military victories."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What role did Alauddin Khilji play in the development of urban infrastructure?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of Cities",
                    "Construction of Forts",
                    "Development of Roads",
                    "Establishment of Trade Centers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Cities",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji focused on the expansion and development of cities during his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous traveler visited Alauddin Khilji's court and described the grandeur of his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Ferdinand Magellan"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Battuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Battuta, the famous traveler, visited Alauddin Khilji's court and described the grandeur of his reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the purpose of Alauddin Khilji's 'Darbars'?",
                  "options": [
                    "Public Audiences",
                    "Military Strategy Meetings",
                    "Religious Ceremonies",
                    "Cultural Festivals"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Public Audiences",
                  "explanation": "The 'Darbars' were public audiences held by Alauddin Khilji to address his subjects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the major challenges faced by Alauddin Khilji during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebellion by Nobles",
                    "Invasion by the Mughals",
                    "Economic Instability",
                    "Religious Conflicts"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rebellion by Nobles",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji faced significant challenges, including rebellion from his own nobles."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which administration reform was introduced by Alauddin Khilji to monitor the revenue system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Iqta System",
                    "Maqta System",
                    "Darbari System",
                    "Muqtis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Muqtis",
                  "explanation": "The Muqtis system was introduced by Alauddin Khilji to monitor and manage the revenue collection process."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important aspect of Alauddin Khilji's reign involved reforms in the army?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of the Cavalry",
                    "Reduction of the Infantry",
                    "Introduction of New Weaponry",
                    "Increased Soldier Salaries"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased Soldier Salaries",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented reforms to increase the salaries of soldiers to maintain a loyal and effective army."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous traveler from the 14th century described the grandeur of Alauddin Khilji's court?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Christopher Columbus",
                    "Vasco da Gama"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Battuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Battuta, a famous 14th-century traveler, described the grandeur and opulence of Alauddin Khilji's court."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary purpose of Alauddin Khilji's tax reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increase Revenue",
                    "Simplify Tax Collection",
                    "Promote Trade",
                    "Reduce Corruption"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increase Revenue",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's tax reforms were primarily aimed at increasing the revenue for the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural marvel was commissioned by Alauddin Khilji as part of his expansion projects?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alai Minar",
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Minar",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji commissioned the construction of the Alai Minar as part of his expansion and architectural projects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main feature of Alauddin Khilji's fortifications in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "High Walls",
                    "Moats",
                    "Multiple Gates",
                    "Defensive Towers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "High Walls",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's fortifications in Delhi featured high walls to protect the city from invaders."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which event marked the decline of Alauddin Khilji's power?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebellion by Nobles",
                    "Mongol Invasion",
                    "Economic Collapse",
                    "Religious Uprisings"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rebellion by Nobles",
                  "explanation": "The decline of Alauddin Khilji's power was marked by rebellion from his own nobles."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who led the first Mongol invasion during Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Changez Khan",
                    "Jalaluddin",
                    "Tarmashirin",
                    "Qutlugh Khwaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutlugh Khwaja",
                  "explanation": "Qutlugh Khwaja led the first Mongol invasion during Alauddin Khilji's reign, but it was successfully repelled."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major economic reform is Alauddin Khilji known for?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abolishing the Jizya tax",
                    "Market price control",
                    "Free trade policies",
                    "Land redistribution"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Market price control",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji is well-known for implementing market price control to regulate food prices and stabilize the economy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which southern kingdom did Alauddin Khilji’s general, Malik Kafur, defeat?",
                  "options": ["Chola", "Vijayanagara", "Hoysala", "Yadava"],
                  "answer": "Yadava",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's general, Malik Kafur, defeated the Yadava kingdom during his southern campaigns."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What significant change did Alauddin Khilji make to the coinage system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of Silver Tanka",
                    "Elimination of Copper Coins",
                    "Standardization of Weights",
                    "Gold Coins Only"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Introduction of Silver Tanka",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji introduced the silver tanka to standardize currency and control inflation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which prominent historian was a contemporary of Alauddin Khilji and wrote about his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Ziauddin Barani",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Ibn Khaldun"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ziauddin Barani",
                  "explanation": "Ziauddin Barani was a contemporary historian who wrote extensively about Alauddin Khilji's administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Alauddin Khilji handle the issue of famine during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Food Distribution Programs",
                    "Import of Grain",
                    "Reduction of Taxes",
                    "Price Regulation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Regulation",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji regulated prices to manage the effects of famine and ensure affordable food."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Alauddin Khilji's military strategies to maintain his empire's stability?",
                  "options": [
                    "Frequent Wars",
                    "Diplomatic Alliances",
                    "Marriages with Regional Rulers",
                    "Establishment of Garrison Towns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Garrison Towns",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji established garrison towns to ensure military control and stability within his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which notable construction project was initiated by Alauddin Khilji to improve Delhi's defenses?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of the Qutb Minar",
                    "Building of the Siri Fort",
                    "Reconstruction of the Red Fort",
                    "Development of the Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Building of the Siri Fort",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji initiated the building of the Siri Fort to improve the defense of Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's approach towards the Hindu temples in his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Protection",
                    "Destruction",
                    "Reconstruction",
                    "Monetary Taxation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Destruction",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji is known for his policy of destroying Hindu temples as part of his administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant Persian work provides detailed insights into Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
                    "Al-Kamil fi al-Tarikh",
                    "Shahnameh",
                    "Jami' al-Tawarikh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
                  "explanation": "The Tabaqat-i-Nasiri provides detailed insights into Alauddin Khilji's reign and administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Alauddin Khilji's policy towards foreign merchants?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tax Exemption",
                    "Price Regulation",
                    "Trade Expansion",
                    "Currency Control"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Regulation",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's policy towards foreign merchants primarily focused on price regulation and control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous poet and musician lived during Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Kalidasa",
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Ameer Khusro",
                    "Tulsidas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ameer Khusro",
                  "explanation": "Ameer Khusro, a famous poet and musician, lived during Alauddin Khilji's reign and made significant contributions to Persian and Hindi literature."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle solidified Alauddin Khilji's control over the Deccan region?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Warangal",
                    "Battle of Talikota",
                    "Battle of Chandawar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Warangal",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Warangal was a significant victory for Alauddin Khilji, solidifying his control over the Deccan region."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which unique feature distinguished Alauddin Khilji's palace architecture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Use of Marble",
                    "Innovative Water Systems",
                    "Extensive Use of Gold",
                    "Multi-Storied Buildings"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Innovative Water Systems",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's palace architecture was distinguished by its innovative water systems, including aqueducts and fountains."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Alauddin Khilji's reforms on the military?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Salaries",
                    "Professionalization",
                    "Expansion of Territories",
                    "Reduction of Size"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Professionalization",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's reforms led to the professionalization of the military, improving its efficiency and effectiveness."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main source of revenue for Alauddin Khilji’s treasury?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land Revenue",
                    "Trade Taxes",
                    "Tribute from Vassals",
                    "Booty from Conquests"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land Revenue",
                  "explanation": "Land revenue was the main source of revenue for Alauddin Khilji's treasury, due to his reforms in tax collection."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural project did Alauddin Khilji undertake to celebrate his victory over the Rajputs?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alai Darwaza",
                    "Qutb Minar Extension",
                    "Red Fort Construction",
                    "Jama Masjid"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji undertook the construction of the Alai Darwaza to commemorate his victory over the Rajputs."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian’s account is crucial for understanding Alauddin Khilji's economic policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Ziauddin Barani",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Ibn Khaldun"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ziauddin Barani",
                  "explanation": "Ziauddin Barani’s historical account is crucial for understanding the economic policies and administration of Alauddin Khilji."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What strategy did Alauddin Khilji use to control the prices of essential goods?",
                  "options": [
                    "Price Capping",
                    "Government Subsidies",
                    "Import Restrictions",
                    "Market Surveillance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Capping",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji used price capping as a strategy to control the prices of essential goods and prevent inflation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major region did Alauddin Khilji attempt to conquer but faced significant resistance?",
                  "options": ["Gujarat", "Bengal", "Maharashtra", "Punjab"],
                  "answer": "Gujarat",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji attempted to conquer Gujarat but faced strong resistance from the local rulers."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Alauddin Khilji ensure the loyalty of his military commanders?",
                  "options": [
                    "Regular Salaries",
                    "Personal Rewards",
                    "Land Grants",
                    "Political Marriages"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Regular Salaries",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji ensured the loyalty of his military commanders through regular salaries and payments."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant reform did Alauddin Khilji implement to increase the efficiency of his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized Bureaucracy",
                    "Local Autonomy",
                    "Decentralized Governance",
                    "Feudal System"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Bureaucracy",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented a centralized bureaucracy to increase the efficiency of his administration and control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major result of Alauddin Khilji's invasions of southern India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Annexation of Territories",
                    "Establishment of Trade Routes",
                    "Cultural Exchange",
                    "Religious Conversion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Annexation of Territories",
                  "explanation": "The major result of Alauddin Khilji's invasions of southern India was the annexation of territories into his empire."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's strategy to suppress the nobility and ensure loyalty?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralization of Power",
                    "Empowering Local Rulers",
                    "Establishment of a Secret Police",
                    "Religious Reform"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralization of Power",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji centralized power to suppress the nobility and ensure their loyalty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following regions was not part of Alauddin Khilji's empire?",
                  "options": ["Sindh", "Kashmir", "Gujarat", "Bengal"],
                  "answer": "Bengal",
                  "explanation": "Bengal was not part of Alauddin Khilji's empire; his empire extended to other regions such as Sindh, Kashmir, and Gujarat."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle marked the high point of Alauddin Khilji's military expansion?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Amroha",
                    "Battle of Chittorgarh",
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Delhi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Chittorgarh",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Chittorgarh was a significant battle marking the high point of Alauddin Khilji's military expansion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's policy towards trade and merchants?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tax Exemptions",
                    "Heavy Taxation",
                    "Trade Restrictions",
                    "Currency Devaluation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Heavy Taxation",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji imposed heavy taxation on trade and merchants to control the economy and increase revenue."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which historian wrote a detailed account of Alauddin Khilji's administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ziauddin Barani",
                    "Ibn Khaldun",
                    "Al-Masudi",
                    "Ameer Khusro"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ziauddin Barani",
                  "explanation": "Ziauddin Barani wrote a detailed account of Alauddin Khilji's administration in his historical work."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary objective of Alauddin Khilji's market reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Price Regulation",
                    "Trade Promotion",
                    "Currency Stabilization",
                    "Land Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Regulation",
                  "explanation": "The primary objective of Alauddin Khilji's market reforms was to regulate and stabilize prices."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Alauddin Khilji's policies led to significant economic control and administrative efficiency?",
                  "options": [
                    "Price Control Measures",
                    "Land Revenue System",
                    "Military Reforms",
                    "Judicial Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Price Control Measures",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's price control measures contributed significantly to economic control and administrative efficiency."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the reason for Alauddin Khilji's aggressive military campaigns in South India?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control of Trade Routes",
                    "Expansion of Territory",
                    "Religious Conversion",
                    "Political Alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control of Trade Routes",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's aggressive military campaigns in South India aimed to control important trade routes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major economic reform is Alauddin Khilji known for?",
                  "options": [
                    "Abolishing the Jizya tax",
                    "Market price control",
                    "Free trade policies",
                    "Land redistribution"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Market price control",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji is well-known for implementing market price control to regulate food prices and stabilize the economy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Alauddin Khilji's stance on the Mongol invasions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Negotiation",
                    "Military Defense",
                    "Alliance Formation",
                    "Economic Sanctions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Defense",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji took a strong stance against Mongol invasions through military defense strategies."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which ancient structure in Delhi was enhanced under Alauddin Khilji's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Alai Darwaza",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "The Alai Darwaza, part of the Qutb complex, was enhanced and expanded under Alauddin Khilji's rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which system was introduced by Alauddin Khilji to check the corruption in his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Secret Police",
                    "Central Audit System",
                    "Revenue Inspection Teams",
                    "Judicial Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Secret Police",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji introduced a secret police system to monitor and control corruption within his administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of the following was not a primary focus of Alauddin Khilji's economic policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Price Control",
                    "Revenue Maximization",
                    "Land Redistribution",
                    "Trade Expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land Redistribution",
                  "explanation": "Land redistribution was not a primary focus of Alauddin Khilji's economic policies; his policies concentrated on price control, revenue maximization, and trade expansion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Alauddin Khilji's policies aimed to control the wealth of his court nobility?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land Reforms",
                    "Price Control",
                    "Treasury Regulations",
                    "Marriage Restrictions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Marriage Restrictions",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji imposed marriage restrictions on his court nobility to control and reduce their wealth and power."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which battle did Alauddin Khilji fight to suppress a Rajput rebellion?",
                  "options": [
                    "Battle of Panipat",
                    "Battle of Warangal",
                    "Battle of Ranthambore",
                    "Battle of Chandawar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Battle of Ranthambore",
                  "explanation": "The Battle of Ranthambore was fought by Alauddin Khilji to suppress a Rajput rebellion."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Persian historian provided a critical view of Alauddin Khilji's rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ziauddin Barani",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Ibn Khaldun",
                    "Ibn Battuta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ziauddin Barani",
                  "explanation": "Ziauddin Barani provided a critical and detailed view of Alauddin Khilji's rule in his historical writings."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main objective of Alauddin Khilji's military campaigns in Gujarat?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control of Trade Routes",
                    "Territorial Expansion",
                    "Religious Conversion",
                    "Economic Exploitation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control of Trade Routes",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's military campaigns in Gujarat were primarily aimed at controlling important trade routes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Alauddin Khilji's administrative reforms on the local zamindars?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Autonomy",
                    "Decreased Power",
                    "Enhanced Revenue Collection",
                    "Rebellion Encouragement"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decreased Power",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's administrative reforms decreased the power of local zamindars and centralized control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Persian architectural style influenced the construction projects under Alauddin Khilji?",
                  "options": ["Gothic", "Romanesque", "Persian", "Mughal"],
                  "answer": "Persian",
                  "explanation": "The Persian architectural style significantly influenced the construction projects during Alauddin Khilji's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the major reasons for Alauddin Khilji's successful administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strict Law Enforcement",
                    "Cultural Patronage",
                    "Economic Isolation",
                    "Diplomatic Alliances"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strict Law Enforcement",
                  "explanation": "Strict law enforcement and centralization of power were major reasons for the successful administration of Alauddin Khilji."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Who led the first Mongol invasion during Alauddin Khilji's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Changez Khan",
                    "Jalaluddin",
                    "Tarmashirin",
                    "Qutlugh Khwaja"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Qutlugh Khwaja",
                  "explanation": "Qutlugh Khwaja led the first Mongol invasion during Alauddin Khilji's reign, but it was successfully repelled."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the key features of Alauddin Khilji's land revenue system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fixed Revenue Assessment",
                    "Revenue Sharing",
                    "Tax-Free Land",
                    "Variable Tax Rates"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Fixed Revenue Assessment",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji implemented a fixed revenue assessment system to standardize tax collection and increase state revenue."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Alauddin Khilji successfully annex during his campaigns in the south?",
                  "options": [
                    "Karnataka",
                    "Tamil Nadu",
                    "Andhra Pradesh",
                    "Kerala"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Karnataka",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji successfully annexed parts of Karnataka during his southern campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main purpose of Alauddin Khilji’s market control reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Control Inflation",
                    "Promote Trade",
                    "Increase Revenue",
                    "Support Farmers"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Control Inflation",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji’s market control reforms were aimed at controlling inflation and stabilizing the economy."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important structure was built by Alauddin Khilji to commemorate his victories in the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Alai Darwaza",
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                    "Hauz Khas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Alai Darwaza",
                  "explanation": "The Alai Darwaza was built by Alauddin Khilji to commemorate his victories and to serve as an entrance to the fortified city."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Alauddin Khilji's diplomatic relations?",
                  "options": [
                    "Trade Alliances",
                    "Military Pacts",
                    "Cultural Exchange",
                    "Political Marriages"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Military Pacts",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji focused on military pacts and alliances to secure his empire's borders and strengthen his position."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Alauddin Khilji address the issue of corruption within his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Regular Inspections",
                    "Increased Salaries",
                    "Strict Penalties",
                    "Transparency Measures"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strict Penalties",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji addressed corruption by enforcing strict penalties and monitoring officials closely."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which southern kingdom did Alauddin Khilji’s general, Malik Kafur, defeat?",
                  "options": ["Chola", "Vijayanagara", "Hoysala", "Yadava"],
                  "answer": "Yadava",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's general, Malik Kafur, defeated the Yadava kingdom during his southern campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which key administrative reform did Alauddin Khilji implement to enhance military efficiency?",
                  "options": [
                    "Creation of a Standing Army",
                    "Introduction of Military Uniforms",
                    "Standardization of Weaponry",
                    "Establishment of Garrison Towns"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Garrison Towns",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji established garrison towns to enhance military efficiency and ensure strategic control over his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant impact did Alauddin Khilji’s reign have on the cultural life of Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Cultural Flourishing",
                    "Cultural Suppression",
                    "Cultural Exchange",
                    "Cultural Decline"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Cultural Flourishing",
                  "explanation": "Alauddin Khilji's reign saw a flourishing of culture, including contributions from poets like Ameer Khusro and advancements in architecture."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        },

        {
          "subtopicName": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
          "description": [
            "Muhammad bin Tughlaq was the Sultan of the Delhi Sultanate from 1325 to 1351, belonging to the Tughlaq Dynasty.",
            "He is often remembered for his ambitious but controversial reforms and decisions, which ultimately led to instability in the empire.",
            " Known for his intelligence and vision, he attempted several bold projects, though many of them failed due to poor execution."
          ],
          "questionSets": [
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 1,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Muhammad bin Tughlaq's original name before he became Sultan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
                    "Muhammad Shah",
                    "Nasiruddin Tughlaq",
                    "Firoz Shah"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Muhammad Shah",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq was originally named Muhammad Shah before becoming Sultan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which dynasty did Muhammad bin Tughlaq belong to?",
                  "options": ["Mamluk", "Tughlaq", "Khilji", "Sayyid"],
                  "answer": "Tughlaq",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq was a member of the Tughlaq dynasty."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major city did Muhammad bin Tughlaq shift the capital to during his reign?",
                  "options": ["Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore", "Daultabad"],
                  "answer": "Daultabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq shifted the capital from Delhi to Daultabad."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's major economic policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of Token Currency",
                    "Land Revenue Reform",
                    "Trade Expansion",
                    "Luxury Tax"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Introduction of Token Currency",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq introduced token currency as a major economic policy, which faced many challenges."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to conquer but faced significant resistance?",
                  "options": [
                    "South India",
                    "Central Asia",
                    "East India",
                    "North India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Central Asia",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to conquer Central Asia but faced significant resistance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main reason for the failure of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s token currency?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lack of Trust",
                    "Counterfeiting",
                    "Economic Disruption",
                    "Administrative Mismanagement"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Counterfeiting",
                  "explanation": "The token currency failed largely due to widespread counterfeiting and lack of trust."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which military campaign was led by Muhammad bin Tughlaq to expand his empire into the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "Campaign against Vijayanagara",
                    "Conquest of Golconda",
                    "Invasion of the Bahmani Sultanate",
                    "Campaign against the Cholas"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Invasion of the Bahmani Sultanate",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq led military campaigns to invade the Bahmani Sultanate in the Deccan region."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's controversial administrative decisions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Reforming the Military",
                    "Disbanding the Army",
                    "Introducing New Taxes",
                    "Redistributing Land"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Introducing New Taxes",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq introduced new taxes, which were often controversial and faced resistance."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who succeeded Muhammad bin Tughlaq as Sultan after his death?",
                  "options": [
                    "Firoz Shah Tughlaq",
                    "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
                    "Alauddin Khilji",
                    "Nasiruddin Tughlaq"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Firoz Shah Tughlaq",
                  "explanation": "Firoz Shah Tughlaq, Muhammad bin Tughlaq's cousin, succeeded him as Sultan after his death."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s shifting of the capital on his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Efficiency",
                    "Administrative Confusion",
                    "Economic Prosperity",
                    "Political Stability"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Confusion",
                  "explanation": "The shifting of the capital created significant administrative confusion and logistical challenges."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 2,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the reasons Muhammad bin Tughlaq shifted the capital to Daultabad?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strategic Location",
                    "Economic Opportunity",
                    "Religious Significance",
                    "Administrative Convenience"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strategic Location",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq shifted the capital to Daultabad for its strategic location, which was central in his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s token currency on trade?",
                  "options": [
                    "Boosted Trade",
                    "Disrupted Trade",
                    "No Impact",
                    "Increased Trade Volume"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Disrupted Trade",
                  "explanation": "The introduction of token currency disrupted trade due to lack of trust and widespread counterfeiting."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the predecessor of Muhammad bin Tughlaq on the throne?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
                    "Firoz Shah Tughlaq",
                    "Alauddin Khilji",
                    "Raja Ratan Singh"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq succeeded his father, Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq, as Sultan."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq focus on for expansion through military campaigns?",
                  "options": ["Deccan", "Punjab", "Bengal", "Gujarat"],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq focused on the Deccan region for expansion through military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the reasons Muhammad bin Tughlaq's economic policies faced criticism?",
                  "options": [
                    "Poor Implementation",
                    "Lack of Resources",
                    "Increased Taxes",
                    "Corruption"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Poor Implementation",
                  "explanation": "Many of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's economic policies faced criticism due to poor implementation and execution."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq handle dissent within his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Repression",
                    "Negotiation",
                    "Reform",
                    "Isolation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Repression",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq often dealt with dissent through repressive measures and strict control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reforms in the military?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of Army",
                    "Standardization of Weaponry",
                    "Training and Discipline",
                    "Military Infrastructure"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Army",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq focused on the expansion of his army to support his military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the fate of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's capital shift to Daultabad?",
                  "options": [
                    "Successful Transition",
                    "Failed Attempt",
                    "Partial Success",
                    "Temporary Relocation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Failed Attempt",
                  "explanation": "The capital shift to Daultabad was largely considered a failed attempt due to the logistical difficulties and administrative issues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which Persian historian wrote about Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign in detail?",
                  "options": [
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Ibn Sina",
                    "Ibn Khaldun",
                    "Ibn Battuta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Battuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Battuta wrote detailed accounts of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign in his travelogues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s notable policies regarding taxation?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Taxation on Agriculture",
                    "Tax Relief for Merchants",
                    "Uniform Tax Rates Across Empire",
                    "Tax Exemption for Nobility"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased Taxation on Agriculture",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq increased taxation on agriculture to raise revenue, which faced significant resistance."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Easy",
              "setNumber": 3,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which significant tax did Muhammad bin Tughlaq implement during his rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Agricultural Tax",
                    "Trade Tax",
                    "Luxury Tax",
                    "Property Tax"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Agricultural Tax",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq implemented a significant increase in agricultural tax to boost state revenue."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary challenge faced by Muhammad bin Tughlaq during his military expeditions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Logistical Issues",
                    "Insufficient Troops",
                    "Poor Strategy",
                    "Local Resistance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Logistical Issues",
                  "explanation": "Logistical issues were a primary challenge faced by Muhammad bin Tughlaq during his military expeditions."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What innovative measure did Muhammad bin Tughlaq take to improve the empire’s communication?",
                  "options": [
                    "Establishment of Relay Stations",
                    "Construction of New Roads",
                    "Introduction of Postal Service",
                    "Improvement of Telegraph System"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Establishment of Relay Stations",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq established relay stations to improve communication across his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which city did Muhammad bin Tughlaq temporarily make the capital before returning to Delhi?",
                  "options": ["Agra", "Lahore", "Daultabad", "Jaipur"],
                  "answer": "Daultabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq temporarily made Daultabad the capital before eventually returning to Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the outcome of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's policy of introducing a new currency system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Successful Implementation",
                    "Economic Stability",
                    "Currency Collapse",
                    "Increased Trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Collapse",
                  "explanation": "The policy of introducing a new currency system led to currency collapse due to counterfeiting and lack of trust."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies impact the trade routes in his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Improved Trade",
                    "Disrupted Trade",
                    "No Impact",
                    "Increased Revenue"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Disrupted Trade",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies, including the introduction of token currency, disrupted trade routes."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important event in Muhammad bin Tughlaq's rule marked the end of his ambitious expansion policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Rebellion in the Deccan",
                    "Failure of the Token Currency",
                    "Loss of Kashmir",
                    "Economic Crisis"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Rebellion in the Deccan",
                  "explanation": "The rebellion in the Deccan marked the end of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's ambitious expansion policies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for the failure of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s experiments in administrative reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Poor Execution",
                    "Resistance from Nobility",
                    "Lack of Resources",
                    "Economic Instability"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Poor Execution",
                  "explanation": "The primary reason for the failure of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s administrative reforms was poor execution and implementation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Who was the chief advisor to Muhammad bin Tughlaq known for his contributions to administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Khairuddin Tughlaq",
                    "Alauddin Tughlaq",
                    "Firoz Shah Tughlaq",
                    "Hafiz Ibn Hajar"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Khairuddin Tughlaq",
                  "explanation": "Khairuddin Tughlaq was known for his contributions to the administration during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's policies on the local artisans and craftsmen?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Patronage",
                    "Decreased Patronage",
                    "Economic Boom",
                    "Stagnation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decreased Patronage",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies led to decreased patronage for local artisans and craftsmen due to economic disruptions."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 4,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the major military campaigns led by Muhammad bin Tughlaq?",
                  "options": [
                    "Campaign in Bengal",
                    "Campaign in South India",
                    "Campaign in Tibet",
                    "Campaign in Kashmir"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Campaign in South India",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq undertook a major military campaign in South India, aiming to expand his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which significant decision regarding land revenue was made by Muhammad bin Tughlaq?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increase in Land Revenue",
                    "Introduction of Land Revenue Taxation",
                    "Exemption of Land Revenue for Farmers",
                    "Uniform Land Revenue Rates"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increase in Land Revenue",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq decided to increase land revenue, which faced backlash from the agrarian community."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the key criticisms of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Over-centralization",
                    "Lack of Military Discipline",
                    "Neglect of Trade Routes",
                    "Weak Foreign Policy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Over-centralization",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq was criticized for his over-centralization of administrative power, which led to inefficiencies."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural project is Muhammad bin Tughlaq most known for?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq is most known for initiating the construction of Tughlaqabad Fort, which is one of his significant architectural projects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major shift in the capital city did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "From Delhi to Agra",
                    "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                    "From Agra to Delhi",
                    "From Daulatabad to Delhi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to shift the capital from Delhi to Daulatabad in a bid to improve administrative efficiency, but the move led to significant challenges and was eventually reversed."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policy on the coinage system?",
                  "options": [
                    "Stable Currency",
                    "Devaluation of Currency",
                    "Introduction of Gold Coins",
                    "Standardization of Coins"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Devaluation of Currency",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policy on coinage led to the devaluation of currency due to counterfeiting and mismanagement."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary reason for Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s attempt to shift the capital to Daultabad?",
                  "options": [
                    "Administrative Efficiency",
                    "Strategic Advantage",
                    "Economic Benefits",
                    "Religious Reasons"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Strategic Advantage",
                  "explanation": "The move to Daultabad was primarily driven by the strategic advantage it offered, being centrally located."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which administrative reform by Muhammad bin Tughlaq was seen as ambitious but ultimately unsuccessful?",
                  "options": [
                    "Introduction of Token Currency",
                    "Establishment of New Tax System",
                    "Expansion of Bureaucracy",
                    "Centralization of Power"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Introduction of Token Currency",
                  "explanation": "The introduction of token currency was an ambitious reform that failed due to widespread issues with counterfeiting and trust."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule impact the relationship between the central authority and regional governors?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthened Central Authority",
                    "Weakened Central Authority",
                    "Enhanced Regional Autonomy",
                    "No Significant Change"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Weakened Central Authority",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies and centralization efforts often weakened the central authority in relation to regional governors."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the long-term impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies on the Delhi Sultanate?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthened the Sultanate",
                    "Led to Fragmentation",
                    "Promoted Economic Growth",
                    "Unified the Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Led to Fragmentation",
                  "explanation": "The long-term impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies contributed to the fragmentation and decline of the Delhi Sultanate."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 5,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural project is attributed to Muhammad bin Tughlaq in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                    "Humayun’s Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq commissioned the construction of Tughlaqabad Fort in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s approach towards administrative divisions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Fragmentation",
                    "Centralization",
                    "Decentralization",
                    "Federal System"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralization",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq favored centralization in his administrative divisions to consolidate control."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq address the challenge of a diverse empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Unified Legal System",
                    "Cultural Integration",
                    "Regional Autonomy",
                    "Centralized Administration"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Administration",
                  "explanation": "To address the diverse needs of his empire, Muhammad bin Tughlaq implemented centralized administration."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to control through military expeditions but faced significant resistance?",
                  "options": [
                    "North-West Frontier",
                    "Deccan Plateau",
                    "Eastern Bengal",
                    "Western India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Deccan Plateau",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq faced significant resistance during his military expeditions to the Deccan Plateau."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary focus of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s economic reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Currency Regulation",
                    "Land Taxation",
                    "Trade Policies",
                    "Agricultural Development"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Regulation",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq focused on currency regulation as part of his economic reforms, which faced challenges."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What was one of the significant reforms Muhammad bin Tughlaq implemented in the military?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of Military Units",
                    "Introduction of New Weaponry",
                    "Establishment of Military Training Camps",
                    "Uniform Recruitment Policies"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Military Units",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq focused on expanding military units to strengthen his control over the empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the result of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policy to control the nomadic tribes in the northern regions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Successful Integration",
                    "Increased Conflict",
                    "Peaceful Coexistence",
                    "Economic Benefits"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased Conflict",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policy to control nomadic tribes led to increased conflict and challenges."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which major shift in policy during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign had lasting consequences for his administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Capital Relocation",
                    "Currency Reform",
                    "Taxation Policy",
                    "Military Expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Reform",
                  "explanation": "The currency reform during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign had lasting consequences, including economic instability."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the general perception of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule among his contemporaries?",
                  "options": [
                    "Progressive",
                    "Tyrannical",
                    "Effective",
                    "Neutral"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tyrannical",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule was often perceived as tyrannical due to his autocratic policies and centralization efforts."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major shift in the capital city did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "From Delhi to Agra",
                    "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                    "From Agra to Delhi",
                    "From Daulatabad to Delhi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to shift the capital from Delhi to Daulatabad in a bid to improve administrative efficiency, but the move led to significant challenges and was eventually reversed."
                }
              ]
            },

            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 6,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's notable reforms in agriculture?",
                  "options": [
                    "Land Revenue Assessment",
                    "Introduction of Irrigation Systems",
                    "Redistribution of Land",
                    "Expansion of Agricultural Lands"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Land Revenue Assessment",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to reform land revenue assessment but faced challenges in implementation."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous traveler visited Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s court and recorded his experiences?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Battuta",
                    "Marco Polo",
                    "Al-Biruni",
                    "Xuanzang"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Battuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Battuta visited Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s court and recorded detailed observations in his travelogues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the region where Muhammad bin Tughlaq established a new capital?",
                  "options": ["Bijapur", "Srinagar", "Daultabad", "Hyderabad"],
                  "answer": "Daultabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq established Daultabad as his new capital."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which important project did Muhammad bin Tughlaq undertake to improve trade?",
                  "options": [
                    "Canal Construction",
                    "Road Building",
                    "Building of Ports",
                    "Establishment of Trade Guilds"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Road Building",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq undertook road-building projects to improve trade and connectivity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the significant consequences of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's token currency experiment?",
                  "options": [
                    "Economic Growth",
                    "Currency Collapse",
                    "Administrative Efficiency",
                    "Increased Trade"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Collapse",
                  "explanation": "The token currency experiment led to a collapse of the currency system due to widespread counterfeiting."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq's policies affect his popularity among the common people?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Favor",
                    "Decreased Favor",
                    "No Impact",
                    "Mixed Reactions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Decreased Favor",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies, such as the token currency and capital shift, led to decreased favor among the common people."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to control through administrative reforms?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Punjab", "Gujarat", "Deccan"],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to control the Deccan region through various administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major reason behind the failure of Muhammad bin Tughlaq's military expeditions?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lack of Resources",
                    "Poor Planning",
                    "Internal Rebellions",
                    "Overextended Empire"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Overextended Empire",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s military expeditions often failed due to the overextended nature of his empire and lack of resources."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Muhammad bin Tughlaq's approach to dealing with dissent and rebellion?",
                  "options": [
                    "Negotiation",
                    "Repression",
                    "Reform",
                    "Incorporation"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Repression",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq often dealt with dissent and rebellion through repressive measures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reforms had the longest-lasting impact on the administration?",
                  "options": [
                    "Military Reforms",
                    "Revenue Reforms",
                    "Judicial Reforms",
                    "Administrative Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Reforms",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s administrative reforms, although controversial, had a long-lasting impact on the structure of the empire."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Medium",
              "setNumber": 7,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the primary impact of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies on the common people?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Tax Burden",
                    "Improved Living Standards",
                    "Better Infrastructure",
                    "Enhanced Security"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased Tax Burden",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies often led to an increased tax burden on the common people."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq face significant unrest from due to his administrative policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "North India",
                    "South India",
                    "Eastern Bengal",
                    "Western India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "South India",
                  "explanation": "South India witnessed significant unrest due to Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s administrative policies and military campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the major failures of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s monetary reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "Lack of Public Trust",
                    "Successful Implementation",
                    "Increased Gold Reserves",
                    "Stable Currency"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Lack of Public Trust",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s monetary reforms faced major failure due to a lack of public trust in the new currency."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which aspect of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign is often criticized by historians?",
                  "options": [
                    "Economic Mismanagement",
                    "Military Aggression",
                    "Cultural Patronage",
                    "Diplomatic Success"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Economic Mismanagement",
                  "explanation": "Historians often criticize Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign for economic mismanagement and its adverse effects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was a major consequence of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s relocation of his capital?",
                  "options": [
                    "Administrative Disruption",
                    "Economic Growth",
                    "Increased Trade",
                    "Cultural Flourishing"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Disruption",
                  "explanation": "The relocation of the capital led to significant administrative disruption and challenges."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policies faced the most resistance from the nobility?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralization of Power",
                    "Military Campaigns",
                    "Economic Reforms",
                    "Currency Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralization of Power",
                  "explanation": "The centralization of power faced considerable resistance from the nobility during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule affect the political stability of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthened Stability",
                    "Weakened Stability",
                    "No Significant Change",
                    "Increased Unity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Weakened Stability",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule weakened the political stability of his empire due to various policy failures."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which architectural project is Muhammad bin Tughlaq most known for?",
                  "options": [
                    "Red Fort",
                    "Qutub Minar",
                    "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                    "Humayun's Tomb"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq is most known for initiating the construction of Tughlaqabad Fort, which is one of his significant architectural projects."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What major shift in the capital city did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt during his reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "From Delhi to Agra",
                    "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                    "From Agra to Delhi",
                    "From Daulatabad to Delhi"
                  ],
                  "answer": "From Delhi to Daulatabad",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to shift the capital from Delhi to Daulatabad in a bid to improve administrative efficiency, but the move led to significant challenges and was eventually reversed."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s attempts to address regional disparities?",
                  "options": [
                    "Relocation of Capital",
                    "New Taxation System",
                    "Regional Autonomy",
                    "Economic Incentives"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Relocation of Capital",
                  "explanation": "The relocation of the capital was one of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s attempts to address regional disparities."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 8,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was the name of the extensive army Muhammad bin Tughlaq raised for his campaigns in the Deccan?",
                  "options": [
                    "The Tughlaq Army",
                    "The Khilji Army",
                    "The Imperial Army",
                    "The Tughlaq Campaign Force"
                  ],
                  "answer": "The Imperial Army",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq raised an extensive Imperial Army for his Deccan campaigns."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region’s administration did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to standardize through his reforms?",
                  "options": ["Bengal", "Gujarat", "Deccan", "Punjab"],
                  "answer": "Deccan",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to standardize administration in the Deccan region through various reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What significant architectural project did Muhammad bin Tughlaq undertake in Delhi?",
                  "options": [
                    "Qutb Minar",
                    "Alai Darwaza",
                    "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                    "Red Fort"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Tughlaqabad Fort",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq undertook the construction of Tughlaqabad Fort in Delhi."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which famous Persian scholar and traveler visited the court of Muhammad bin Tughlaq?",
                  "options": [
                    "Ibn Khaldun",
                    "Al-Razi",
                    "Ibn Sina",
                    "Ibn Battuta"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Ibn Battuta",
                  "explanation": "Ibn Battuta visited Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s court and provided detailed observations of the Sultan's reign."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s approach to managing the vast distances of his empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Centralized Management",
                    "Local Autonomy",
                    "Delegated Administration",
                    "Regional Governors"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Management",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted centralized management to handle the vast distances of his empire."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which economic reform led to the largest backlash during Muhammad bin Tughlaq's reign?",
                  "options": [
                    "Token Currency",
                    "Land Revenue Reassessment",
                    "Tax Increase",
                    "Agricultural Reforms"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Token Currency",
                  "explanation": "The introduction of token currency led to significant backlash and was one of the most controversial reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major reason behind the failure of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s move to shift the capital?",
                  "options": [
                    "Logistical Challenges",
                    "Military Defeats",
                    "Administrative Overload",
                    "Economic Disruptions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Logistical Challenges",
                  "explanation": "The shift of the capital faced major logistical challenges and administrative issues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main focus of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s economic policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Taxation and Revenue",
                    "Trade and Commerce",
                    "Agriculture",
                    "Currency and Banking"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Taxation and Revenue",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq's economic policies primarily focused on taxation and revenue management."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule impact the local nobility?",
                  "options": [
                    "Strengthened their Power",
                    "Reduced their Influence",
                    "Increased Autonomy",
                    "No Significant Impact"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Reduced their Influence",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq's rule reduced the influence of the local nobility through centralization and administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the outcome of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s attempts to conquer the region of Kashmir?",
                  "options": [
                    "Successful Annexation",
                    "Partial Control",
                    "Failure and Withdrawal",
                    "Unsuccessful Negotiations"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Partial Control",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s attempts to conquer Kashmir resulted in partial control with limited success."
                }
              ]
            },
            {
              "level": "Hard",
              "setNumber": 9,
              "questions": [
                {
                  "question": "What was Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s policy regarding the taxation of the peasantry?",
                  "options": [
                    "Increased Taxes",
                    "Decreased Taxes",
                    "Uniform Tax Rates",
                    "Tax Exemption"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Increased Taxes",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq implemented an increase in taxes on the peasantry, leading to economic difficulties."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the major cause of dissatisfaction among the army during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Low Pay",
                    "Lack of Supplies",
                    "Overextension of Campaigns",
                    "Poor Leadership"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Low Pay",
                  "explanation": "Dissatisfaction among the army was caused by low pay and inadequate compensation during Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which region did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to consolidate through his administrative reforms?",
                  "options": [
                    "South India",
                    "North India",
                    "Central India",
                    "Western India"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Central India",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to consolidate control over Central India through various administrative reforms."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the notable aspects of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s diplomatic policies?",
                  "options": [
                    "Peace Treaties",
                    "Alliance with Neighboring States",
                    "Hostile Relations",
                    "Economic Diplomacy"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Hostile Relations",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s diplomatic policies often led to hostile relations with neighboring states."
                },
                {
                  "question": "How did Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempt to address the issue of local governance?",
                  "options": [
                    "Direct Control",
                    "Delegation to Local Leaders",
                    "Decentralization",
                    "Centralized Appointments"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Appointments",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq attempted to address local governance issues through centralized appointments."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which administrative change introduced by Muhammad bin Tughlaq was particularly controversial?",
                  "options": [
                    "Tax Reforms",
                    "Capital Shift",
                    "Currency Change",
                    "Military Expansion"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Change",
                  "explanation": "The change in currency introduced by Muhammad bin Tughlaq was particularly controversial and led to economic issues."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the main focus of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s military campaigns?",
                  "options": [
                    "Expansion of Territory",
                    "Defense of Borders",
                    "Repression of Rebels",
                    "Alliances with Other States"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Expansion of Territory",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s military campaigns were primarily focused on the expansion of territory."
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which policy of Muhammad bin Tughlaq led to significant economic difficulties for the common people?",
                  "options": [
                    "Currency Reforms",
                    "Increased Taxes",
                    "Land Redistribution",
                    "Trade Restrictions"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Currency Reforms",
                  "explanation": "The currency reforms led to significant economic difficulties for the common people due to instability."
                },

                {
                  "question": "What was a key factor in the decline of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule?",
                  "options": [
                    "Administrative Inefficiency",
                    "Military Defeats",
                    "Diplomatic Failures",
                    "Economic Prosperity"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Administrative Inefficiency",
                  "explanation": "Administrative inefficiency was a key factor in the decline of Muhammad bin Tughlaq’s rule."
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was one of the administrative strategies employed by Muhammad bin Tughlaq to manage his vast empire?",
                  "options": [
                    "Regional Delegation",
                    "Direct Control from Delhi",
                    "Establishment of New Provinces",
                    "Centralized Governance"
                  ],
                  "answer": "Centralized Governance",
                  "explanation": "Muhammad bin Tughlaq employed centralized governance as a strategy to manage his vast empire."
                }
              ]
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
